<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Page1 Department of Farm Machinery and Power</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Dr. BSKKV Dapoli</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Ph.D. Student Department of Farm Machinery and Power</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Farm Machinery and Power</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Dr. BSKKV Dapoli. 3 Technical Director</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep4">ASPEE Agricultural Research and Development Foundation</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Dr. BSKKV Dapoli. 2 Professor &amp; Head</addrLine>
									<country>Tansa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Managing Director</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">ASPEE Agricultural Research and Development Foundation</orgName>
								<address>
									<region>Tansa</region>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<idno type="ISSN">2582-8223</idno>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9114F3DBC65462149D1703AD8FC11E1B</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Introduction</head><p>Smart farmers made by adopting modern agriculture smart Agriculture Equipment, increasing income most farmers in India do farming through traditional methods. Due to which they get less crop production. As a result, their income starts declining. At the same time, the farmer increases his crop production by farming with the help of modern resources and automatic farming equipment. This gives him a good profit which increases his income.</p><p>Uses of this Agriculture Equipment will increase farmer production and profits Today, the farmers who are doing smart farming are making good profits by using new farming tools made with modern technology, which is increasing their income.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agricultural equipment used for farming</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Two stroke and four stroke sprayer pump (Agricultural Sprayer)</head><p>Agricultural sprayers used in agricultural work are available in 2 and 4 stroke spray pumps in the market. These have been launched in the market with some features. With this help, the farmer can easily spray insecticides on crops in his fields. Apart from this, they can also be used for the cleanliness of the environment. Talking about the price of 2 &amp; 4 Stroke power supply sprayer, it is available in an affordable price range at Rs. 9,000 -Rs. 22,000.   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Mini sprayer:</head><p>These sprayers are proving to be extremely useful for small farmers due to their manual operation. It costs neither engine nor electricity. For this reason, every small farmer can use them. There are many types of mini sprayers in the market which are available in 1.2 liters to 100 liters. The farmer can buy it from the market at very cheap prices according to its utility.</p><p>These mini sprayers help you to reduce the work of spreading the water from hands. With the adorable and handy design of mini sprayer, its price comes according to tank capacity. Here is the table below. Trailer mounted sprayers or tractor mounted sprayers are those used for mounting trailers and tractors. The farmer should choose this in view of its necessity and ease of use.</p><p>There are many types of tractor sprayers available in the market which is extremely useful.</p><p>According to its features and use, trailer sprayer price starts from Rs.1,00,000* to Rs. 3.00 lakh*. This price can vary on the brand, model, weight and tank capacity.  Manure Spreader is a machine that is used for agriculture purposes. In agriculture purposes, its main work is to distribute manure in a field as in a form of fertilizer. It is not working on its own engine but it is towed behind a tractor. This machine of agriculture is not so expensive; it is available at an affordable price starts from Rs. 55,000* to Rs. 5.00 lakh*, so every farmer can buy it in an easy way. It may vary on its capacity, brand, product type and material. In the price range, this farming technology can be adjusted in the budget of every farmer because its rate is cheaper.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The price of 2 &amp; 4 Stroke Sprayer Pump is very convenient and budget-friendly, also very easy to buy. 2 &amp; 4 Stroke spray pumps, both come in high quality, but 4 stroke spray pumps have twice the capacity than 2 stroke spray pumps. Now let's talk about 4 stroke spray pumps, these are high capacity pumps which have twice the capacity of 2 stroke spray pumps. Rajsan -89-1000, 4 stroke power supply spar is now available in the market for Rs 11,500 instead of 11,000, and Sparman-1000 power supply spar 12,000 for Rs 11,500. Thus, both these 2 and 4 stroke spray pumps (agricultural sprayers) have been reduced significantly, which the farmers can avail.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig.1 stroke sprayer pump Fig.2 4 stroke sprayer pump 2. Engine Driven Portable Agricultural Sprayer: A special sprayer is an engine-driven portable sprayer in agricultural sprayers. It is also a useful sprayer used in disinfectant and hygiene operations. It is shaped like an electric motor. It can be placed comfortably in a low place. It has been launched in two categories with many attractive features. It has an engine-powered portable sprayer and the other is a disinfectant / sanitary sprayer engine-driven portable sprayer.</figDesc><graphic coords="2,72.25,212.20,450.75,450.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 3</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Fig.3 Engine Driven Portable Agricultural SprayerThere are different rates in their market according to their special features, capacity and brand. With the engine-powered portable sprayers, it comes in a reasonable price range</figDesc><graphic coords="2,180.65,501.13,234.00,170.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig.4 Mini sprayer</figDesc><graphic coords="3,234.65,393.53,125.25,138.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig.6 Trailer sprayer</figDesc><graphic coords="4,154.40,405.74,286.50,165.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 8 Cultivator</figDesc><graphic coords="5,147.65,423.43,300.00,120.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 10 Manure spreader</figDesc><graphic coords="6,140.15,442.63,314.25,113.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 11 Rotary tiller</figDesc><graphic coords="7,150.65,155.85,330.00,141.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
