<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">6F734F38FC650A3E6D75DB5F72ED38FA</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:39+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cropping Pattern</head><p> The soils in the region falling in Eastern parts and Vindhyachal are alluvium-derived soils mostly khaddar (recent alluvium) and hangar (old alluvium). In some area the soil is highly calcareous.</p><p> The soils are loamy and high in organic matter content.</p><p> Rice, maize, pigeon pea, moong bean crops are common in kharif season.</p><p> In post-rainy (rabi) season wheat, lentil, Bengal gram, pea, and sesame and at some places groundnut is grown on residual soil moisture with one or two supplemental irrigation.</p><p> The important cash crops of the region are sugarcane, potato, tobacco, chillies, turmeric and coriander with supplemental irrigation. Rice-wheat cropping system is more predominant.</p><p> The dominant soil landscapes, representing the northern plains, constitute gently to very gently sloping lands. In some area the soil is highly calcareous.</p><p> The soils in general are neutral in reaction and have moderate clay and low organic carbon content.</p><p> Traditionally rain fed and irrigated agriculture is common.</p><p> The main crops grown are rice, maize, pigeon pea, sorghum, pearl millet, moong beans during kharif and wheat, Bengal gram, green peas, rapeseed and mustard and lentil during rabi season.</p><p> Sugarcane is the main cash crop. Rice-wheat cropping system is more predominant. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scope of Farm Mechanization</head><p> The State although highly populated, should progressively adopt power farming for timely and precise field operation at reduced costs and to maximize utilization efficiencies of costly inputs and for conservation of natural resources.</p><p> Precision land levelling and use of efficient irrigation equipment for economizing in water requirements of crops including diversification of crops suiting to water availability are important issues in the region.</p><p> Gradual increasing in farm power availability from the present level of 1.75 kW/ha to about 2 kW/ ha by 2020 is necessary for timely farm operations.</p><p> Mechanization of most of the agricultural operations through custom hiring of high capacity equipment is required so that marginal, small and medium categories of farmers can also take the advantage of mechanization.</p><p> Crop residue management for feed, fodder and energy is also important.</p><p> It is presumed that by 2020, about 70% of the tillage, land leveling, sowing/planting, irrigation and threshing of all the important crops will be fully mechanized and other operations for different types of crops will be mechanized upto about 25-30%. In U.P. sale of tractors is maximum. However, about more than 50 laser land leveler are being used on custom hire basis. Under this accidental insurance scheme, the state govt. will provide financial assistance to family of farmer's who die or become handicapped while working in fields. This new scheme will replace the existing U.P Mukhyamantri Krishak Durghatna Jivan Bima Yojana.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">U.P Mukhyamantri Kisan &amp; Sarvhit Bima Yojana 2020</head><p>U.P Mukhyamantri Kisan &amp; Sarvhit Bima Yojana will cover the incidents of road / air / rail accidents, collision, injury due to fall, leakage of gas, mongoose (Nevla), injury due to cylinder burst, dog bite, bite and attack by an wild animal, burning, drowning, flowing in the flood, cutting the hands and legs due to accident, earthquake and lightening. Upon implementation, this scheme will benefit 12 crore people in mostly rural areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4</head><p>U.P Fasal Rin Mochan Yojana 2018 U.P Fasal Rin Mochan Yojana or the loan waiver scheme is expected to benefit about 86 lakh farmers across the state whose loans would be waived off by the government. U.P farm loan waiver scheme or the fasal rin mochan yojana is the first official scheme launched by CM Yogi Aadityanath after coming to the power. By 17th of August 2019, all the eligible farmers should get the loan waiver and thereafter the loan waiver certificates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kisan Uday Yojana 2017</head><p>Subsequently, farmers will receive energy efficient pumps sets of different capacities. Accordingly, this scheme will save energy and helps in achieving the target of "Power for All". Under this scheme, the state govt. is going to provide 10 lakh pumps to the farmers till the financial year 2022.</p><p>This scheme is going to reduce the dependence of farmers on the conventional power pumps which utilizes 35% more energy. Moreover, farmers can turn the pump on or off through their cell phones. In addition to this, the farmers will also get free of cost maintenance for the upcoming 5 years. To enhance the income of betel producers and to improvise their financial condition.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dr. Roli Misra</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To introduce new developed technologies in betel production.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To increase the agricultural area of betel production.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To promote scientific biological methods over disease and pest control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To do reformation in grading, packing stores, transport and marketting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To increase the employment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To stop betel producers' migration in other areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To increase maximum income and employment in per unit area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To develop resources in quality betel production.</p><p>Dr. Roli Misra</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Net Area Irrigated by Different Sources in Uttar Pradesh (Area in Hectare)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Percentage of</cell></row><row><cell>Year</cell><cell>Canals</cell><cell>Tubewells and Wells</cell><cell>Tanks and Lake s</cell><cell>Other Sources</cell><cell>Total</cell><cell>Net Irrigated Area to Net</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Area Sown</cell></row><row><cell>1950-1951</cell><cell>1847122</cell><cell>2181449</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>811125</cell><cell>4839696</cell><cell>29.80</cell></row><row><cell>1960-1961</cell><cell>1992580</cell><cell>2387123</cell><cell>419069</cell><cell>245304</cell><cell>5044076</cell><cell>30.50</cell></row><row><cell>1970-1971</cell><cell>2497972</cell><cell>4033735</cell><cell>371303</cell><cell>315701</cell><cell>7218711</cell><cell>41.70</cell></row><row><cell>1980-1981</cell><cell>3178250</cell><cell>5799490</cell><cell>166364</cell><cell>308934</cell><cell>9453038</cell><cell>54.90</cell></row><row><cell>1990-1991</cell><cell>3192858</cell><cell>7054297</cell><cell>104437</cell><cell>309119</cell><cell>10660711</cell><cell>61.60</cell></row><row><cell>1995-1996</cell><cell>3089745</cell><cell>7826679</cell><cell>58100</cell><cell>772860</cell><cell>11747384</cell><cell>67.50</cell></row><row><cell>2000-2001</cell><cell>2748801</cell><cell>9378427</cell><cell>67145</cell><cell>206134</cell><cell>12400507</cell><cell>73.70</cell></row><row><cell>2001-2002</cell><cell>2718702</cell><cell>9904258</cell><cell>84261</cell><cell>121014</cell><cell>12828235</cell><cell>76.30</cell></row><row><cell>2002-2003</cell><cell>2630485</cell><cell>10012024</cell><cell>127281</cell><cell>78438</cell><cell>12848228</cell><cell>77.40</cell></row><row><cell>2003-2004</cell><cell>2767233</cell><cell>9357143</cell><cell>147461</cell><cell>955501</cell><cell>13227338</cell><cell>79.00</cell></row><row><cell>2004-2005</cell><cell>2691891</cell><cell>10144417</cell><cell>144834</cell><cell>137657</cell><cell>13118799</cell><cell>78.60</cell></row><row><cell>2005-2006</cell><cell>2652074</cell><cell>10218370</cell><cell>136897</cell><cell>67412</cell><cell>13074753</cell><cell>78.60</cell></row><row><cell>2006-2007</cell><cell>2613665</cell><cell>10488588</cell><cell>149166</cell><cell>61732</cell><cell>13313151</cell><cell>80.30</cell></row><row><cell>2007-2008</cell><cell>2657885</cell><cell>10580526</cell><cell>104780</cell><cell>41337</cell><cell>13084528</cell><cell>79.70</cell></row><row><cell>2008-2009</cell><cell>2666549</cell><cell>10599483</cell><cell>124659</cell><cell>44438</cell><cell>13435129</cell><cell>81.10</cell></row><row><cell>2009-2010</cell><cell>2558098</cell><cell>10646697</cell><cell>125891</cell><cell>52716</cell><cell>13383402</cell><cell>80.80</cell></row><row><cell>2010-2011</cell><cell>2538838</cell><cell>10760463</cell><cell>102340</cell><cell>38713</cell><cell>13440354</cell><cell>81.00</cell></row><row><cell>2011-2012</cell><cell>2554554</cell><cell>11009249</cell><cell>98710</cell><cell>146233</cell><cell>13808746</cell><cell>83.10</cell></row><row><cell>2012-2013</cell><cell>2541070</cell><cell>11215639</cell><cell>115775</cell><cell>56032</cell><cell>13928516</cell><cell>84.10</cell></row><row><cell>2013-2014</cell><cell>2556870</cell><cell>11291484</cell><cell>118910</cell><cell>59723</cell><cell>14026987</cell><cell>84.80</cell></row><row><cell>2014-2015</cell><cell>2481854</cell><cell>11657023</cell><cell>183647</cell><cell>66914</cell><cell>14389438</cell><cell>81.80</cell></row><row><cell>Dr. Roli Misra Dr. Roli Misra</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Source : Economics and Statistics Division, Govt. of Uttar Pradesh,</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Important Factors Explaining Crisis in Agriculture</head><label></label><figDesc>High indebtedness . It reduces cropping intensity (for want of resources), makes appropriate technology inaccessible, distress sales</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">Marketing Infrastructure Projects Sanctioned under National</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="5">Horticulture Mission (NHM) Scheme in Uttar Pradesh</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">(As on 31.03.2017)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Rs. in Lakh)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Rural Primary Market</cell><cell cols="2">Wholesale Market</cell><cell cols="2">Terminal Market Complex</cell></row><row><cell>State</cell><cell>No. of</cell><cell>Assistanc</cell><cell>No. of</cell><cell>Assistanc</cell><cell>No. of</cell><cell>Assistanc</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Project</cell><cell>e</cell><cell>Project</cell><cell>e</cell><cell>Project</cell><cell>e</cell></row><row><cell>Uttar Pradesh</cell><cell>4</cell><cell>90.84</cell><cell>11</cell><cell>1599.22</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>India</cell><cell>215</cell><cell>1141.75</cell><cell>68</cell><cell>7115.67</cell><cell>5</cell><cell>14814.00</cell></row><row><cell>Dr. Roli Misra Dr. Roli Misra</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>  High cost of cultivation and frequent crop failure  Declining crop yield  The falling profitability of agriculture  Low investment by public sector  Lack of proper irrigation facility especially in Bundelkhand.  Marginalization of farmers and low access to modern technology in Eastern belt. Sugarcane (the main commercial crop of Uttar Pradesh that covers more than 70 percent of net sown area in western region) growing farmers do not receive sufficient return from their cultivation, exploitation from mill owners and pending arrears  At the block or village level, market imperfection emerges as a main bottleneck in earning a remunerative price of the agricultural product. Price spread and farmers not getting remunerative prices Source :</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Ministry of Agriculture &amp; Farmers Welfare, Govt. of India. Recent Agricultural schemes in the State Sr.No.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Scheme Name</cell><cell>Year</cell><cell>Objective</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Under this U.P Easy Installment Scheme, farmers can</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>pay their outstanding tubewell electricity bills in</cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>U.P Kisan Asan Kist Yojana</cell><cell>2020</cell><cell>installments (kishts). As per the Energy department of Uttar Pradesh, the interest waiver on tubewells bill would also remain applicable. Each farmer can now</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>avail the benefits of aasaan kisht yojna by applying</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>online at the nearest CSC</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Mukhyamantri</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>Krishak Durghatna</cell><cell>2020</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Kalyan Yojana</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>latest techniques of irrigation. All the small and marginal farmers are given 90% of cost of these units in form of subsidy and 80% in case of other farmers.</figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>•</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Pradhan Mantri Krishi Sinchai Yojana (PMKSY) is going to be</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>implemented in all districts of UP. PMKSY will extend</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>coverage of irrigation 'Har Khet ko Pani' and improve water use</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>efficiency 'More Crop per Drop' in focused manner. Yogi</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Adityanath said that PM Krishi Sinchayee Yojna will ensure</cell></row><row><cell>Paan</cell><cell></cell><cell>water harvesting and increase productivity of farmers.</cell></row><row><cell>utpaadan</cell><cell>2016</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Pradhan Mantri yojna</cell><cell>2015</cell><cell>The state govt. of UP was already providing 35% subsidy in</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Krishi Sinchai Yojana sprinklers and other Dr. Roli Misra addition to prescribed subsidy on drip irrigation system,</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0">Dr. Roli Misra</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>The agricultural products include pulses, Kala Namak rice where as allied sectors include Wheat stalk handi craft ,Hing 'Asafoetida', Perfume( Attar), Banana fiber products,.One District One Product Scheme will boost the GDP of the state up to 2 percent. Govt. will implement this scheme with the collaboration of several industries working in various states. Furthermore, each district will get assigned a product under Ek Zila -Ek Utpadan Scheme.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phal Patti Development</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2017</head><p>• To get the direct environmental safety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>To make awareness in public regarding environmental safety.</p><p>• Solutions on nutritional safety.</p><p>• Updation in soil health.</p><p>• Enhancement in quality fruit production.</p><p>• Increase in the production capacity in the unproductive gardens by implementing the canopy management/renovation. Quality production and increase in productivity by adopting drip and sprinkler irrigation system in horticulture and agricultural crops.</p><p>• Use of water as per age of saplings and requirement.</p><p>• Encouraging ground water harvesting in view of day to day fall in water levels.</p><p>• Reduction in use of chemical fertilizers / pesticides by using drip irrigation at the root of saplings and fertilizers and anti pest/disease chemicals.</p><p>• Encouraging horticulture crops on uneven and muriate fields by adopting drip irrigation system.</p><p>Dr. Roli Misra</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suggested way out</head><p> Create supplementary employment opportunities in rural areas through development of rural non-farm sector.</p><p> Focus more on rural manufacturing and establishing more specifically agro-based industries  Accelerating public investment so that private invested also gets a boast up.</p><p> More effective agricultural Price Policy.</p><p> Micro irrigation and warehousing need to be the focus areas of the government investment in the state.</p><p> Promotion of Farmer Producers Organization (FPO).</p><p> Improved public procurement and agricultural marketing system would improve farmers income  Adoption of hybrid and improved seeds would significantly increase crop productivity.</p><p> One district one product (ODOP) scheme can be used to promote food processing sector in the state.</p><p> A good marketing infrastructure, which includes marketing yard, storage facility. Dr. Roli Misra</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
