<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Www</forename><surname>Hortiagri</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Com</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Www</forename><forename type="middle">Hortiagri</forename><surname>Com</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><surname>Hortiagri</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">691D182825D91B7B1F842AD364495BAB</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Grain discolouration -Drechslera oryzae</term>
					<term>D. rostratum</term>
					<term>D.tetramera</term>
					<term>Curvularia lunata</term>
					<term>Trichoconis padwickii</term>
					<term>Sarocladium oryzae</term>
					<term>Alternaria tenuis</term>
					<term>Fusarium moniliforme</term>
					<term>Cladosporium herbarum</term>
					<term>Epicoccum purpurascens</term>
					<term>Cephalosporium sp.</term>
					<term>Phoma sp.</term>
					<term>Nigrospora sp</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The grains may be infected by various organisms before or after harvesting causing discoloration, the extent of which varies according to season and locality. The infection may be external or internal causing discoloration of the glumes or kernels or both. Dark brown or black spots appear on the grains.</p><p>The discoloration may be red, yellow, orange, pink or black, depending upon the organism involved and the degree of infection. This disease is responsible for quantitative and qualitative losses of grains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Micro and macro conidia</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Diseases of Rice Fungal Diseases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blast -Pyricularia oryzae (Syn: P. grisea) (Sexual stage: Magnaporthe grisea)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus attacks the crop at all stages of crop growth. Symptoms appear on leaves, nodes, rachis, and glumes. On the leaves, the lesions appear as small bluish green flecks, which enlarge under moist weather to form the characteristic spindle shaped spots with grey centre and dark brown margin (Leaf blast).</p><p>The spots coalesce as the disease progresses and large areas of the leaves dry up and wither. Spots also appear on sheath. Severely infected nursery and field appear as burnt. Black lesions appear on nodes girdling them. The affected nodes may break up and all the plant parts above the infected nodes may die (nodal blast).</p><p>During flower emergence, the fungus attacks the peduncle and the lesion turns to brownish-black which is referred to as rotten neck / neck rot / panicle blast (neck blast).</p><p>In early neck infection, grain filling does not occur while in late infection, partial grain filling occurs. Small brown to black spots may also be observed on glumes of the heavily infected panicles. The pathogen causes yield losses ranging from 30-61 per cent depending upon the stages of infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The mycelium is hyaline to olivaceous and septate. Conidia are produced in clusters on long septate, olivaceous conidiophores. Conidia are pyriform to ellipsoid, attached at the broader base by a hilum. Conidia are hyaline to pale olive green, usually 3 celled. The perfect state of the blast Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri fungus is M. grisea producing perithecia. The ascospores are hyaline, fusiform, 4 celled and slightly curved.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Intermittent drizzles, cloudy weather, more of rainy days, longer duration of dew high relative humidity (93-99 per cent).</p><p>• Low night temperature (between 15-20˚C or less than 26˚C).</p><p>• Aavailability of collateral hosts and excess dose of nitrogen.</p><p>Forecast for rice blast can be made on the basis of minimum night temperature range of 20-26˚C in association with a high relative humidity of 90 per cent and above lasting for a period of a week or more during any of the three susceptible phases of crop growth, viz., seedling stage, post transplanting tillering stage and neck emergence stage. In Japan, the first leaf blast forecasting model was developed named as BLAST. Later several other models have also been developed namely, PYRICULARIA, PYRIVIEW, BLASTAM, EPIBLA and PBLAST.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The disease spreads primarily through airborne conidia since spores of the fungus present throughout the year. Mycelium and conidia in the infected straw and seeds are major sources of inoculum. Irrigation water may carry the conidia to different fields.The fungus also survives on collateral hosts viz., Panicum repens, Digitaria marginata, Brachiaria mutica, Leersia hexandra and Echinochloa crusgalli.</p><p>Conidia and Conidiophore of P. grisea</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri Spores land on leaves, germinate, penetrate the leaf, and cause a lesion 4 days later; more spores are produced in as little as 6 days. Infections from spores arriving from a distance are termed primary infections.</p><p>Primary infections generally result in a few widely scattered spots on leaves. Spores arising from the primary infections are capable of causing many more infections. This cycling is called secondary spread. Secondary spread is responsible for the severe epidemics of blast in fields and localized areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Grow resistant to moderately resistant varieties CO47, IR 20, ADT36, ADT39, ASD 18 and IR64. Avoid cultivation of highly susceptible varieties viz., IR50 and TKM6 in disease favourable season.</p><p>• Remove and destory the weed hosts in the field bunds and channels.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Captan or Thiram or Carbendazim or Tricyclazole at 2 g/kg. or</p><p>Pseudomonas fluorescens @ 10g/kg of seed. Spray the nursery with carbendazim 500mg/L or tricyclazole 300mg/L.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 6</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• Spray the main field with Edifenphos 500 ml or Carbendazim 500 g or Tricyclazole 500</p><p>g or Iprobenphos (IBP) 500 ml /ha.</p><p>Brown Spot -Helminthosporium oryzae (Syn: Drechslera oryzae; Bipolaris oryzae) (Sexual stage: Cochliobolus miyabeanus)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus attacks the crop from seedling to milky stage in main field. Symptoms appear as minute spots on the coleoptile, leaf blade, leaf sheath, and glume, being most prominent on the leaf blade and glumes.</p><p>The spots become cylindrical or oval, dark brown with yellow halo later becoming circular. Several spots coalesce and the leaf dries up. The seedlings die and affected nurseries can be often recognised from a distance by scorched appearance. Dark brown or black spots also appear on glumes leading to grain discoloration. It causes failure of seed germination, seedling mortality and reduces the grain quality and weight.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen Leaf symptoms Glume infection</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Bipolaris oryzae produces brown septate mycelium. Conidiophores arise singly or in small groups. They are geniculate, brown in colour. Conidia are usually curved with a bulged center and tapered ends. They are pale to golden brown in colour and are 6-14 septate. The perfect stage of the fungus is C. miyabeanus.</p><p>It produces perithecia with asci containing 6-15 septate, filamentous or long cylinderical, hyaline to pale olive green ascospores. The fungus produces terpenoid phytotoxins called ophiobolin A (or Cochliobolin A), ophiobolin B (or cochliobolin B) and ophiobolin I.</p><p>Ophiobolin A is most toxic. These breakdown the protein fragment of cell wall resulting in partial disruption of integrity of cell.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Temperature of 25-30˚C with relative humidity above 80 per cent are highly favourable.</p><p>• Excess of nitrogen aggravates the disease severity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>Infected seeds and stubbles are the most common source of primary infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Coidia and Conidiophore</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The conidia present on infected grain and mycelium in the infected tissue are viable for 2 to 3 years. Airborne conidia infect the plants both in nursery and in main field.</p><p>The fungus also survives on collateral hosts like Leersia hexandra and Echinochloa colonum. The brown spot fungus is normally present in areas with a long history of rice culture.</p><p>Airborne spores that are capable of causing infection are produced in infested debris and older lesions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Field sanitation-removal of collateral hosts and infected debris from the field.</p><p>• Use of slow release nitrogenous fertilizers is advisable.</p><p>• Grow tolerant varieties viz., Co44 and Bhavani.</p><p>• Use disease free seeds.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Thiram or Captan at 4 g/kg. Spray the nursery with Edifenphos 40 ml or Mancozeb 80 g for 20 cent nursery.</p><p>• Spray the crop in the main field with Edifenphos 500 ml or Mancozeb 2 kg/ha when grade reaches 3. If needed repeat after 15 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Narrow brown leaf spot -Cercospora janseana (Sexual stage: Sphaerulina oryzina)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus produces short, linear brown spots mostly on leaves and also on sheaths, pedicels and glumes. The spots appear in large numbers during later stages of crop growth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Conidiophores are produced in groups and brown in colour. Conidia are hyaline or sub hyaline, cylindrical and 3-5 septate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>Spray Carbendazim 500 g or Mancozeb 2 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sheath rot -Sarocladium oryzae (Syn: Acrocylindrium oryzae)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initial symptoms are noticed only on the upper most leaf sheath enclosing young panicles. The flag leaf sheath show oblong or irregular greyish brown spots. They enlarge and develop grey centre and brown margins covering major portions of the leaf sheath.</p><p>The young panicles remain within the sheath or emerge partially. The panicles rot and abundant whitish powdery fungal growth is seen inside the leaf sheath.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces whitish, sparsely branched, septate mycelium. Conidia are hyaline, smooth, single celled and cylindrical in shape.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Closer planting</p><p>• High doses of nitrogen</p><p>• High humidity and temperature around 25-30˚C</p><p>• Injuries made by leaf folder, brown plant hopper and mites increase infection</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The disease spreads mainly through air-borne conidia and also seed-borne. Primary source of inoculum is by means of infected plant debris. Secondary spread is by means of air borne conidia produced on the leaf sheath.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Spray Carbendazim 500g or Edifenphos 1L or Mancozeb 2 kg/ha at boot leaf stage and 15 days later.</p><p>• Soil application of gypsum (500 kg/ha) in two splits.</p><p>• Application of Neem Seed Kernal Extract (NSKE) 5% or neem oil 3 % or Ipomoea leaf powder extract 25 Kg/ha. First spray at boot leaf stage and second 15 days later.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sheath blight -Rhizoctonia solani (Sexual stage: Thanetophorus cucumeris)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus affects the crop from tillering to heading stage. Initial symptoms are noticed on leaf sheaths near water level. On the leaf sheath oval or elliptical or irregular greenish grey spots are formed. As the spots enlarge, the centre becomes greyish white with an irregular blackish brown or purple brown border.</p><p>Lesions on the upper parts of plants extend rapidly coalesing with each other to cover entire tillers from the water line to the flag leaf. The presence of several large lesions on a leaf sheath usually causes death of the whole leaf, and in severe cases all the leaves of a plant may be blighted</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 11</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>The infection extends to the inner sheaths resulting in death of the entire plant. Older plants are highly susceptible. Plants heavily infected in the early heading and grain filling growth stages produce poorly filled grain, especially in the lower part of the panicle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces septate mycelium which are hyaline when young, yellowish brown when old. It produces large number of spherical brown sclerotia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High relative humidity (96-97 per cent), high temperature (30-32˚C).</p><p>• Closer planting.</p><p>• Heavy doses of nitrogenous fertilizers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The pathogen can survive as sclerotia or mycelium in dry soil for about 20 months but for 5-8 months in moist soil. Sclerotia spread through irrigation water. The fungus has a wide host range.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Grow resistant varieties like Mansarovar, Swarau Dhan, Pankaj etc.</p><p>• Apply organic amendments viz., neem cake @ 150Kg/ha or FYM 12.5 tons/ha. Avoid flow of irrigation water from infected fields to healthy fields.</p><p>• Deep ploughing in summer and burning of stubbles.</p><p>• Spray Carbendazim 500 g/ha</p><p>• Soil application of P.fluorescens @ of 2.5 kg/ha after 30 days of transplanting (product should be mixed with 50 kg of FYM/Sand and applied).</p><p>• Foliar spray P.fluorescens at 0.2% at boot leaf stage and 10 days later False smut -Ustilaginoidea virens (Syn: Claviceps oryzae -sativa)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri 13</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>The fungus transforms individual ovaries / grains into greenish spore balls of velvetty appearance. Only a few spikelets in a panicle are affected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Chlamydospores are formed as spore balls which are spherical to elliptical, warty and olivaceous.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>Grasses and wild rice species are alternate hosts. The main source of inoculum is airborne spores. Ascospores produced from sclerotia act as primary source of infection while chalmydospores are secondary source of infection. Chlamydospores are air -borne, abundant at heading stage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable conditions</head><p>• Rainfall and cloudy weather during flowering and maturity</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spore balls</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Udbatta disease -Ephelis oryzae (Sexual stage: Balansia oryzae-sativa)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Symptoms appear at the time of panicle emergence. The entire ear head is converted into a straight compact cylindrical black spike like structure since the infected panicle is matted together by the fungal mycelium. The spikelets are cemented to the central rachis and the size is remarkably reduced. The entire spike is covered by greyish stroma with convex pycnidia immersed inside.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Pycnidiospores are hyaline, needle shaped and 4-5 celled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• The pathogen is internally seed borne.</p><p>• Hot water seed treatment at 45˚C for 10 min. effectively controls the disease.</p><p>• Removal of collateral hosts Isachne elegans, Eragrostis tenuifolia and Cynadon dactylon.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stackburn disease -Trichoconis padwickii (Syn: Alternaria padwickii)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Leaves and ripening grains are affected. On leaves circular to oval spots with dark brown margins are formed. The center of the spot turns light brown or white with numerous minute dots. On the glumes reddish brown spots appear. The kernels may shrivel and become brittle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Conidia are elongated with a long beak at the tip, 3 to 5 septate, thick walled and constricted at the septa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Thiram or Captan or Mancozeb at 2g/kg.</p><p>• Hot water treatment at 54˚ C for 15 minutes is also effective.</p><p>• Burn the stubbles and straw in the field. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bunt or Kernel</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>White to greyish hyphae, spherical black and shiny sclerotia, visible to naked eyes as black masses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Infestation of leaf hoppers and stem borer.</p><p>• High doses of nitrogenous fertilizers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The sclerotia survive in stubbles and straw those are carried through irrigation water. The fungus over winters and survives for long periods as sclerotia in the upper layers (2-3 inches) of the soil profile. The half-life of sclerotia in the field is about 2 years. Viable sclerotia have been found in fields for up to 6 years after a rice crop. The sclerotia are buoyant and float to the surface of floodwater where they contact, germinate, and infect rice tillers near the water line.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep ploughing in summer and burning stubbles to eliminate sclerotia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Use of balanced application of fertilizer.</p><p>• Avoid flow of irrigation water from infected to healthy fields.</p><p>• Draining irrigation water and letting soil to dry.</p><p>Foot rot or Bakanae disease -Fusarium moniliforme (Sexual stage: Gibberella fujikuroi)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Infected seedlings in nursery are lean and lanky, much taller and die after some time. In the main field, the affected plants have tall lanky tillers with longer internodes and aerial adventitious roots from the nodes above ground level. The root system is fibrous and bushy. The plants are killed before earhead formation or they produce only sterile spikelets. When the culm is split open white mycelial growth can be seen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Fungus produces both macroconidia and microconidia. Microconidia are hyaline, single celled and oval. Macroconidia are slightly sickle shaped, and two to five celled.The fungus produces the phytotoxin , fusaric acid, which is non-host specific.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High humidity and cloudy weather during heading stage</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The disease spreads mainly through air-borne conidia and the fungus survives as parasite and saprophyte in the infected grains, plant debris and also on other crop debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Pre and post-harvest measures should be taken into account for prevention of grain discolouration.</p><p>• Spray the crop at boot leaf stage and at 50% flowering with Carbendazim + Mancozeb</p><p>(1:1) @ 0.2%.</p><p>• Store the grains with 13.5-14% moisture content.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial Disesases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial leaf blight -Xanthomonas oryzae pv. oryzae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease is usually noticed at the time of heading but it can occur earlier also.</p><p>Seedlings in the nursery show circular, yellow spots in the margin, that enlarge, coalesce leading to drying of foliage. "Kresek" symptom is seen in seedlings, 1-2 weeks after transplanting. The bacteria enter through the cut wounds in the leaf tips, become systemic and cause death of entire seedling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>In grown up plants water soaked, translucent lesions appear near the leaf margin. The lesions enlarge both in length and width with a wavy margin and turn straw yellow within a few days, covering the entire leaf. As the disease advances, the lesions cover the entire lamina which turns white or straw coloured. Milky or opaque dew drops containing bacterial masses are formed on young lesions in the early morning. They dry up on the surface leaving a white encrustation. The affected grains have discoloured spots. If the cut end of leaf is dipped in water, it becomes turbid because of bacterial ooze.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The bacterium is aerobic, gram negative, non spore forming, rod with size ranging from 1-2 x 0.8-1.0 m with monotrichous polar flagellum. Bacterial colonies are circular, convex with entire margins, whitish yellow to straw yellow colored and opaque.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable Conditions</head><p>• Clipping of tip of the seedling at the time of transplanting</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Kresek symptom Leaf blight symptom</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterium</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Heavy rain, heavy dew, flooding, deep irrigation water</p><p>• Severe wind and temperature of 25-30 C</p><p>• Application of excessive nitrogen, especially late top dressing</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The infected seeds as a source of inoculum may not be important since the bacteria decrease rapidly and die in the course of seed soaking. The pathogen survives in soil and in the infected stubbles and on collateral hosts Leersia spp., Plantago najor, Paspalum dictum, and</p><p>Cyanodon dactylon. The pathogen spreads through irrigation water and also through rain storms.</p><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Burn the stubbles.</p><p>• Use optimum dose of fertilizers.</p><p>• Avoid clipping of tip of seedling at the time of transplanting.</p><p>• Avoid flooded conditions. Remove weed hosts.</p><p>• Grow resistant cultivars IR 20 and TKM 6.</p><p>• Spray Streptomycin sulphate and tetracycline combination 300g + Copper oxychloride 1.25 Kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial leaf streak -Xanthomonas oryzae pv. oryzicola</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Fine translucent streaks are formed on the veins and the lesions enlarge lengthwise and infect larger veins and turn brown. On the surface of the lesions, bacterial ooze out and form small yellow band-like exudates under humid conditions. In severe cases the leaves dry up.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Burn the stubbles.</p><p>• Use optimum dose of fertilizers.</p><p>• Avoid clipping of tip of seedling at the time of transplanting.</p><p>• Avoid flooded conditions.</p><p>• Remove weed hosts. Grow resistant cultivars IR 20 and TKM 6. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Field sanitation, removal of weed hosts of the virus and vectors.</p><p>• Grow disease tolerant cultivars like Pankhari203, BM66, BM68, Latisail, Ambemohar102, Kamod253, IR50 and Co45.</p><p>• Control the vectors in the nursery by application of Carbofuran 170 g/cent 10 days after sowing to control hoppers.</p><p>• Spray Phosphomidan 500 ml or Monocrotophos 1lit/ha (2 ml/litre) or Neem oil 3% or NSKE 5% to control the vector in the main field 15 and 30 days after transplanting.</p><p>• Set up light traps to monitor the vector population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rice Grassy stunt disease -Rice grassy stunt tenuivirus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Plants are markedly stunted with excessive tillering and an erect growth habit. Leaves become narrow, pale green with small rusty spots. May produce a few small panicles which bear dark brown unfilled grains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Rice grassy stunt tenuivirus, flexuous, filamentous 950-1350nm long x 6nm wide, ssRNA genome</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>Disease spreads by the brown plant hopper, Nilaparvata lugens, in a persistent manner having a latent period of 5 to 28 days in the vector. Ratoon crop and presence of vector perpetuate the disease from one crop to other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rice dwarf -Rice dwarf virus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Infected plants show stunted growth, reduced tillering and root system. Leaves show chlorotic specks turning to streaks along the veins. In early stage of infection no ear heads formed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>• The virus is spherical, 70nm diameter with an envelope, dsRNA genome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>Spreads by leafhopper feeding by Nephotettix cincticeps, Recllia dorsalis and N. nigropictus in a persistent manner. The transmission is transovarial through eggs. Gramineous</p><p>weeds Echinochloa crusgalli and Panicum miliaceaum serve as source of inoculum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Destory weed host that serve as source of inoculum</p><p>• Spray Phosphamidon or Fenthinon 500 ml or Monocrotophos 1 lit/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rice ragged stunt disease -Rice ragged stunt virus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>• Formation of ragged leaves with irregular margins, vein swelling, enations on leaf veins may be formed</p><p>• Stunting of plants, delayed flowering, production of nodal branches and incomplete emergence of panicles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>• Spherical virus (Figivirus), 65 nm diameter, dsRNA genome</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>Spreads through brown planthopper, Nilaparvata lugens transmitted in a persistent manner. Multiplies in the vector, latent period of 3 to 35 days, but not transmitted congenitally</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rice yellow dwarf disease -Rice yellow dwarf virus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Prominent stunting of plants and excessive tillering are the characteristic symptoms of the disease. Leaves yellowish green to whitish green, become soft and droop. Plants usually remain sterile but sometimes may produce small panicles with unfilled grains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>• Caused by a phytoplasma (rice yellow dwarf phytoplasma designated as a novel taxon, 'Candidatus Phytoplasma oryzae')</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The disease is transmitted by leafhopper vectors Nephotettix sp. Nephotettix with a latent period of 25-30 days in the vector. The pathogen survives on several grass weeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep ploughing during summer months and burning of stubbles.</p><p>• Rice varieties IR62 and IR64 are moderately resistant to the disease.</p><p>• The management practices followed for Rice Tungro disease holds good for this disease also.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri Oospores are spherical, thick walled and deep brown in colour.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Diseases of Sorghum</head><note type="other">Downy</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Maximum sporulation takes place at 100 per cent relative humidity.</p><p>• Optimum temperature for sporulation is 21-23˚C during night.</p><p>• Light drizzling accompanied by cool weather is highly favourable.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The primary infection is by means of oospores present in the soil which germinate and initiate the systemic infection. Oospores persist in the soil for several years. Secondary spread is by air-borne sporangia. Presence of mycelium of the fungus in the seeds of systemically infected plants is also a source of infection.The disease has been known to occur through a collateral host, Heteropogen centortus on which the fungus perpetuates of the host. The breakdown of tissue causes shredding. The oospores either fall to the soil or are wind blown, often within host tissue.</p><p>They can remain viable in the soil for 5-10 years. Conidia are formed at night in large numbers.</p><p>The optimum temperature for production is 20-23 0 C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sporangia and sporangiophores</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Crop rotation with other crops viz., pulses and oilseeds.</p><p>• Avoid the secondary spread of the disease by roguing out the infected plants since the wind plays a major role in the secondary spread of the disease.</p><p>• Grow moderately resistant varieties like Co25 and Co26.</p><p>• Seed treatment with Metalaxyl at 6 g/kg of seed.</p><p>• Spray Metalaxyl 500 g or Mancozeb 2 kg or Ziram 1 kg or Zineb 1kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf blight -Exerohilum turcicum (Syn: Helminthosporium turcicum)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The pathogen also causes seed rot and seedling blight of sorghum. The disease appears as small narrow elongated spots in the initial stage and in due course they extend along the length of the leaf. On older plants, the typical symptoms are long elliptical necrotic lesions, straw coloured in the centre with dark margins.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>The straw coloured centre becomes darker during sporulation. The lesions can be several centimeters long and wide. Many lesions may develop and coalesce on the leaves, destroying large areas of leaf tissue, giving the crop a burnt appearance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The mycelium is localised in the infected lesion. Conidiophores emerge through stomata and are simple, olivaceous, septate and geniculate. Conidia are olivaceous brown, 3-8 septate and thick walled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Cool moist weather.</p><p>• High humidity (90 per cent)</p><p>• High rainfall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen is found to persist in the infected plant debris. Seed borne conidia are responsible for seedling infection. Secondary spread is through wind-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Use disease free seeds.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Captan or Thiram at 4 g/kg.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 1.25 kg or Captafol 1 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rectangular Leaf spot -Cercospora sorghi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The symptoms appear as small leaf spots which enlarge to become rectangular lesions (which can be 5-15 mm long by 2 to 5 mm wide) on the leaf and leaf sheath. Usually the lower</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri leaves are first attacked. The lesions are typical dark red to purplish with lighter centers. The lesions are mostly isolated and limited by veins. The colour of the spots varies from red, purple, brown or dark depending upon the variety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Mycelium of the fungus is hyaline and septate. Conidiophores emerge in clusters through stomata, which are brown and simple, rarely branched. Conidia are hyaline, thin walled, 2-13 celled and long obclavate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Cool moist weather.</p><p>• High humidity (90 per cent)</p><p>• High rainfall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The conidia survive up to 5 months. The disease spreads through air-borne and seedborne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Use disease free seeds.</p><p>• Treat the seed with Captan or Thiram at 4 g/kg.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 2 kg /ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anthracnose and red rot -Colletotrichum graminicolum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus causes both leaf spot (anthracnose) and stalk rot (red rot). The disease appears as small red coloured spots on both surfaces of the leaf. The centre of the spot is white in colour encircled by red, purple or brown margin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Numerous small black dots like acervuli are seen on the white surface of the lesions. Red rot can be characterized externally by the development of circular cankers, particularly in the inflorescence. Infected stem when split open shows discoloration, which may be continuous over a large area or more generally discontinuous giving the stem a marbeled appearance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The mycelium of the fungus is localised in the spot. Acervuli with setae arise through epidermis. Conidia are hyaline, single celled, vacuolate and falcate in shape.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Continuous rain.</p><p>• Temperature of 28-30˚C.</p><p>• High humidity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The disease spread by means of seed-borne and air-borne conidia and also through the infected plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Captan or Thiram at 4 g/kg.</p><p>• Spray the crop with Mancozeb 2 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Rust -Puccinia purpurea</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus affects the crop at all stages of growth. The first symptoms are small flecks on the lower leaves (purple, tan or red depending upon the cultivar). Pustules (uredosori) appear on both surfaces of leaf as purplish spots which rupture to release reddish powdery masses of uredospores. Teliopores develop later sometimes in the old uredosori or in telisori, which are darker and longer than the uredosori. The pustules may also occur on the leaf sheaths and on the stalks of inflorescence.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The uredospores are pedicellate, elliptical or oval, thin walled, echinulated and darkbrown in colour. The teliospores are reddish or brown in colour and two celled, rounded at the apex with one germ pore in each cell. The teliospores germinate and produce promycelium and basidiospores. Basidiospores infect Oxalis corniculata ) where pycnial and aecial stages arise.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Low temperature of 10 to 12˚C favours teliospore germination.</p><p>• A spell of rainy weather favours the onset of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The uredospores survive for a short time in soil and infected debris. Presence of alternate host helps in perpetuation of the fungus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms on leaves and stalk</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove the alternate host Oxalis comiculata.</p><p>• Spray the crop with Mancozeb at 2 kg/ha.</p><p>Grain smut/Kernel smut / Covered smut / Short smut -Sphacelotheca sorghi</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The individual grains are replaced by smut sori. The sori are oval or cyclindrical and are covered with a tough creamy skin (peridium) which often persists unbroken up to thrashing.</p><p>Ratoon crops exhibit higher incidence of disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Loose smut/ kernel smut -Sphacelotheca cruenta</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The affected plants can be detected before the ears come out. They are shorter than the healthy plants with thinner stalks and marked tillering. The ears come out much earlier than the healthy. The glumes are hypertrophied and the earhead gives a loose appearance than healthy.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The sorus is covered by a thin membrane which ruptures very early, exposing the spores even as the head emerges from the sheath.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Long smut -Tolyposporium ehrenbergii</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>This disease is normally restricted to a relatively a small proportion of the florets which are scattered on a head. The sori are long, more or less cylindrical, elongated, slightly curved with a relatively thick creamy-brown covering membrane (peridium). The peridium splits at the apex to release black mass of spores (spore in groups of balls) among which are found several dark brown filaments which represent the vascular bundles of the infected ovary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptom</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Head smut -Sphacelotheca reiliana</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The entire head is replaced by large sori. The sorus is covered by a whitish grey membrane of fungal tissue, which ruptures, before the head emerges from the boot leaf to expose a mass of brown smut spores. Spores are embedded in long, thin, dark colored filaments which are the vascular bundles of the infected head.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management for all smuts</head><p>• Treat the seed with Captan or Thiram at 4 g/kg.</p><p>• Use disease free seeds.</p><p>• Follow crop rotation.</p><p>• Collect the smutted ear heads in cloth bags and bury in soil.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ergot or Sugary disease -Sphacelia sorghi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease is confined to individual spikelets. The first symptom is the secretion of honey dew from infected florets. Under favourable conditions, long, straight or curved, cream to light brown, hard sclerotia develop. Often the honey dew is colonised by Crerebella sorghivulgaris which gives the head a blackened appearance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces septate mycelium. The honey dew is a concentrated suspension of conidia, which are single celled, hyaline, elliptic or oblong.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• A period of high rainfall and high humidity during flowering season.</p><p>• Cool night temperature and cloudy weather aggravate the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The primary source of infection is through the germination of sclerotia which release ascospores that infect the ovary. The secondary spread takes place through air and insect-borne conidia. Rain splashes also help in spreading the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Adjust the date of sowing so that the crop does not flower during September-October when high rainfall and high humidity favor the disease.</p><p>• Spray any one of the following fungicides viz., Mancozeb 2 kg/ha (or) Carbendazim at 500 g/ha at emergence of ear head (5-10 per cent flowering stage) followed by a spray at 50 per cent flowering and repeat the spray after a week, if necessary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Head mould/Grain mould/Head blight</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptom</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>More than thirty two genera of fungi were found to occur on the grains of sorghum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>If rains occur during the flowering and grain filling stages, severe grain moulding occusr.</p><p>The most frequently occurring genera are Fusarium, Curvularia, Alternaria, Aspergillus and Phoma. Fusarium semitectum and F.moniliforme develop a fluffy white or pinkish coloration. C. lunata colours the grain black. Symptom varies depending upon the organism involved and the degree of infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Wet weather following the flowering favors grain mould development.</p><p>• The longer the wet period the greater the mould development.</p><p>• Compact ear heads are highly susceptible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungi mainly spread through air-borne conidia. The fungi survive as parasites as well as saprophytes in the infected plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Adjust the sowing time.</p><p>• Spray any one of the following fungicides in case of intermittent rainfall during earhead emergence, a week later and during milky stage.</p><p>• Mancozeb 1 kg/ha or Captan 1 kg + Aureofungin-sol 100 g/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phanerogamic parasite -Striga asiatica and Striga densiflora</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>It is a partial root parasite and occurs mainly in the rainfed sorghum. It is a small plant with bright green leaves, grows up to a height of 15-30 cm. The plants occur in clusters of 10-20/host plant. S. asiatica produces red to pink flowers while. S. densiflora produces white flowers. Each fruit contains minute seeds in abundance which survives in the soil for several years.</p><p>The root exudates of sorghum stimulate the seeds of the parasite to germinate. The parasite then slowly attaches to the root of the host by haustoria and grows below the soil surface producing underground stems and roots for about 1-2 months. The parasite grows faster and appears at the base of the plant. Severe infestation causes yellowing and wilting of the host leaves. The infected plants are stunted in growth and may die prior to seed setting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Regular weeding and intercultural operation during early stages of parasite growth.</p><p>• Spray Fernoxone (sodium salt of 2, 4-D) at 450g /500 litre of water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Brown or leaf rust -Puccinia triticina (P. recondita)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p><p>The most common site for symptoms is on leaf blades, however, sheaths, glumes and awns may occasionally become infected and exhibit symptoms. Uredia are seen as small, circular orange blisters or pustules on the upper surface of leaves.</p><p>Orange spores are easily dislodged and may cover clothing, hands or implements. When the infection is severe leaves dry out and die. Since inoculum is blown into a given area, symptoms are often seen on upper leaves first. As plants mature, the orange urediospores are replaced by black teliospores. Pustules containing these spores are black and shiny since the epidermis does not rupture. Yield loss often occurs as a result of infection by Puccinia recondita f. sp. tritici. Heavy infection which extends to the flag leaf results in a shorter period of grain fill and small kernels.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yellow or stripe rust -Puccinia striiformis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptom</head><p>Mainly occur on leaves than the leaf sheaths and stem. Bright yellow pustules (Uredia)</p><p>appear on leaves at early stage of crop and pustules are arranged in linear rows as stripes. The stripes are yellow to orange yellow. The teliospores are also arranged in long stripes and are dull black in colour.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The uredospores of rust pathogen are almost round or oval in shape and bright orange in colour. The teliospores are bright organge to dark brown, two celled and flattened at the top.</p><p>Sterile paraphyses are also present at the end of sorus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>In India, all these rusts appear in wheat growing belt during Rabi crop season. Uredosori turn into teliosori as summer approaches. The inoculum survives in the form of uredospores / teliospores in the hills during off season on self sown crop or volunteer hosts, which provide an excellent source of inoculum. In India, role of alternate host (Barberis) is not there in completing the life cycle.</p><p>The fungus is inhibited by temperatures over 20˚C although strains tolerant of high temperatures do exist. The complete cycle from infection to the production of new spores can take as little as 7 days during ideal conditions. The disease cycle may therefore be repeated many times in one season. During late summer, the dark teliospores may be produced. These can germinate to produce yet another spore type, the basidiospore, but no alternate host has been found. Although the teliospores seem to have no function in the disease cycle they may contribute to the development of new races through sexual recombination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle of Puccinia graminis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Low temperature (15-20˚C) and high humidity during November -December favour black and brown rusts.</p><p>• Temperature less &lt; 10 o favours yellow rusts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Uredospores and dormant mycelium survive on stubbles and straws and also on weed hosts and self sown wheat crops. Wind borne uredospores from hills are lifted due to cyclonic winds and infect the crop in the plains during crop season.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Mixed cropping with suitable crops.</p><p>• Avoid excess dose of nitrogenous fertilizers.</p><p>• Spray Zineb at 2.5 kg/ha or Propioconazole @ 0.1 %.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties like PBW 343, PBW 550, PBW 17</p><p>Loose smut -Ustilago nuda tritici (Ustilago tritici)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>It is very difficult to detect infected plants in the field until heading. At this time, infected heads emerge earlier than normal heads. The entire inflorescence is commonly affected and appears as a mass of olive-black spores, initially covered by a thin gray membrane. Once the membrane ruptures, the head appears powdery.</p><p>Spores are dislodged, leaving only the rachis intact. In some cases remnants of glumes and awns may be present on the exposed rachis. Smutted heads are shorter than healthy heads due to a reduction in the length of the rachis and peduncle. All or a portion of the heads on an infected plant may exhibit these symptoms. While infected heads are shorter, the rest of the plant is slightly taller than healthy plants. Prior to heading affected plants have dark green erect leaves.</p><p>Chlorotic streaks may also be visible on the leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>Ears of infected plants emerge early. The spores released from the infected heads land on the later emerging florets and infect the developing seed. Infection during flowering is favored</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri by frequent rain showers, high humidity and temperature. The disease is internally seed borne, where pathogen infects the embryo in the seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>Treat the seed with Vitavax @ 2g/kg seed before sowing. Burry the infected ear heads in the soil, so that secondary spread is avoided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flag smut -Urocystis tritici</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The symptoms can be seen on stem, clum and leaves from late seedling stage to maturity.</p><p>The seedling infection leads to twisting and drooping of leaves followed by withering. Grey to grayish black sori occurs on leaf blade and sheath. The sorus contains black powdery mass of spores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Aggregated spore balls, consisting 1-6 bright globose, brown smoth walled spores surrounded by a layer of flat sterile cells.</p><p>s</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Temperature of 18-24˚C.</p><p>• Relative humidity 65% and above.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Seed and soil borne. Smut spores are viable for more than 10 years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with carboxin at 2g /kg.</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties like Pusa 44 and WG 377.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hill bunt or Stinking smut -Tilletia caries / T.foetida</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spore balls</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus attacks seedling of 8-10 days old and become systemic and grows along the tip of shoot. At the time of flowering hyphae concentrate in the inflorescence and spikelets and transforming the ovary into smut sorus of dark green color with masses of chlamydospores. The diseased plants mature earlier and all the spikelets are affected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Reticulate and rough walled. No resting period. Germinate to produce primary sporidia which unite to form 'H' shaped structure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle</head><p>The spores on the seed surface germinate along with the seed. Each produces a short fungal thread terminating in a cluster of elongated cells. These then produce secondary spores which infect the coleoptiles of the young seedlings before the emergence of the first true leaves.</p><p>The mycelium grows internally within the shoot infecting the developing ear. Affected plants develop apparently normally until the ear emerges when it can be seen that grain sites have been replaced by bunt balls. In India disease occurs only in Northern hills, where wheat is grown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms on earhead and grains</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spores and its germination</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Temperature of 18-20˚C.</p><p>• High soil moisture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Externally seed borne</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with carboxin or carbendazim at 2g/kg.</p><p>• Grow the crop during high temperature period.</p><p>• Adopt shallow sowing.</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties like Kalyan sona, S227, PV18, HD2021, HD4513 and HD4519.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Karnal bunt -Neovassia indica</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Symptoms of Karnal bunt are often difficult to distinguish in the field due to the fact that incidence of infected kernels on a given head is low. There may be some spreading of the glumes</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri due to sorus production but it is not as extensive as that observed with common bunt. Symptoms are most readily detected on seed after harvest.</p><p>The black sorus, containing dusty spores is evident on part of the seed, commonly occurring along the groove. Heavily infected seed is fragile and the pericarp ruptures easily. The foul, fishy odor associated with common bunt is also found with karnal bunt. The odor is caused by the production of trimethylamine by the fungus. Seed that is not extensively infected may germinate and produce healthy plants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Foot rot -Pythium graminicolum and P. arrhenomanes</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 50</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>The disease mainly occurs in seedlings and roots and rootlets become brown in colour.</p><p>Seedlings become pale green and have stunted growth. Fungus produces sporangia and zoospores and oospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>Wet weather and high rainfall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Through soil and irrigation water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Follow crop rotation.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Carboxin or Carbendazim at 2g/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mildew -Erysiphe graminis var. tritici</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Greyish white powdery growth appears on the leaf, sheath, stem and floral parts.</p><p>Powdery growth later become black lesion and cause drying of leaves and other parts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Fungus produces septate, superficial, hyaline mycelium on leaf surface with short conidiophores. The conidia are elliptical, hyaline, single celled, thin walled and produced in</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p><p>Google -HortiAgri chains. Dark globose cleistothecia containing 9-30 asci develop with oblong, hyaline and thinwalled ascospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Fungus remains in infected plant debris as dormant mycelium and asci. Primary spread is by the ascospores and secondary spread through airborne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Temperature of 20-21˚C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Spray Wettable Sulphur 0.2% or Carbendazim @ 500 g/ha</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf blight -Alternaria triticina / Bipolaris sorokiniana</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Reddish brown oval spots appear on young seedlings with bright yellow margin. In severe cases, several spots coalesce to cause drying of leaves. It is a complex disease, having association of A.triticina, B.sorokiniana and A. alternate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conidia and conidiophores</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Primary spread is by externally seed-borne and soil borne conidia. Secondary spread by air-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Temperature of 25˚C and high relative humidity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Spray the crop with Mancozeb or Zineb at 2 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other minor diseases</head><p>Helminthosporium leaf spot: Helminthosporium spp.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tundu or yellow ear rot: Corynebacterium tritici + Anguina tritici</head><p>Seedling blight: Rhizoctonia solani and Fusarium sp Sclerotinia rot: Sclerotinia sclerotiorum Molya disease: Heterodera avenae (Nematode)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Diseases of Pearlmillet Downy mildew -Sclerospora graminicola</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Infection is mainly systemic and symptoms appear on leaves and inflorescence. The initial symptoms appear in seedlings at three to four leaf stages. The affected leaves show patches of light green to light yellow colour on the upper surface and the corresponding lower surface bears white downy growth of the fungus consisting of sporangiophores and sporangia.</p><p>The yellow discolouration often turns to streaks along veins. As a result of infection young plants dry and die ultimately. Symptoms may appear first on the upper leaves of the main shoot or the main shoot may be symptom free and symptoms appear on tillers or on the lateral shoots.</p><p>The inflorescence of infected plants gets completely or partially malformed with florets converted into leafy structures, giving the typical symptom of green ear.</p><p>Infected leaves and inflorescences produce sporangia over a considerable period of time under humid conditions and necrosis begins. The dry necrotic tissues contain masses of oospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The mycelium is systemic, non septae and intercellular. Short, stout, hyaline sporangiophores arise through stomata and branch irregularly, with stalks bearing sporangia.</p><p>Sporangia are hyaline, thin walled, elliptical and bear prominent papilla. Oospores are round in shape, surrounded by a smooth, thick and yellowish brown wall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Very high humidity (90%).</p><p>• Presence of water on the leaves</p><p>• Low temperature of 15-25˚C favor the formation of sporangiophore and sporangia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Green ear sym toms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Oospores</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The oospores remain viable in soil for 5 years or longer giving rise to the primary infection on seedlings. Secondary spread is through sporangia produced during rainy season. The dormant mycelium of the fungus is present in embryo of infected seeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep ploughing to bury the oospores.</p><p>• Roguing out infected plants.</p><p>• Adopt crop rotation.</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties WCC-75, Co7 and Co (Cu)9.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Metalaxyl at 6g/kg.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 2 kg or Metalaxyl + Mancozeb at 1 kg/ha on 20th day after sowing in the field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Smut -Tolyposporium penicillariae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The pathogen infects few florets and transforms them into plump sori containing smut spores. The sori are larger than normal healthy grains and when the sori mature they become dark brown releasing millions of black smut spore balls.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus is mostly confined to the sorus. The sori contain spores in groups and are not easy to separate. Each spore is angular or round and light brown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High relative humidity.</p><p>• Successive cropping with pearlmillet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>• The pathogen survives as spore balls in the soil and serves as primary source of inoculum. Secondary spread is by air-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• The damage caused by the fungus is negligible.</p><p>• Removal and destruction of affected ear head will help in controlling the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rust -Puccinia pennisetti</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Symptoms first appear mostly on the distal half of the lamina. The leaf soon becomes covered by uredosori which appear more on the upper surface. The pustules may be formed on leaf sheath, stem and on peduncles. Later, telial formation takes place on leaf blade, leaf sheath and stem. While brownish uredia are exposed at maturity, the black telia remain covered by the epidermis for a longer duration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Uredospores are oval, elliptic, sparsely echinulated and pedicellate. Teliospores are dark brown in colour, two celled, cylindrical to club shaped, apex flattened, broad at top and tapering towards base. The fungus is macrocyclic producing uredial and telial stages on pearlmillet and aecial and pycnial stages on brinjal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Closer spacing.</p><p>• Presence of abundant brinjal plants and other species of Solanum viz., S.torvum, S.</p><p>xanthocarpum and S. pubescens.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Air-borne uredospores are the primary sources. The uredial stages also occur on several species of Pennisetum, which helps in secondary spread of the pathogen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>Spray with Wettable Sulphur 3 kg or Mancozeb 2 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ergot or Sugary disease -Claviceps fusiformis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The symptom is seen by exudation of small droplets of light pinkish or brownish honey dew from the infected spikelets. Under severe infection many such spikelets exude plenty of honey dew which trickles along the earhead. This attracts several insects. In the later stages, the infected ovary turns into small dark brown sclerotium which projects out of the spikelet.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The pathogen produces septate mycelium which produces conidiophores and is closely arranged. Conidia are hyaline and one celled. The sclerotia are small (3-8mm x 0.3-15mm) and dark grey but white inside.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sclerotia</head><p>and C. setigerus in perpetuation of fungus is significant. The fungus also infects other species of Pennisetum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Adjust the sowing date so that the crop does not flower during September when high rainfall and high relative humidity favour the disease spread.</p><p>• Immerse the seeds in 10 per cent common salt solution and remove the floating sclerotia.</p><p>• Remove collateral hosts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Spray with Carbendazim 500g or Mancozeb 2 kg or Ziram 1kg/ha when 5-10 per cent flowers have opened and again at 50 per cent flowering stage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head><p>Grain mould -Fungal complex Grains covered with white, pink or black moulds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Blast -Pyricularia setariae</head><p>Diamond shaped to circular lesions with dark brown margins and chlorotic haloes.</p><p>Zonate leaf spot -Gloeocercospora sp.</p><p>Rough circular lesions with alternating concentric bands of straw and brown colour, often coalescing over the leaf surface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Banded leaf spot -Rhizoctonia spp.</head><p>Patch of light and dark, discoloured areas and often bearing fluffy to light brown fungal mats.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Diseases of Maize Downy mildew/Crazy top</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sorghum downy mildew -Peronosclerospora sorghi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phlippine downy mildew -Peronosclerospora philippinensis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Crazy top -Sclerophthora macrospora</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The most characteristic symptom is the development of chlorotic streaks on the leaves.</p><p>Plants exhibit a stunted and bushy appearance due to shortening of the internodes. White downy growth is seen on the lower surface of leaf. Downy growth also occurs on bracts of green unopened male flowers in the tassel. Small to large leaves are noticed in the tassel. Proliferation of auxillary buds on the stalk of tassel and the cobs is common (Crazy top).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus grows as white downy growth on both surface of the leaves, consisting of sporangiophores and sporangia. Sporangiophores are quite short and stout, branch profusely into series of pointed sterigmata which bear hyaline, oblong or ovoid sporangia (conidia). Sporangia germinate directly and infect the plants. In advanced stages, oospores are formed which are spherical, thick walled and deep brown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Low temperature (21-33˚C)</p><p>• High relative humidity (90 per cent) and drizzling.</p><p>• Young plants are highly susceptible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The primary source of infection is through oospores in soil and also dormant mycelium present in the infected maize seeds. Secondary spread is through airborne conidia. Depending on the pathogen species, the initial source of disease inoculum can be oospores that over winter in the soil or conidia produced in infected, over wintering crop debris and infected neighboring plants. Some species that cause downy mildew can also be seed borne, although this is largely restricted to seed that is fresh and has high moisture content.</p><p>At the onset of the growing season, at soil temperatures above 20°C, oospores in the soil germinate in response to root exudates from susceptible maize seedlings. The germ tube infects the underground sections of maize plants leading to characteristic symptoms of systemic infection including extensive chlorosis and stunted growth. If the pathogen is seed borne, whole plants show symptoms. Oospores are reported to survive in nature for up to 10 years.</p><p>Once the fungus has colonised host tissue, sporangiophores (conidiophores) emerge from stomata and produce sporangia (conidia) which are wind and rain splash disseminated and initiate secondary infections. Sporangia are always produced in the night. They are fragile and can not be disseminated more than a few hundred meters and do not remain viable for more than a few hours.</p><p>Germination of sporangia is dependent on the availability of free water on the leaf surface. Initial symptoms of disease (chlorotic specks and streaks that elongate parallel to veins)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri occur in 3 days. Conidia are produced profusely during the growing season. As the crop approaches senescence, oospores are produced in large numbers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep ploughing.</p><p>• Crop rotation with pulses.</p><p>• Rogue out infected plants.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with metalaxyl at 6g/kg.</p><p>• Spray the crop with Metalaxyl + Mancozeb @ 1kg on 20th day after sowing.</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties and hybrids viz. CO1, COH1and COH2.</p><p>Leaf blight -Helminthosporium maydis (Syn: H. turcicum)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The fungus affects the crop at young stage. Small yellowish round to oval spots are seen on the leaves. The spots gradually increase in area into bigger elliptical spots and are straw to grayish brown in the centre with dark brown margins. The spots coalesce giving blighted appearance. The surface is covered with olive green velvetty masses of conidia and conidiophores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Conidiophores are in group, geniculate, mid dark brown, pale near the apex and smooth.</p><p>Conidia are distinctly curved, fusiform, pale to mid dark golden brown with 5-11 septa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Optimum temperature for the germination of conidia is 8 to 27˚C provided with freewater on the leaf.</p><p>• Infection takes place early in the wet season.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>It is a seed-borne fungus. It also infects sorghum, wheat, barely, oats, sugarcane and spores of the fungus are also found to associate with seeds of green gram, black gram, cowpea, varagu, Sudan grass, Johnson grass and Teosinte.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Captan or Thiram at 4 g/kg.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 2 kg or captan 1 kg/ha. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rust -Puccinia sorghi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Cool temperature and high relative humidity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Primary source of inoculums is uredospores surviving on alternate hosts viz., Oxalis corniculata and Euchlaena mexicana.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove the alternate hosts.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb at 2 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Head smut -Sphacelotheca reiliana</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Uredospores and telios oes</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Symptoms are usually noticed on the cob and tassel. Large smut sori replace the tassel and the ear. Sometimes the tassel is partially or wholly converted into smut sorus. The smutted plants are stunted produce little yield and remain greener than that of the rest of the plants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Smut spores are produced in large numbers which are reddish brown to black, thick walled, finely spined, spherical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Low temperature favours more infection and this fungus also infects the sorghum</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The smut spores retain its viability for two years. The fungus is externally seedborne and soil-borne. The major source of infection is through soil-borne chlamydospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Field sanitation.</p><p>• Crop rotation with pulses.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Captan or Thiram at 4 g/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Charcoal rot -Macrophomina phaseolina (Rhizoctonia bataticola)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The affected plants exhibit wilting symptoms. The stalk of the infected plants can be recognized by grayish streak. The pith becomes shredded and grayish black minute sclerotia develop on the vascular bundles. Shredding of the interior of the stalk often causes stalks to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Google -HortiAgri break in the region of the crown. The crown region of the infected plant becomes dark in colour.</p><p>Shredding of root bark and disintegration of root system are the common features.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces large number of sclerotia which are round and black in colour.</p><p>Sometimes, it produces pycnidia on the stems or stalks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High temperature and low soil moisture (drought)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus has a wide host range, attacking sorghum, pearlmillet, fingermillet and pulses. It survives for more than 16 years in the infected plant debris. The primary source of infection is through soil-borne sclerotia. The pathogen also attacks many other hosts, which helps in its perpetuation. Since the fungus is a facultative parasite it is capable of living saprophytically on dead organic tissues, particularly many of its natural hosts producing sclerotial bodies. The fungus over winters as a sclerotia in the soil and infects the host at susceptible crop stage through roots and proceeds towards stem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Long crop rotation with crops that are not natural host of the fungus.</p><p>• Irrigate the crops at the time of earhead emergence to maturity.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim or Captan at 2 g/kg.</p><p>• Grow disease tolerant varieties viz., SN-65, SWS-8029, Diva and Zenit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sym toms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases Bacterial Stalk rot -Erwinia dissolvens</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The basal internodes develop soft rot and give a water soaked appearance. A mild sweet fermenting odour accompanies such rotting. Leaves some time show signs of wilting and affected plants topple down in few days. Ears and shank may also show rot. They fail to develop further and the ears hang down simply from the plant</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Borer insects play a significant role in initiation of the disease. The organism is soil borne and makes its entry through wounds and injuries on the host surface. The organism survives saprophytically on debris of infected materials and serves primary inoculum in the next season.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mosaic -Maize mosaic potyvirus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Symptoms appear as chlorotic spots, which gradually turn into stripes covering entire leaf blade. Chlorotic stripes and spots can also develop on leaf sheaths, stalks and husks.</p><p>Moderate to severe rosetting of new growth is observed. Size of stalk, leaf blades and tassel tend to be normal in late infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>It is caused by Maize mosaic potyvirus. Virions are flexuous, 750-900nm long, ssRNA genome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>It is transmitted in nature by leaf hopper vector, Perigrimus maidis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Brown spot -Physoderma maydis</head><p>Water soaked lesions, which are oval, later turn into light green and finally brown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Monoculturing of sugarcane.</p><p>• Successive ratoon cropping.</p><p>• Water logged conditions and injuries caused by insects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus is sett-borne and also persists in the soil on the diseased clumps and stubbles as chlamydospores and dormant mycelium. The primary infection is mainly from infected setts.</p><p>Secondary spread in the field is through irrigation water and cultivation tools. The rain splash, air currents and dew drops also help in the spread of conidia from the diseased to healthy plants in the field. The fungus also survives on collateral hosts Sorghum vulgare, S. halepense and Saccharum spontaneum.If the conidia settle on the leaves they may germinate and invade the leaves through various types of wounds. Stem infection may take place through insect bores and root primordia. The soil-borne fungus may also enter the healthy setts through cut-ends, and</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri cause early infection of the shoots. Though the perfect stage of the fungus has been observed in nature, the role of ascospores in the disease cycle is not understood.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Adopt crop rotation by including rice and green manure crops.</p><p>• Select the setts from the disease free fields or disease free areas.</p><p>• Aviod ratooning of the diseased crop.</p><p>• Soak the setts in 0.1% Carbendazim or Triademefon 0.05% solution for 15 minutes before planting.</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties CO 62198, CO 7704 and moderately resistant varieties CO 8001, CO8201.</p><p>• Setts can be treated with aerated steam at 52 ˚C for 4 to 5 hours and by moist hot air at 54˚C for 2 hours.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Smut -Ustilago scitaminea</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>It is a culmiculous smut. The affected plants are stunted and the central shoot is converted into a long whip-like, dusty black structure. The length of the whip varies from few inches to several feet. In early stages, this structure is covered by a thin, white papery membrane. The whip may be straight or slightly curved.</p><p>On maturity it ruptures and millions of tiny black smut spores (teliospores) are liberated and disseminated by the wind. Affected plants are usually thin, stiff and remain at acute angle.</p><p>The whip like structure, representing the central shoot with its various leaves, may be produced by each one of the shoots/tillers arising from the clump.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The smutted clumps also produce mummified arrows in which lower portion consisted of a normal inflorescence with typical flowers and the upper portion of the rachis is converted into a typical smut whip. Occasionally smut sori may develop on the leaves and stem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungal hyphae are primarily intercellular and collect as a dense mass between the vascular bundles of host cell and produce tiny black spores. The thin membrane which covers the smut whip represents the host epidermis. The smut spores are light brown in colour, spherical, echinulated and measuring 6.5-8.5 m in diameter. Smut spores germinate to produce 3-4 celled, hyaline promycelium and produce 3-4 sporidia which are hyaline and oval shaped with pointed ends.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Monoculturing of sugarcane.</p><p>• Continuous ratooning and dry weather during tillering stage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Teliospores may survive in the soil for long periods, upto 10 years. The spores and sporidia are also present in the infected plant materials in the soil. The smut spores and dormant mycelium also present in or on the infected setts. The primary spread of the disease is through diseased seed-pieces (setts). In addition, sporidia and spores present in the soil also spread through rain and irrigation water and cause soil-borne infection. The secondary spread in the</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri field is mainly through the smut spores developed in the whips, aided by air currents. The fungus also survives on collateral hosts like Saccharum spontaneum, S. robustum, Sorghum vulgare, Imperata arundinacea and Cyperus dilatatus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Plant healthy setts taken from disease free area.</p><p>• Remove and destory the smutted clump (collect the whips in a thick cloth bag/polythene bag and immerse in boiling water for 1 hr to kill the spores).</p><p>• Discourage ratooning of the diseased crops having more than 10 per cent infection.</p><p>• Follow crop rotation with green manure crops or dry fallowing.</p><p>• Grow redgram as a companion crop between 2 rows of sugarcane.</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties like Co 7704 and moderately resistant varieties COC 85061 and COC 8201.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sett rot or Pineapple disease -Ceratocystis paradoxa</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease primarily affects the setts usually two to three weeks after planning. The fungus is soil-borne and enters through cut ends and proliferates rapidly in the parenchymatous tissues. The affected tissues first develop a reddish colour which turns to brownish black in the later stages. The severely affected setts show internodal cavities covered with the mycelium and abundant spores. A characteristic pineapple smell is associated with the rotting tissues. The setts may decay before the buds germinate or the shoots may die after reaching a height of about 6-12 inches. Infected shoots are stunted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symp Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces both macroconidia and microconidia. Conidiophores are linear, thin walled with short cells at the base and a long terminal cell. The microconidia are hyaline when young but become almost black at maturity. They are thinwalled, cylindrical and produced endogenously in chains in the long cells of conidiophores and pushed out in succession.</p><p>Macroconidia are produced singly or in chains on a short, lateral conidiophores. Macroconidia are spherical or elliptical or truncate or pyriform and are hyaline to olive green or black measuring 16-19x10-12 um.</p><p>The fungus also produces chlamydospores on short lateral hyphae in chains, which are oval, thick walled and brown in colour. The perithecia are flask shaped with a very long neck.</p><p>The bulbous base of the perithecium is hyaline or pale yellow, 200-300 m in diameter and ornamented with irregularly shaped, knobbed appendages. The ostiole is covered by numerous pale-brown, erect tapering hyphae. Asci are clavate and measures 25x10 m and ascospores are single celled, hyaline, ellipsoid, more convex on one side, measures 7-10 x 2.5-4 m.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Poorly drained fields.</p><p>• Heavy clay soils</p><p>• Temperature of 25-30 o C</p><p>• Prolonged rainfall after planting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus survives as conidia and chlamydospores in the soil and in the infected, burried cane tissues. The inoculum moves from field to field through wind-borne conidia or irrigation or rain water. Inside the sett it spreads rapidly through the parenchymatous tissues and causes sett rot.</p><p>The insects like cane borer (Diatraea dyari) also helps in the spread of the disease. The pathogen also survives on coconut, cocoa, mango, papaya, coffee, maize and arecanut. Insects also play a part in the dissemination of the pathogen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Soak the setts in 0.05% Carbendazim 15 minutes.</p><p>• Use long setts having 3 or 4 buds.</p><p>• Provide adequate drainage during rainy seasons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wilt -Cephalosporium sacchari</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The first symptom of the disease is visible in the canes of 4-5 month age. The canes may wither in groups. The affected plants are stunted with yellowing and withering of crown leaves.</p><p>The midribs of all leaves in a crown generally turn yellow, while the leaf lamina may remain green. The leaves dry up and stem develop hollowness in the core. The core shows the reddish discolouration with longitudinal red streaks passing from one internode to another. In severe cases, spindle shaped cavities tapering towards the nodes develop in each internode. The canes emit a disagreeable odour, with lot of mycelial threads of the fungus cover the cavity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungal mycelium is hyaline, septate and thin walled. The conidiophores are simple or branched and produce single celled, hyaline, oval to elliptical microconidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High day temperature (30-35˚C).</p><p>• Low humidity (50-60%).</p><p>• Low soil moisture and alkaline soils.</p><p>• Excess doses of nitrogenous fertilizers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus is soil-borne and remains in the soil as saprophyte for 2-3 years. The disease is primarily transmitted through infected seed pieces. The secondary spread is aided by wind, rain and irrigation water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Select the seed material from the disease-free plots.</p><p>• Avoid the practice of ratooning in diseased fields.</p><p>• Burn the trashes and stubbles in the field.</p><p>• Grow coriander or mustard as a companion crop in the early stages of crop.</p><p>• Dip the setts in 40ppm Boran or Manganese for 10 minutes or in 0.25% Emisan or 0.05%</p><p>Carbendazim for 15 minutes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Temperature of 30˚C.</p><p>• Rumidity between 70 and 90 per cent.</p><p>• High wind velocity and continuous cloudiness.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus survives on collateral hosts like Erianthus fulvus and Saccharum spontaneum.</p><p>The uredospores also survive in the infected stubbles in the soil. The disease is mainly spread through air-borne uredospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Uredospores</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove the collateral hosts.</p><p>• Spray Tridemorph 1 kg or Mancozeb 2 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gummosis -Xanthomonas axonopodis pv. vasculorum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The bacterium produces two distinct types of symptoms. On the mature leaves, longitudinal stripes or streaks, 3-7mm in width and several cm in length, appear around the affected veins, near the tip. Initially these stripes are pale yellow in colour, later turn to brown.</p><p>The affected tissues slowly dry up.</p><p>The infected canes are stunted with short internodes, giving a bushy appearance. When </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The bacterium is a short rod, Gram negative, non spore forming measuring 1.0 to 1.5 m X 0.4 to 0.5 m, with a single polar flagellum. It is facultative anaerobe and it produces yellow slimy growth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The bacterium remains viable in the soil as well as in infected canes. The primary transmission is through naturally affected diseased setts or through soil-borne contamination.</p><p>The secondary spread may be through wind splashed rain, harvesting implements, animals and insects. The bacterium can survive in the insect's body for a long time and in this way may be transmitted long distances. On entry into the host the bacterium reaches the vascular tissues and becomes systemic. The bacterium also perpetuates on maize, sorghum, pearlmillet and other weed hosts, which also serve as sources of inoculum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and burn the affected clumps and the stubbles in the field. Select setts from disease free areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Avoid growing collateral hosts like maize, sorghum and pearlmillet near the sugarcane fields.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Red stripe -Pseudomonas rubrilineans</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease first makes it appearance on the basal part of the young leaves. The stripes appear as water soaked, long, narrow chlorotic streaks and become reddish brown in few days.</p><p>These stripes are 0.5 to 1 mm in width and 5-100 mm in length, run parallel to the midrib. The stripes remain confined to lower half of the leaf lamina and whitish flakes spreads to growing points of the shoot and yellowish stripes develop, which later turn reddish brown. The rotting may commence from the tip of the shoot and spreads downwards. The core is discoloured to reddish brown and shrivelled and form cavity in the centre. In badly affected fields, a foul and nauseating smell appears.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The bacterium is a short rod (0.7 X 1.67 m), gram negative, non capsulate with a polar flagellum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Continuous ratooning and prolonged rainy weather with low temperature (25 0 C)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The pathogen remains viable in the soil and infected plant residues. The bacterium also survives on sorghum, pearlmillet, maize, fingermillet and other species of Saccharum. The bacterium primarily spreads through infected canes. The secondary spread is mainly through rainsplash, irrigation water and insects. Infected parenchymatous cells may collapse and normal functioning of the plant parts may fail. Several grasses, including ragi and bajra, have been reported to be infected by the bacteria and these hosts may also play a role in the perpetuation and spread of the pathogen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Whenever the disease is noticed; the affected plants should be removed and burnt.</p><p>• Growing resistant varieties Select setts from the healthy fields.</p><p>• Avoid growing collateral hosts near the sugarcane fields.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sugarcane Mosaic -Sugarcane mosaic potyvirus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears more prominently on the basal portion of the younger foliage as chlorotic or yellowish stripes alternate with normal green portion of the leaf. As infection becomes severe, yellow stripes appear on the leaf sheath and stalks. Elongated necrotic lesions are produced on the stalks and stem splitting occurs. The necrotic lesions also develop on the internodes and the entire plant becomes stunted and chlorotic.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Sugarcane mosaic potyvirus is a flexous rod, 650-770nm long X 12-15nm with ss RNA genome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The virus is mainly transmitted through infected canes used as seed. The virus also infects Zea mays and a number of other cereals (Sorghum vulgare, Pennisetum americanum, Eleusine indica, Setaria lutescens, Echinochloa crusgalli, Stenotaphrum secondatum, Digitaria didactyla) which serve as potential sources of virus inoculum. The virus also spreads through viruliferous aphids viz., Melanaphis sacchari, Rhopalosiphum maidis in a non-persistant manner.</p><p>The virus is also sap-transmissible. The incubation period varies from 7 to 20 days, depending upon the host variety and virus strain. The symptoms may be prominent or masked depending on the environmental conditions and variety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Roguing of infected plants and use of disease free planting material.</p><p>• Chemical sprays to manage the insect vector population in early crop stage.</p><p>• G row mosaic-resistant or, at least, tolerant varieties.</p><p>• Breeding mosaic-resistant varieties is needed.</p><p>• Saccharum spontaneum L. and S. barberi (Jesweit) carry resistance to mosaic and so varieties with this background must be preferred.</p><p>• Rogue out the diseased clumps periodically. Select setts from the healthy fields as the virus is sett-borne Aerated Steam Therapy (AST) at 56˚C for 3 hrs, for setts before planting is advised.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grassy shoot -Phytoplasma</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears nearly two months after planting. The disease is characterised by the production of numerous lanky tillers from the base of the affected shoots. Leaves become pale yellow to completely chlorotic, thin and narrow. The plants appear bushy and 'grass-like' due to reduction in the length of internodes premature and continuous tillering. The affected clumps are stunted with premature proliferation of auxillary buds. Cane formation rarely occurs in the affected clumps, if formed, thin with shorter internodes having aerial roots at the lower nodes.</p><p>The buds on such canes usually papery and abnormally elongated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The disease is caused by a phytoplasma. Two types of bodies are seen in ultrathin sections of phloem cells of infected plants. The spherical bodies of 300-400 nm diameter and filamentous bodies of 30-53 mm diameter in size.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The primary spread of the phytoplasma is through diseased setts and cutting knifes. The pathogen is transmitted secondarily by aphids viz., Rhopalosiphum maydis, Melanaphis sacchari and M. idiosacchari. Sorghum and maize serves as natural collateral hosts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Eradication of diseased parts as soon as symptoms are seen.</p><p>• Avoid selection of setts from diseased area.</p><p>• Pre-treating the healthy setts with hot water at 52°C for 1 hour before planting</p><p>• Treating them with hot air at 54°C for 8 hours.</p><p>• Spraying the crop twice a month with insecticides. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ratoon stunting -</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The primary spread is through the use of diseased setts. The disease also spreads through harvesting implements contaminated with the juice of the diseased canes. Maize, sorghum, Sudan grass and Cynodon serves as collateral hosts for the pathogen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Select the setts from disease free fields or from disease free commercial nursery.</p><p>• Remove and burn the clumps showing the disease incidence.</p><p>• Treat the setts before planting, as specified for grassy shoot disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head><p>Damping-off -Pythium aphanidermatum, P. debaryanum, P. graminicola, P.ultimum</p><p>Germinating seeds and young seedlings are attacked and killed in pre-emergence phase and seedlings show water soaked lesions at collar region, leading to withering and drying in post emergence stage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Downy mildew -Peronosclerospora sacchari</head><p>Downy fungal growth with yellow stripes on upper surface, shredding of older leaves, rapid elongation of internodes of affected canes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eye spot -Helminthosporium sacchari</head><p>The water soaked spot develops on leaves, later elongated and turns to form "eye" shaped spot with reddish brown centre surrounded by straw yellow tissues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ring spot -Leptosphaeria sacchari</head><p>The water soaked spots appear on leaves and turns to straw colour later surrounded by a thin reddish brown band and a diffused discolouration zone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf scald -Xanthomonas albilineans</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 83</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com Whitish lines appear on the leaves, run to the full length of leaves and sheaths. Later leaves wither and dry from tip down-wards, gives a scald appearance to the clump. Sprouting of lateral buds of the matured canes occurs in acropetal fashion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>White leaf -Phytoplasma</head><p>Sugarcane white leaf is of minor importance and is caused by phytoplasma. The plants exhibit pure white leaves, stripped leaves and mottled leaves. Its vector is Matsumuratettix hiroglyphicus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Diseases of Turmeric Rhizome Rot -Pythium graminicolum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Starting from the margins the leaves get dried up, collar region of pseudo stem becomes soft and water-soaked and plants collapse. The rhizomes decay as a result of the attack of the fungus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Pathogen is soil-borne, therefore primary inoculam comes from soil. Infected rhizomes used for seed purpose may also transmit the disease. Irrigation water from diseased field helps in the spread of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Seed material should be selected from disease free areas.</p><p>• Avoid water stagnation in the field. Light soil may be preferred and drainage facility to be ensured.</p><p>• Grow tolerant varieties like Suguna and Sudarshan.</p><p>• Crop rotation to be followed.</p><p>• Deep plough in summer. Planting is to be done in ridge and furrow method.</p><p>• Remove diseased plants and the soil around plants to be drenced with Mancozeb (3gm/lit) or 3gm Ridomil M.Z.</p><p>• Spray the crop with Mancozeb (2.5g/lit) or Carbendazim (1g/lit) +1ml sandovit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Keep rhizomes in 3g Metalaxyl or 3g Mancozeb mixed in one litre of water for one hour and shade dry before planting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf Spot -Colletotrichum capsici</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Oblong brown spots with grey centres are found on leaves. The spots are about 4-5 cm in length and 2-3 cm in width. In advanced stages of disease black dots representing fungal acervuli occur in concentric rings on spot. The grey centers become thin and gets teared. Severely effected leaves dry and wilt. They are surrounded by yellow halos. Indefinite number of spots may be found on a single leaf and as the disease advances; spots enlarge and cover a major portion of leaf blade.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable condition</head><p>• The disease is usually appears in October and November</p><p>• Relative humidity of 80% and temperatures of 21 -230C favours the primary infection</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus is carried on the scales of rhizomes which are the source of primary infection during sowing. The secondary spread is by wind, water and other physical and biological agents.</p><p>The same pathogen is also reported to cause leaf-spot and fruit rot of chilli where it is transmitted through seed borne infections. If chilli is grown in nearby fields or used in crop rotation with turmeric, the pathogen perpetuates easily, building up inoculum potential for epiphytotic outbreaks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>• Select seed material from disease free areas.</p><p>• Treat seed material with mancozeb @ 3g/litre of water or carbendazim @ 1 g/litre of water, for 30 minutes and shade dry before sowing.</p><p>• Spray mancozeb @ 2.5 g/litre of water or carbendazim @ 1g/litre; 2-3 sprays at fortnightly intervals.</p><p>• The infected and dried leaves should be collected and burnt in order to reduce the inoculum source in the field.</p><p>• Spraying Blitox or Blue copper at 3 g/l of water was found effective against leaf spot.</p><p>• Crop rotations should be followed whenever possible.</p><p>• Cultivate tolerant varieties like Suguna and Sudarshan.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf Blotch -Taphrina maculans</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>This disease usually appears on lower leaves in October and November. The individual spots are small 1-2 mm in width and are mostly rectangular in shape. The disease is characterized by the appearance of several spots on both the surfaces of leaves, being generally numerous on the upper surface. They are arranged in rows along the veins. The spots coalesce freely and form irregular lesions. They first appear as pale yellow discolorations and then become dirty yellow in colour. The infected leaves disort and have reddish brown appearance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus is mainly air borne and primary infection occurs on lower leaves with the inoculum surviving in dried leaves of host, left over in the field. The ascospores discharged from</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri successively maturing asci infect fresh leaves without dormancy, thus causing secondary infection. Secondary infection is most dangerous than primary one causing profuse sprouting all over the leaves. The pathogen persists in summer by means of ascogenous cells on leaf debris, and dessicated ascospores and blastospores in soil and among fallen leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Select seed material from disease free areas.</p><p>• Treat the seed material with Mancozeb @ 3g/litre of water or Carbendazim @ 1 g/litre of water for 30 minutes and shade dry before sowing.</p><p>• Spray mancozeb @ 2.5 g/litre of water or Carbendazim @ 1g/litre; 2-3 sprays at fortnightly intervals.</p><p>• The infected and dried leaves should be collected and burnt in order to reduce the inoculum source in the field.</p><p>• Spraying Cpper oxy chloride at 3 g/l of water was found effective against leaf blotch.</p><p>• Crop rotations should be followed whenever possible. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Diseases of Tobacco Damping off -Pythium aphanidermatum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The pathogen attacks the seedlings at any stage in the nursery. Sprouting seedlings are infected and wither before emergence from the soil (Pre emergence damping off). Water soaked minute lesions appear on the stems near the soil surface, soon girdling the stem, spreading up and down in the stems and with in one or two days stem may rot leading to toppling over of the seedlings (Post-emergence damping off).</p><p>The young seedlings in the nursery are killed in patches and infection spreads quickly.</p><p>Under the favorable conditions, the entire seedlings in the nursery are killed within 3 to 4 days.</p><p>A thick weft of mycelium may be seen on the surface of the soil.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces thick, hyaline, thin walled, non-septate mycelium. It produces irregularly lobed sporangia which germinate to produce vesicle containing zoopores. The zoospores are kidney shaped and biflagellate. Oospores spherical, light to deep yellow or yellowish brown coloured, measuring 17-19 m in diameter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Over crowding of seedling.</p><p>• Ill drained nursery beds</p><p>• Heavy shade in nursery</p><p>• High atmospheric humidity (90-100 per cent)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pre and post emergence</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 89</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• High soil moisture</p><p>• Low temperature (below 24 C) and low soil temperature of about 20˚C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives in the soil as oospores and chlamydospores. The primary infection is from the soil-borne fungal spores and secondary spread through sporangia and zoospores transmitted by wind and irrigation water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Prepare raised seed beds with adequate drainage facility.</p><p>• Burn the seed beds with paddy husk before sowing.</p><p>• Drench the seed bed with 1 per cent Bordeaux mixture or 0.2 per cent Copper oxychloride, two days before sowing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 90</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• Avoid over crowding of seedlings by using recommended seed rate (1 to 1.5g/2.5m 2 ).</p><p>• Avoid excess watering of the seedlings.</p><p>• Spray the nursery beds two weeks after sowing with 1 per cent Bordeaux mixture or 0.2 per cent Copper oxychloride or 0.2 per cent Mancozeb and repeat subsequently at 4 days interval under dry weather and at 2 days interval under wet cloudy weather or spray 0.2 per cent Metalaxyl at 10 days interval commencing from 20 days after germination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Black shank -Phytophthora parasitica var. nicotianae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The pathogen may affect the crop at any stage of its growth. Even though all parts are affected, the disease infects chiefly the roots and base of the stem. Seedlings in the nursery show black discolor of the stem near the soil level and blackening of roots, leading the wet rot in humid condition and seedling blight in dry weather with withering and drying of tips. The pathogen also spreads to the leaves and causes blighting and drying of the bottom leaves. In the transplanted crop, the disease appears as minute black spot on the stem, spreads along the stem to produce irregular black patches and often girdling occurs.</p><p>The upward movement leads to development of necrotic patches on the stems.</p><p>The infected tissues shrink, leaving a depression and in advanced condition the stem shrivels and plant wilts. When the affected stem is split open, the pith region is found to be dried up in disclike plates showing black discolouration. On the leaves large brown concentrically zonate patches appear during humid weather, leading to blackening and rotting of the leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The fungus produces hyaline and non-septate mycelium. The sporangia, which are hyaline, thin walled, ovate or pyriform with papillae, develop on the sporangiophores in a sympodial fashion. Sporangia germinate to release zoospores which are usually kidney shaped, biciliate and measure 11-13 x 8-9 m. The fungus also produces globoose and thick walled chlamydospores, measuring 27-42 m in diameter. Oospores are thick walled, globose, smooth and light yellow coloured, measuring 15-20 m in diameter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Frequent rainfall and high soil moisture.</p><p>• High population of rootknot nematodes Meloidogyne incognita var. acrita.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus lives as a saprophyte on organic wastes and infected crop residues in soil. The fungus is also present in the soil as dormant mycelium, oospores and chlamydospores for more than 2 years. The primary infection is by means of oospores and chlamydospores in the soil.</p><p>Secondary spread is by wind-borne sporangia. The pathogen in the soil spreads through irrigation water, transport of soil, farm implements and animals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Cover the seed beds with paddy husk or groundnut shell at 15-20 cm thick layer and burn.</p><p>• Provide adequate drainage in the nursery. Drench the nursery beds with 1 per cent Bordeaux mixture or 0.2 per cent Copper oxychloride, two days before sowing.</p><p>• Spray the beds two weeks after sowing with 0.2 per cent Metalaxyl or 0.2 per cent Captafol or 0.2 per cent Copper oxychloride or 1 per cent Boreaux mixture and repeat after 10 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sporangia</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 92</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• Select healthy, disease free seedlings for transplanting.</p><p>• Remove and destroy the affected plants in the field.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 2 kg or Copper oxychloride 1 kg or Ziram 1 lit/ha. Spot drench with 0.4 per cent Bordeaux mixture or 0.2 per cent Copper oxychloride.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Frog eye spot -Cercospora nicotianae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears mostly on mature, lower leaves as small ashy grey spots with brown border. The typical spots have a white centre, surrounded in succession by grey, brown portions with a dark brown to black margin, resembling the eyes of a frog. Under favorable conditions, several spots coalesce to form large necrotic areas, causing the leaf to dry up from the margin and wither prematurely. Both yield and quality are reduced greatly. The disease may occur in the seedlings also, leading to withering of leaves and death of the seedlings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The mycelium is intercellular and collects beneath the epidermis and clusters of conidiophores emerge through stomata. The conidiophores are septate, dark brown at the base and lighter towards the top bearing 2-3 conidia. The conidia are hyaline, slender, slightly curved, thinwalled and 2-12 septate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable Conditions</head><p>• Temperature of 20-30˚C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 93</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• High humidity (80-90 per cent).</p><p>• Close spacing, frequent irrigation and excess application of nitrogenous fertilizers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen is seed-borne and also persists on crop residues in the soil. The primary infection is from the seed and soil-borne inoculum. The secondary spread is through wind-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and burn plant debris in the soil.</p><p>• Avoid excess nitrogenous fertilization.</p><p>• Adopt optimum spacing.</p><p>• Regulate irrigation frequency.</p><p>• Spray the crop with 0.4 per cent Bordeaux mixture or Thiophanate Methyl 750g/ha or Carbendazim 750 g/ha and repeat after 15 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mildew -Erysiphe cichoracearum var. nicotianae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initially the disease appears as small, white isolated patches on the upper surface of the leaves. Later, it spreads fast and covers the entire lamina. The disease initially appears on the lower leaves and as disease advances, the rest of the leaves are also infected and sometimes powdery growth can be seen on the stem also. The affected leaves turn to brown and wither and show scorched appearance. The severe infection leads to defoliation and reduction in quantity and quality of the curable leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus is ecotophytic and produces hyaline, septate and highly branched mycelium.</p><p>Short, stout and hyaline conidiophores arise from the mycelium and bear conidia in chains. The conidia are barrel shaped or cylindrical, hyaline and thin walled. Cleistothecia are black, spherical with no ostiole, with numerous densely-woven septate, brown-coloured appendages.</p><p>They contain 10-15 asci which are ovate with a short stalk. Each ascus contains two ascospores which are oval to elliptical, thinwalled, hyaline and single celled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri Www.HortiAgri.Com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Humid cloudy weather.</p><p>• Low temperature (16-23˚C.</p><p>• Close planting and excess doses of nitrogenous fertilizers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus remains dormant as mycelium and cleistothecia in the infected plant debris in soil. The primary infection is mainly from soil-borne inoculum. The secondary spread is aided by wind blown conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Apply balanced ferilizers.</p><p>• Avoid overcrowding of plants.</p><p>• Remove and destroy the affected leaves.</p><p>• Plant early in the season so that crop escapes the cool temperature at maturity phase.</p><p>• Spray dinocap at 375 ml or Carbendazim at 500g/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Brown spot -Alternaria longipes</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Brown spot in contrast to frog-eye spot is not normally observed in the nursery but is very much prevalent in the field. Initially it appears on lower and older leaves as small brown, circular lesions, which</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conidia and conidiophores</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri spread, to upper leaves, petioles, stalks and capsules even. In warm weather (30 ˚ C) under high humidity, the leaf spots enlarge, 1-3 cm in diameter, centres are necroses and turn brown with characteristic marking giving target board appearance with a definite outline. In severe infection spots enlarge, coalesce and damage large areas making leaf dark-brown, ragged and worthless.</p><p>On leaves nearing maturity, leaf spots are surrounded by bright yellow halo, due to production of toxin 'alternin' by the fungus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus over summers in the soil as mycelium in the diseased plant debris such as stems of tobacco, weeds and other hosts. Under favourable weather in the next season conidial production starts which infect the lowermost leaves. As the season progresses, repeated infection cycles of the fungus attack healthy tissues of all aerial parts of tobacco of any age under high humidity. There is enormous spore density in the air near the end of the harvesting. Fungus persists as a mycelium in dead tissue for several months.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Removal and destruction of diseased plant debris can check the primary infection promptly.</p><p>• Continuous growing of tobacco after tobacco must be avoided in the heavily infected fields.</p><p>• Weekly, spraying of fungicides such as Maneb or Zineb @ 2g/ha or Benomyl or</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Thiophanate methyl</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Several spots may coalesce to cause necrotic patches on the leaves. In advanced conditions, the entire leaf is fully covered with enlarged spots with yellow haloes. The leaves slowly wither and dry. Under humid weather condition, the disease spreads very fast and covers all the leaves and the entire plant gives a blighted appearance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The bacterium is a rod, motile with a single polar flagellum, non-capsulated, non spore forming and Gram negative.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Close planting.</p><p>• Humid wet weather.</p><p>• Strong winds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disaease cycle</head><p>The bacterium survives in the infected crop residues in the soil, which is the primary source of infection. The secondary spread of the pathogen in the field is through wind splashed rain water and implements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and burn the infected crop residues in the soil.</p><p>• Avoid very close planting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Tobacco mosaic -Tobacco mosaic virus (TMV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The disease begins as light discoloration along the veins of the youngest leaves. Soon the leaves develop a characteristic light and dark green pattern, the dark green areas associated more with the veins, turning into irregular blisters.</p><p>The early infected plants in the season are usually stunted with small, chlorotic, mottled and curled leaves. In severe infections, the leaves are narrowed, puckered, thin and malformed beyond recognition, Later, dark brown necrotic spots develop under hot weather and this symptom is called "Mosaic burn" or "Mosaic scorching".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The disease is caused by Tobacco mosaic tobamovirus. It is a rigid rod measuring 300 X 150-180 nm with a central hollow tube of about 4nm diameter with ssRNA as its genome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The virus spreads most rapidly by contact wounds, sap and farm implements and operators. The </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and destroy infected plants.</p><p>• Keep the field free of weeds which harbour the virus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 99</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• Wash hands with soap and running water before or after handling the plants or after weeding.</p><p>• Prohibit smoking, chewing and snuffing during field operations.</p><p>• Spray the nursery and main field with botanical leaf extracts of Bougainvillea or Basella alba at 1 litre of extract in 150 litres of water, two to three times at weekly intervals.</p><p>• Adopt crop rotation by growing non-host plants for two seasons.</p><p>• Grow resistant varieties like TMV RR2, TMV RR 2a and TMV RR3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf curl -Tobacco leaf curl virus (TLCV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The virus has a narrow host range in eight plant families. The virus is not transmissible through sap or seed. The whitefly, Bemisia tabaci is the vector. Due to wide host range of the virus many other plants are acting as source of inoculums.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and destroy the infected plants.</p><p>• Rogue out the reservoir weed hosts which harbour the virus and whiteflies. Planting tobacco crop during the crop periods when the vector population is low.</p><p>• Spray Methyldemeton at 0.1 to 0.2 per cent to control the vectors.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phanerogamic parasite</head><p>Broom rape -Orobanche cernua var. desertorum</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The seeds of the parasite remain dormant in the soil for several years. Primary infection occurs from the seeds in the soil. The seeds spread from field to field by irrigation water, animals, human beings and implements. The dormant seeds are stimulated to germinate by the root exudates of tobacco and attach itself, to the roots by forming haustoria. Later, it grows rapidly to produce shoot and flowers. Orobanche also attacks other crops like brinjal, tomato, cauliflower, turnip and other cruciferous crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out the tender shoots of the parasite before flowering and seed set.</p><p>• Spray the soil with 25 per cent copper sulphate.</p><p>• Spray 0.1 per cent Allyl alcohol.</p><p>• Apply few drops of kerosene directly on the shoot.</p><p>• Grow decoy or trap crops like chilli, moth bean, sorghum or cowpea to stimulate seed germination and kill the parasite.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="9.">Diseases of Groundnut</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease occurs on all above ground parts of the plant, more severely on the leaves.</p><p>The leaf symptoms produced by the two pathogens can be easily distinguished by appearance, spot colour and shapes. Both the fungi produce lesions also on petiole, stem and pegs. The lesions caused by both species coalesce as infection develops and severely spotted leaves shed prematurely. The quality and yield of nuts are drastically reduced in severe infections.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen C. arachidicola (Sexual stage: M. arachidis) Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The pathogen is intercellular and do not produce haustoria and become intracellular when host cells die. The fungus produces abundant sporulation on the upper surface of the leaves.</p><p>Conidiophores are olivaceous brown or yellowish brown in colour, short, 1 or 2 septate, unbranched and geniculate and arise in clusters.</p><p>Conidia are sub hyaline or pale yellow, obclavate, often curved 3-12 septate, 35-110 x 2.5 -5.4 m in size with rounded to distinctly truncate base and sub-acute tip. The perfect stage of the fungus produces perithecia as ascostromata. They are globose with papillate ostiole. Asci are cylindrical to clavate and contain 8 ascospores. Ascospores are hyaline, slightly curved and two celled, apical cell larger than the lower cell.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>P. personata (C. personata) (Sexual stage: M. berkeleyii)</head><p>The fungus produces internal and intercellular mycelium with the production of haustoria. The conidiphores are long, continuous, 1-2 septate, geniculate, arise inclusters and olive brown in colour. The conidia are cylindrical or obclavate, short, measure 18-60 x 6-10 m, hyaline to olive brown, usually straight or curved slightly with 1-9 septa, not constricted but mostly 3-4 septate. The fungus in its perfect stage produces perithecia as ascostromata which are globose or broadly ovate with papillate ostiole. Asci are cylindrical to ovate, contain 8 ascospores. Ascospores are 2 celled and constricted at septum and hyaline.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Prolonged high relative humidity for 3 days.</p><p>• Low temperature (20 C) with dew on leaf surface.</p><p>• Heavy doses of nitrogen and phosporus fertilizers</p><p>• Deficiency of magesium in soil.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives for a long period in the infected plant debris through conidia, dormant mycelium and perithecia in soil. The volunteer groundnut plants also harbour the pathogen. The primary infection is by ascospores or conidia from infected plant debris or infectd seeds. The secondary spread is by wind blown conidia. Rain splash also helps in the spread of conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and destory the infected plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 104</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• Eradicate the volunteer groundnut plants.</p><p>• Keep weeds under control.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim or Thiram at 2g/kg.</p><p>• Spray Carbendazim 500g or mancozeb 2 kg or Chlorothalonil 2 kg/ha and if necessary, repeat after 15 days.</p><p>• Grow moderately resistant varieties like ALR 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rust -Puccinia arachidis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease attacks all aerial parts of the plant. The disease is usually found when the plants are about 6 weeks old. Small brown to chestnut dusty pustules (uredosori) appear on the lower surface of leaves. The epidermis ruptures and exposes a powdery mass of uredospores.</p><p>Corresponding to the sori, small, necrotic, brown spots appear on the upper surface of leaves.</p><p>The rust pustules may be seen on petioles and stem. Late in the season, brown teliosori, as dark pustules, appear among the necrotic patches. In severe infection lower leaves dry and drop prematurely. The severe infection leads to production of small and shriveled seeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The pathogen produces both uredial and telial stages. Uredial stages are produced abundant in groundnut and production of telia is limited. Uredospores are pedicellate,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri unicellular, yellow, oval or round and echinulated with 2 or 3 germpores. Teliospores are dark brown with two cells. Pycnial and aecial stages have not been recorded and there is no information available about the role of alternate host.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Teliospores Uredospores</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High relative humidity (above 85 per cent).</p><p>• Heavy rainfall.</p><p>• Low temperature (20-25˚C).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives as uredospores on volunter groundnut plants. The fungus also survives in infected plant debris in soil. The spread is mainly through wind borne inoculum of uredospores. The uredospores also spread as contamination of seeds and pods. Rainsplash and implements also help in dissemination. The fungus also survives on the collateral hosts like Arachis marginata, A. nambyquarae and A. prostrate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Avoid monoculturing of groundnut.</p><p>• Remove volunteer groundnut plants and reservoir hosts.</p><p>• Spray mancozeb 2 kg or Wettable Sulphur 3 kg or Tridemorph 500ml or Chlorothalonil 2 kg/ha.</p><p>• Grow moderatelyresistant varieties like ALR 1.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collar rot or seedling blight or crown rot -Aspergillus niger and A. pulverulentum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 106</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>The disease usually appears in three phases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i. Pre-emergence rot</head><p>Seeds are attacked by soil-borne conidia and caused rotting of seeds. The seeds are covered with black masses of spores and internal tissues of seed become soft and watery.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ii. Post-emergence rot</head><p>The pathogen attacks the emerging young seedling and cause circular brown spots on the cotyledons. The symptom spreads later to the hypocotyl and stem. Brown discolored spots appear on collar region. The affected portion become soft and rotten, resulting in the collapse of the seedling. The collar region is covered by profuse growth of fungus and conidia and affected stem also show shredding symptom.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>iii. Crown rot</head><p>The infection when occurs in adult plants show crown rot symptoms. Large lesions develop on the stem below the soil and spread upwards along the branches causing drooping of leaves and wilting of plant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The mycelium of the fungus is hyaline to sub-hyaline. Conidiophores arise directly from the substrate and are septate, thick walled, hyaline or olive brown in colour. The vesicles are mostly globose and have two rows of hyaline phialides</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The conidial head are dark brown to black. The conidia are globose, dark brown in colour and produce in long chains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Deep sowing of seeds.</p><p>• High soil temperature (30-35˚ C).</p><p>• Low soil moisture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survive in plant debris in the soil, not necessarily from a groundnut crop. Soil-borne conidia cause disease carry over from season to season. The other primary source is the infeced seeds. The pathogen is also seedborne in nature.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Crop rotation.</p><p>• Destruction of plant debris.</p><p>• Remove and destroy previous season's infested crop debris in the field</p><p>• Seed treatment with Trichoderma viride / T.harzianum @ 4 g/kg of seeds and soil application of Trichoderma viride / T.harzianum at 2.5kg/ha, preferably with organic amendments such as castor cake or neem cake or mustard cake @ 500 kg/ ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Root rot -Macrophomina phaseolina</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>In the early stages of infection, reddish brown lesion appears on the stem just above the soil level. The leaves and branches show drooping, leading to death of the whole plant. The decaying stems are covered with whitish mycelial growth. The death of the plant results in shredding of bark. The rotten tissues contain large number of black or dark brown, thick walled sclerotia. When infection spreads to underground roots, the sclerotia are formed externally as well as internally in the rotten tissue. Pod infection leads to blackening of the shells and sclerotia can be seen inside the shells.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces hyaline to dull brown mycelium. The sclerotia are thick walled and dark brown in colour.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Prolonged rainy season at seedling stage and low lying areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus remains dormant as sclerotia for a long period in the soil and in infected plant debris. The primary infection is through soil-borne and seed-borne sclerotia. The secondary spread of sclerotia is aided by irrigation water, human agency, implements and cattle etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with thiram or carbendazim 2g/kg or Trichoderma viride at 4g/kg.</p><p>• Spot drench with Carbendazim at 0.5 g/lit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rossette -Groundnut rosette assistor virus (GRAV), Groundnut rosette virus and Groundnut rosette satellites</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The affected plants are characterized by the appearance of dense clump or dwarf shoots with tuft of small leaves forming in a rosette fashion. The plant exhibits chlorosis and mosaic mottling. The infected plants remain stunted and produce flowers, but only a few of the pegs may develop further to nuts but no seed formation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The disease is caused by a complex mixture of viruses viz.,Groundnut rosette assistor virus (GRAV), Ground nut rosette virus and Groundnut rosette satellites is an isometric, not enveloped and 28nm diameter (reported from India) and it gives no overt symptom in groundnut.</p><p>Groundnut rosette virus is with ssRNA genome, which becomes packaged in GRAV virious and thus depends on it for aphid transmission, but produces no overt symptoms in groundnut. The</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management groundnut rosette satellites are satellite RNAs that control the symptoms and cause the different types of rosette (chlorotic, green and mosaic).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The primary source of spread by aphid vector, Aphis craccivora and A. gossipii in a persistent manner, retained by vector but not transmitted congenitally. The virus is not transmitted by any other means like mechanical or seed or pollen. The virus can survive on the volunteer plants of groundnut and other weed hosts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Practice clean cultivation.</p><p>• Use heavy seed rate and rogue out the infected plants periodically.</p><p>• Spray Monocrotophos or Methyl demeton at 500 ml/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Groundnut bud necrosis disease -Groundnut bud necrosis virus (GBNV-Tospo virus) Symptoms</head><p>First symptoms are visible 2-6 weeks after infection as ring spots on leaves. The newly emerging leaves are small, rounded or pinched inwards and rugose with varying patterns of mottling and minute ring spots. Necrotic spots and irregularly shaped lesions develop on leaves and petioles. Stem also exhibits necrotic streaks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Plant becomes stunted with short internodes and short auxillary shoots. Leaflets show reduction in size, distortion of the lamina, mosaic mottling and general chlorosis. In advanced conditions, the necrosis of buds occurs. Top bud is killed and necrosis spreads downwards.</p><p>Drastic reduction in flowering and seeds produced are abnormally small and wrinkled with the dark black lesions on the testa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>It is caused by Groundnut bud necrosis virus (GBNV). The virus particles are spherical, 30 nm in diameter, enveloped, ssRNA with multipartite genome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The virus perpetuates in the weed hosts viz., Bidens pilosa, Erigon bonariensis, Tagetes minuta and Trifolium subterraneum. The virus is transmitted by thrips viz., Thrips palmi, T. tabaci and Frankliniella sp.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Adopt plant spacing of 15x15 cm.</p><p>• Remove and destory infected plants up to 6 weeks after sowing.</p><p>• Application of Monocrotophos 500 ml/ha, 30 days after sowing either alone or in combination with AVP (Anti Viral Principle) extracted from sorghum or coconut leaves.</p><p>Spray the crop with 10 per cent AVP at 500 lit/ha, ten and twenty days after sowing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stem rot -Sclerotium rolfsii</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The first symptom is the sudden drying of a branch which is completely or partially in contact with the soil. The leaves turn brown and dry but remain attached to the plant. Near soil on stems white growth of fungus mycelium is appeared. As the disease advances white mycelium web spreads over the soil and the basal canopy of the plant. The sclerotia, the size and colour of mustard seeds, appear on the infected areas as the disease develops and spreads. The entire plant may be killed or only two or three branches may be affected. Lesions on the developing pegs can retard pod development. Infected pods are usually rotted.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri chlorotic. The leaflets are reduced in size with pointed tips, widely varied in shape and sometimes with veinal clearing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Since the fungus is a weak parasite, agronomic practices which favour rapid germination and vigorous growth of seedling will reduce the chance of A. flavus infection.</p><p>• Seed treatment with carbendazim or captan or thiram at 2g/kg seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grey mould -Botrytis cinerea</head><p>Infection is seen on leaves, stem and underground parts of the groundnut. Initially infection occurs at ground level by a light grey fungal rot which causes death of the plants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial wilt -Pseudomonas solanacearum</head><p>Infected plants appear unhealthy, chlorotic and wilt under water stress. Dark brown discolouration of xylem is seen. Grey slimy liquid ooze out of the vascular bundles. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Alternaria arachidis and A. tenuissima</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="10.">Diseases of Castor</head><p>Seedling blight -Phytophthora parasitica</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears circular, dull green patch on both the surface of the cotyledon leaves.</p><p>It later spreads and causes rotting. The infection moves to stem and causes withering and death of seedling. In mature plants, the infection initially appears on the young leaves and spreads to petiole and stem causing black discoloration and severe defoliation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dead seedling</head><p>Spot on older leaf Leaf blight symptom</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The pathogen produces non-septate and hyaline mycelium. Sporangiophores emerge through the stomata on the lower surface singly or in groups. They are unbranched and bear single celled, hyaline, round or oval sporangia at the tip singly. The sporangia germinate to produce abundant zoospores. The fungus also produces oospores and chlamydospores in adverse seasons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Continuous rainy weather.</p><p>• Low temperature (20-25˚C).</p><p>• Low lying and ill drained soils.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen remains in the soil as chlamydospores and oospores which act as primary source of infection. The fungus also survives on other hosts like potato, tomato, brinjal, sesamum etc. The secondary spread takes place through wind borne sporangia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and destroy infected plant residues.</p><p>• Avoid low-lying and ill drained fields for sowing.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with thiram or captan at 4g/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rust -Melampsora ricini</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Minute, orange-yellow coloured, raised pustules appear with powdery masses on the lower surface of the leaves and the corresponding areas on the upper surface of the leaves are yellow. Often the pustules are grouped in concentric rings and coalesce together to for drying of leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mass covering entire leaf</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The pathogen produces only uredosori in castor plants and other stages of the life cycle are unknown. Uredospores are two kinds, one is thick walled and other is thin walled. They are elliptical to round, orange-yellow coloured and finely warty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the self sown castor crops in the off season. It can also survive on other species of Ricinus. The fungus also attacks Euphorbia obtusifolia, E.geniculata and E.marginata. The infection spreads through airborne uredospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Spraying with 1% Bordeaux mixture or Copper oxy chloride @ 0.2% may help to bring the disease under check; but where the cultures of Eri-silk worm are maintained on castor plants, spraying would not be desirable.</p><p>• Use of resistant varieties would be the most effective method for combating the disease.</p><p>• Spraying twice with Mancozeb 2g/lit or Carbendazim 500g/ha at 10-15 day interval reduces the disease incidence.</p><p>• Treat the seed with thiram or Captan 2gm/kg seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mildew -Leveillula taurica</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>It is characterized by typical mildew growth which is generally confined to the undersurface of the leaf. When the infection is severe the upper-surface is also covered by the whitish growth of the fungus. Light green patches, corresponding to the diseased areas on the under surface, are visible on the upper side especially when the leaves are held against light.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mass covering entire leaf</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• When weather is comparatively dry spray twice with wettable Sulphur 2g/lit at 15 days interval, starting from 3 months after sowing.</p><p>• Spray 1ml hexaconazole or 2ml dinocap / litre of water at fortnight intervals. The variety Jwala is resistant to this disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stem rot -Macrophomina phaseolina</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Small brown depressed lesions on and around nodes. Increase in size on both directions causing 2 to 20 cm necrotic area. Lesions often coalesce and girdle the stem causing leaf drop.</p><p>Google -HortiAgri 120</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Selection of disease free seeds.</p><p>• Grow tolerant and resistant varieties like Jyothi, Jwala, GCH-4 DCH-30 and SHB 145.</p><p>• Avoid water logging</p><p>• Burning of crop debris</p><p>• Green manuring and intercropping with red gram</p><p>• Treat the seeds with thiram @ 2g/ kg or carbendiazim @ 2g/ kg seed.</p><p>• Seed treatment with 4g of Trichoderma viride talc formulation.</p><p>• Multiplication of 2kg of T.viride formulation by mixing in 50kg farm yard manure</p><p>• Sprinkling water and covering with polythene sheet for 15days and then applying between rows of the crops is helpful in reducing the incidence. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces a large number of black, round to irregular shaped sclerotia. The pycnidia are dark brown to black with an ostiole and contain numerous single celled, thin walled, hyaline and elliptical pycnidiospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The pathogen produces cylindrical conidiophores, which are pale grey-yellow coloured, straight or curved, geniculate, simple or branched, septate and bear single conidium. Conidia are cylindrical to long ellipsoid, straight or slightly curved, pale grey-yellow to pale brown, 1 to 2 septate with longitudinal septa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Rainy weather.</p><p>• Cool winter climate.</p><p>• Late sown crops are highly susceptible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected host tissues and weed hosts. The fungus is also seedborne. The secondary spread is mainly through wind blown conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep summer ploughing.</p><p>• Proper spacing</p><p>• Clean cultivation and field sanitation.</p><p>• Use of resistant or tolerant variety like B.S.H.1 .</p><p>• Application of well rotten manures.</p><p>• Practicing crop rotation.</p><p>• Planting in mid-September.</p><p>• Remove and destroy the diseased plants</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Thiram or Carbendazim at 2 g/kg. Spray Mancozeb at 2 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 126</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rust -Puccinia helianthi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Small, reddish brown pustules (uredia) covered with rusty dust appear on the lower surface of bottom leaves. Infection later spreads to other leaves and even to the green parts of the head. In severe infection, when numerous pustules appear on leaves, they become yellow and dry. The black coloured telia are also seen among uredia on the lower surface. The disease is autoecious rust. The pycnial and aecial stages occur on volunteer crops grown during off-season.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The uredospores are round or elliptical, dark cinnamon-brown in colour and minutely echinulated with 2 equatorial germpores. Teliospores are elliptical or oblong, two celled, smooth walled and cheshnut brown in colour with a long, colourless pedicel.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable Conditions</head><p>• Day temperature of 25.5° to 30.5°C with relative humidity of 86 to 92 per cent enhances intensity of rust attack.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Uredospores and Teliospores</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable Conditions</head><p>• The disease is more under dry condition to the end of the winter months.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Complete field and crop sanitation.</p><p>• Early varieties should be preferred.</p><p>• Removal of infected plant debris.</p><p>• Application of karathane or calixin 1L/ha or wettable sulphur 2 kg/ha is found effective in reducing the disease incidences. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Basal rot -Sclerotium rolfsii</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Day temperature of 30˚C and above</p><p>• Prolonged drought followed by copious irrigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus remains dormant as sclerotia in soil as well as in infected plant debris</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 134</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com in soil. The infected plant debris also carries pycnidia. The fungus primarily spreads through infected seeds which carry sclerotia and pycnidia. The fungus also spreads through soil-borne sclerotia. The secondary spread is through the conidia transmitted by wind and rain water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Seed treatment with carbendazim + thiram (1:1) at 2g/kg seed.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4g/kg.</p><p>• Apply farm yard manure or green leaf manure at 10t/ha or neem cake 150 kg/ha. Spot drench with Carbendazim at 1.0 g/litre.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf blight -Alternaria sesami</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initially small, circular, reddish brown spots (1-8mm) appear on leaves which enlarge later and cover large area with concentric rings. The lower surface of the spots are greyish brown in colour. In severe blighting defoliation occurs. Dark brown lesions can also be seen on petioles, stem and capsules. Infection of capsules results in premature splitting with shriveled seeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The mycelium of the fungus is dull brown and septate and produce large number of pale grey-yellow conidiophores which are straight or curved. The conidia are light olive coloured with transverse and longitudinal septa. These are around 3-5 septate and conidia are borne in chain over short conidiophore.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Low temperature (20-25˚C),</p><p>• High relative humidity</p><p>• Cloudy weather.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus is seed-borne and also soil-borne as it remains dormant in the infected plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with thiram or Carbendazim at 2g/kg.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb at 2kg/ha or Iprodion 1L/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 135</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Cercospora sesami</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease first appears on the leaves as minute water-soaked lesions, which enlarge to form round to irregular spots of 5-15 mm diameter on both the leaf surface. The spots coalesce to form irregular patches of varying size leading to premature defoliation. The infection is also seen on stem and petiole forming spots of varying lengths. Dark linear spots also occur on pods causing drying shedding.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The hypha of the fungus is irregularly septate, light brown and thick walled.</p><p>Conidiophores are produced in cluster and are 1-3 septate, hyaline at the tip and light brown coloured at base. Conidia are elongated, 7-10 septate, hyaline to light yellow, broad at the base and tapering towards the apex.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus is externally and internally seed-borne. The fungus also survives in plant debris. Primary infection may be from the seeds and infected debris. The secondary spread is through wind-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazin or Thiram at 2g/kg.</p><p>• Spray with Mancozeb at 2kg/ha. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wilt</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Prolonged rainfall,</p><p>• Low temperature (25˚C)</p><p>• High relative humidity (above 90 per cent)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus can survive in the soil through dormant mycelium and oospores. The seeds also carry the fungus as dormant mycelium, which causes the primary infection. Secondary spread of the disease is through wind-borne sporangia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with captan or thiram at 2g/kg or metalaxyl @ 4g/kg.</p><p>• Avoid continuous cropping of sesamum in the same field.</p><p>• Remove and destrosy infected plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 138</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• Spray metalaxyl 1kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mildew -Erysiphe cichoracearum (Syn: Oidium acanthospermi)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initially greyish-white powdery growth appears on the upper surface of leaves. When several spots coalesce, the entire leaf surface may be covered with powdery coating. In severe cases, the infection may be seen on the flowers and young capsules, leading to premature shedding. The severally affected leaves may be twisted and malformed. In the advanced stages of infection, the mycelial growth changes to dark or black because of development of cleistothecia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The Pathogen produces hyaline, septate mycelium which is extophytic and sends haustoria into the host epidermis. Conidiophores arise from the primary mycelium and are short and non septate bearing conidia in long chains. The conidia are ellipsoid or barrel-shaped, single celled and hyaline. The cleistothecia are dark, globose with the hyaline or pale brown myceloid appendages. The asci are ovate and each ascus produces 2-3 ascospores, which are thin walled, elliptical and pale brown in colour.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Dry humid weather.</p><p>• Low relative humidity.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management 139</p><p>Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>The Pathogen is an obligate parasite and disease perennates through cleistothecia in the infected plant debris in soil. The ascospores from the cleistothecia cause primary infection. The secondary spread is through wind-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove the infected plant debris and destroy.</p><p>• Spray wettable sulphur at 2.5 kg/ha or karathane 1L/ha repeat after 15 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial leaf spot -Xanthomonas campestris pv. sesami</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initially water-soaked spots appear on the undersurface of the leaf and then on the upper surface. They increase in size, become angular and restricted by veins and dark brown in color.</p><p>Several spots coalesce together forming irregular brown patches and cause drying of leaves. The reddish brown lesions may also occur on petioles and stem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The bacterium is a Gram negative rod with a monotrichous flagellum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The bacterium survives in the infected plant debris and in seeds. The secondary spread is by rain water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and burn infected plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Spray Streptomycin sulphate or oxytetracycline hydrochloride or strephocyclin at 100g/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial leaf spot -Pseudomonas sesami</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears as water-soaked yellow specks on the upper surface of the leaves.</p><p>They enlarge and become angular as resticted by veins and veinlets. The colour of spot may be dark brown with shiny oozes of bacterial masses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The bacterium is gram negative aerobic rod with one or more polar flagella.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The bacterium remains viable in the infected plant tissues. It is internally seedborne and secondary spread through rain splash and storms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Keep the field free of infected plant debris.</p><p>• Spray with Streptomycin sulphate or oxytetracycline hydrochloride or streptocyclin at 100g/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phyllody -Phytoplasma</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen has a wide host range and survives on alternate hosts like Brassica campestris var. toria, B. rapa, Cicer arietinum, Crotalaria sp., Trifolium sp., Arachis hypogaea which serve as source of inoculum. The disease is transmitted by jassid, Orosius albicinctus.</p><p>Optimum acquisition period of vector is 3-4 days and inoculation feeding period is 30 minutes.</p><p>The incubation period of the pathogen in leaf hoppers may be 15-63 days and 13-61 days in sesame. Nymphs are incapable of transmitting the phytoplasma. Vector population is more during summer and less during winter months.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove all the reservoir and weed hosts.</p><p>• Avoid growing sesamum near cotton, groundnut and grain legumes.</p><p>• Rogue out the infected plants periodically.</p><p>• Spray Monocrotophos or Dimethoate at 500ml/ha to control the jassids</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Soil treatment with Thirnet 10G @ 10 kg/ha or Phorate 10 G @ 11 kg/ha at the time of sowing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor disease</head><p>Anthracnose -Colletotrichum sp.</p><p>Dark brown lesions on leaf stem and capsules with black acervuli in the central portion.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives during the summer in the infected crop residues. The perennial cotton plants and self-sown cotton plants also harbour the pathogen during summer months. The primary infection is through conidia from infected plant debris and secondary spread is through wind, rain splash, irrigation water and implements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p> Remove and burn the infected crop residues.</p><p> Rogue out the self-sown cotton plants during summer months.</p><p> Avoid excessive application of nitrogenous fertilizers/manures.</p><p> Adopt the correct spacing based on soil conditions and varieties.</p><p> Spray the crop with Carbendazim at 500g/ha, repeat after a week.</p><p> Grow the resistant varieties like Sujatha and Varalakshmi.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Boll rot -Fungal complex</head><p>It is a complex disease caused by several fungal pathogens viz., Fusarium moniliforme, Colletotrichum capsici, Aspergillus flavus, A. niger, Rhizopus nigricans, Nematospora nagpuri and Botryodiplodia sp.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives in the dead leaves as dormant mycelium. The pathogen primarily spreads through irrigation water. The secondary spread is mainly by airborne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p> Remove and destroy the infected plant residues.</p><p> Spray Mancozeb 2 kg or Copper oxychloride at 2kg/ha at the intimation of the disease.</p><p>Four to five sprays may be given at 15 days interval.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial blight -Xanthomonas axonopodis pv. malvacearum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The bacterium attacks all stages from seed to harvest. Usually five common phases of symptoms are noticed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i) Seedling blight:</head><p>Small, water-soaked, circular or irregular lesions develop on the cotyledons, later, the infection spreads to stem through petiole and cause withering and death of seedlings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ii) Angular leaf spot:</head><p>Small, dark green, water soaked areas develop on lower surface of leaves, enlarge gradually and become angular when restricted by veins and veinlets and spots are visible on both the surface of leaves. As the lesions become older, they turn to reddish brown colour and infection spreads to veins and veinlets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>iii) Vein blight or vein necrosis or black vein:</head><p>The infection of veins cause blackening of the veins and veinlets, gives a typical 'blighting' appearance. On the lower surface of the leaf, bacterial oozes are formed as crusts or scales. The affected leaves become crinkled and twisted inward and show withering. The infection also spreads from veins to petiole and cause blighting leading to defoliation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>iv) Black arm:</head><p>On the stem and fruiting branches, dark brown to black lesions are formed, which may girdle the stem and branches to cause premature drooping off of the leaves, cracking of stem and</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The primary source is the viruliferous whitefly vector Bemisia tabaci. The alternate hosts and cultivated hosts serve as virus reservoirs throughout the year. Not transmitted by seed or contact.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p> Management of planting date to avoid peak vector population.  Foliar application of neem leaf extract and 1% neem oil resulted in 80% reduction of virus transmission.</p><p> Vector management by application of granular systemic insecticides.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears when the plants are two to three months old and affected plants are stunted. They put forth numerous extremely small leaves in cluster and the dormant buds are stimulated resulting in profuse vegetative growth. The leaves are disfigured and variously lobed.</p><p>Flowers remain small with abortive ovary.</p><p>Large number of flower buds and young seeds. Root system is poorly developed and can be easily pulled out. Sometimes, the disease affects only the base of the plant, resulting in the formation of clump of short branches which bear small and deformed leaves. The mode of transmission of disease and the role of vector are unknown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="14.">Diseases of Red Gram</head><p>Wilt -Fusarium udum</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease may appear from early stages of plant growth (4-6 week old plant) up to flowering and podding. The disease appears as gradual withering and drying of plants.</p><p>Yellowing of leaves and blackening of stem starting from collar to branches which gradually result in drooping and premature drying of leaves, stems, branches and finally death of plant.</p><p>Vascular tissues exhibit brown discoloration. Often only one side of the stem and root system is affected resulting in partial wilting.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces hyaline, septate mycelium. Microconidia are hyaline, small, elliptical or curved, single celled or two celled. Macroconidia are also hyaline, thin walled, linear, curved or fusoid, pointed at both ends with 3-4 septa. The fungus also poduce thick walled, spherical or oval, terminal or intercalary chlamydospores singly or in chains of 2 to 3.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• Soil temperature of 17-25˚C.</p><p>• Continuous cultivation of redgram in the same field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected stubbles in the field. The primary spread is by soilborne chlamydospores and also by infected seed. Chlamydospores remain viable in soil for 8-20 years. The secondary spread in the field is through irrigation water and implements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4 g/kg (10 6 cfu/g).</p><p>• Avoid successive cultivation of red gram in the same field.</p><p>• Crop rotation with tobacco.</p><p>• Mixed cropping with sorghum in the field. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Soils with poor drainage,</p><p>• Low lying areas,</p><p>• Heavy rain during the months of July-September</p><p>• High temperature (28-30˚C).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the soil and plant debris in the form of oospores. Primary infection is from oospores and secondary spread of the disease by zoospores from sporangia.</p><p>Rain splash and irrigation water help for the movement of zoospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Metalaxyl at 6 g/kg.</p><p>• Spray Metalaxyl at 500 g/ha.</p><p>• Adjust the sowing time so that crop growth should not coincide with heavy rainfall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Cercospora indica</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Small, light brown coloured spots appear on leaves. The spots later become dark brown and the infected portions drop off leaving shot hole symptoms. When several spots join together, irregular necrotic blotches develop and premature defoliation occurs. In severe cases, black lesions develop on petioles and stem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Rust -Uromyces phaseoli typica (Syn: U. appendiculatus)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease is mostly seen on leaves, rarely on petioles, stem and pods. The fungus produces small, round, reddish brown uredosori mostly on lower surface. They may appear in </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Cloudy humid weather, temperature of 21-26˚ C</p><p>• Nights with heavy dews</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mode of Spread and Survival</head><p>The pathogen survives in the soil through teliospores and as uredospores in crop debris.</p><p>Primary infection is by the sporidia developed from teliospores. Secondary spread is by windborne uredospores. The fungus also survives on other legume hosts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove the infected plant debris and destroy.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 2 kg or Carbendazim 500 g or Propiconazole 1L/ha, immediately on the set of disease and repeat after 15 days. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dry</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces dark brown, septate mycelium with constrictions at hyphal branches. Minute, dark, round sclerotia in abundance. The fungus also produces dark brown, globose ostiolated pycnidia on the host tissues. The pycnidiospores are thin walled, hyaline, single celled and elliptical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• Day temperature of 30˚C.</p><p>• Prolonged dry season followed by irrigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Begomovirus belonging to the family geminiviridae. Geminate virus particles, ssDNA, bipartite genome with two gemonic components DNA-A and DNA-B.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Transmitted by whitefly, Bemisia tabaci under favourable conditions. Disease spreads by feeding of plants by viruliferous whiteflies. Summer sown crops are highly susceptible. Weed hosts viz., Croton sparsiflorus, Acalypha indica, Eclipta alba and other legume hosts serve as reservoir for inoculum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out the diseased plants up to 40 days after sowing.</p><p>• Remove the weed hosts periodically.</p><p>• Increase the seed rate (25 kg/ha).</p><p>• Grow resistant black gram variety like VBN-1, PDU 10, IC12/2 and PLU 322. Cultivate the crop during rabi season.</p><p>• Follow mixed cropping by growing two rows of maize (60 x 30 cm) or sorghum (45 x 15 cm) or cumbu (45 x 15 cm) for every 15 rows of black gram or green gram.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Thiomethoxam-70WS or Imidacloprid-70WS @4g/kg</p><p>• Spray Thiamethoxam-25WG @ 100g or Imidacloprid 17.8% SL @ 100 ml in 500 lit of water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf crinkle disease -Urdbean leaf crinkle virus (ULCV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Crinkling and curling of the tips of leaflets and increase in leaf area. Crinkling and rugosity in older leaves becomes severe and leaves thickened. Petioles as well as internodes are shortened. Infected plant gives a stunted and bushy appearance. Flowering is delayed, if inflorescence is formed, is malformed with small size flower buds and fails to open.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Casual organism of the disease is not yet ascertained.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Presence of weed hosts like Aristolochia bracteata and Digera arvensis. Kharif season crop and continuous cropping of other legumes serve as source of inoculum. The virus is seed-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• The seeds must be sown early in the month of June to avoid early incidence of the disease on the crop.</p><p>• . Spray Carbendazim 500g or Wettable sulphur 1.5 kg or Tridemorph 500 ml/ha at the initiation of disease and repeat 15 days later.</p><p>Anthracnose -Colletotrichum lindemuthianum -(Sexual stage: Glomerella lindemuthianum)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears on all aerial part parts and at any stage of plant growth. Circular, black, sunken spots with dark center and bright red orange margins on leaves and pods. In severe infections, the affected parts wither off. Seedlings get blighted due to infection soon after seed germination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The Disease appears on fungus mycelium is septate, hyaline and branched. Conidia are produced in acervuli, arise from the stroma beneath the epidermis and later rupture to become erumpent. A few dark coloured, septate setae are seen in the acervulus. The conidiophores are hyaline and short and bear oblong or cylindrical, hyaline, thinwalled, single celled conidia with oil globules. The perfect stage of the fungus produces perithecia with limited number of asci, which contain typically 8 ascospores which are one or two celled with a central oil globule.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• The disease is more sever in cool and wet seasons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus is seed-borne and cause primary infection. It also lives in the infected plant tissues in soil. The secondary spread by air borne conidia produced on infected plant parts. Rain splash also helps in dissemination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Hot water treatment at 54º for 10 min.</p><p>• Use disease free seed.</p><p>• Follow crop rotation</p><p>• Remove and destroy infected plant debris in soil.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim at 2 g/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p><p>• Spray Carbendazim 500g or Mancozeb 2kg/ha soon after the appearance of disease and repeat after 15 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Cercospora canescens</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>This is an important disease of green gram and is usually occurs in a severe form, causing heavy losses in yield. Spots produced are small, numerous in numbers with pale brown centre and reddish brown margin. Similar spots also occur on branches and pods. Under favourable environmental conditions, severe leaf spotting and defoliation occurs at the time of flowering and pod formation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces clusters of dark brown septate conidiophores. The conidia are linear, hyaline, thin walled and 5-6 septate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• High humidity favours disease development.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives on diseased plant debris and on seeds. The secondary spread is by air-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Cultivate resistant varieties.</p><p>• Intercrop the moong with tall growing cereals and millets.</p><p>• Follow clean cultivation.</p><p>• Use disease free seed.</p><p>• Maintain low crop population density and wide row planting.</p><p>• The crude extracts of cassava, garlic, and zinger are applied for controlling the disease effectively.</p><p>• Mulching reduces the disease incidence resulting in increase yield.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 2kg/ha or Carbendazim 500 g/ha.</p><p>Rust -Uromyces phaseoli typica (Syn: U. appendiculatus)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Smut or black smut -Tilletia barclayana Minute black pustules or streaks are formed on the grains which burst open at the time of ripening. The grains may be partially or entirely replaced by the fungal spores. The sorus pushes the glumes apart exposing the black mass of spores. Only a few flowers are infected in an inflorescence. The fungus survives as chlamydospores for one or more years under normal condition and 3 years in stored grains. Symptoms Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri Stem rot -Sclerotium oryzae (Sexual stage: Magnaporthe salvinii) Symptoms Small black lesions are formed on the outer leaf sheath and they enlarge and reach the inner leaf sheath also. The affected tissues rot and abundant small black sclerotia are seen in the rotting tissues. The culm collapses and plants lodge. The sclerotia are carried in stubbles after harvest.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Spray Streptomycin sulphate and tetracycline combination 300g + Copper oxychloride 1.25 Kg/ha. Viral Diseases Rice Tungro Disease (RTD) -Rice tungro bacilliform virus (RTBV) and Rice tungro spherical virus (RTSV) Symptoms Infection occurs both in the nursery and main field. Plants are markedly stunted. Leaves show yellow to orange discoloration and interveinal chlorosis. Young leaves are sometimes mottled while rusty spots appear on older leaves. Tillering is reduced with poor root system. Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Panicles not formed in very early infection, if formed, remain small with few, deformed and chaffy grains. Pathogen Two morphologically unrelated viruses present in phloem cells. Rice tungro bacilliform virus (RTBV) bacilliform capsid, circular ds DNA genome and Rice tungro spherical virus (RTSV) isometric capsid ss RNA genome. Disease Cycle Transmission mainly by the leaf hopper vector Nephotettix virescens Males, females and nymphs of the insect can transmit the disease. Both the particles are transmitted semipersistently, in the vector the particles are noncirculative and nonpropagative. Plants infected with RTSV alone may be symptomless or exhibit only mild stunting. RTBV enhances the symptoms caused by RTSV. RTSV can be acquired from the infected plant independently of RTBV, but acquisition of RTBV is dependent on RTSV which acts as a helper virus. Both the viruses thrive in rice and several weed hosts which serve as source of inoculum for the next. Ratoon from infected rice stubble serve as reservoirs of the virus. Disease incidence depends on rice cultivars, time of planting, time of infection and presence of vectors and favorable weather conditions Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mildew -Peronosclerospora sorghi Symptoms The fungus causes systemic downy mildew of sorghum. It invades the growing points of young plants, either through oospore or conidial infection. As the leaves unfold they exhibit green or yellow colouration. Abundant downy white growth is produced on the lower surface of the leaves, which consists of sporangiophores and sporangia. Normally three or four leaves develop the chlorotic downy growth. Subsequent leaves show progressively more of a complete bleaching of the leaf tissue in streaks or stripes. As the infected bleached leaves mature they become necrotic and the interveinal tissues disintegrate, releasing the resting spores (oospores) and leaving the vascular bundles loosely connected to give the typical shredded leaf symptom. Pathogen P. sorghi is an obligate parasite systemic in young plant. The mycelium is intercellular, non-septate. Sporangiophores emerge through the stomata in single or in clusters which are stout and dichotomously branched. Spores are single celled, hyaline, globose and thin walled.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>3.</head><label></label><figDesc>Diseases of Wheat Black or stem rust -Puccinia graminis tritici Symptoms Symptoms are produced on almost all aerial parts of the wheat plant but are most common on stem, leaf sheaths and upper and lower leaf surfaces. Uredial pustules (or sori) are oval to spindle shaped and dark reddish brown (rust) in color. They erupt through the epidermis of the host and are surrounded by tattered host tissue. The pustules are dusty in appearance due to the vast number of spores produced. Spores are readily released when touched. As the infection advances teliospores are produced in the same pustule. The color of the pustule changes from rust color to black as teliospore production progresses. If a large number of pustules are produced, stems become weakened and lodge. The pathogen attacks other host (barberry) to complete its life cycle. Symptoms are very different on this woody host. Other spores are Pycnia (spermagonia) produced on the upper leaf surface of barberry which appears as raised orange spots. Small amounts of honeydew that attracts insects are produced in this structure. Aecia, produced on the lower leaf surface, are yellow. They are bell-shaped and extend as far as 5 mm from the leaf surface.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Circular to oval, elongated cinnamon-brown powdery pustules are scattered over both surface of the leaves. As the plant matures, the pustules become brown to black owing to the replacement of red uredospores by black teliospores. Conidia Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri Pathogen Uredospores are globose or elliptical finely echinulate, yellowish brown with 4 germpores. Teliospores are brownish black, or dark brown, oblong to ellipsoidal, rounded to flattened at the apex. They are two celled and slightly constricted at the septum and the spore wall is thickened at the apex.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>6.</head><label></label><figDesc>Diseases of SugarcaneRed rot -Colletotrichum falcatum (Perfect stage: Physalospora tucumanensis)SymptomsThe first external symptom appears mostly on third or fourth leaf which withers away at the tips along the margins. Typical symptoms of red rot are observed in the internodes of a stalk by splitting it longitudinally. These include the reddening of the internal tissues which are usually elongated at right angles to the long axis of the stalk. The presence of cross-wise white patches are the important diagnostic character of the disease. The diseased cane also emits acidic-sour smell. As the disease advances, the stalk becomes hollow and covered with white mycelial growth.Later the rind shrinks longitudinally with minute black, velvetty fruiting bodies protruding out of it. The pathogen also produces tiny reddish lesions on the upper surface of leaves with dark dots in the centre. The lesions are initially blood red with dark margins and later on with straw coloured centres. Often the infected leaves may break at the lesions and hang down, with large number of minute black dots.PathogenThe fungus produces thin, hyaline, septate, profusely branched hyphae containing oil droplets. The fungus produces black, minute velvetty acervuli with long, rigid bristle-like, septate setae. Conidiophores are closely packed inside the acervulus, which are short, hyaline and single celled. The conidia are single celled, hyaline, falcate, granular and guttulate. Fungus Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri also produces large number of globose and dark brown to black perithecia with a papillate ostiole. Asci are clavate, unitunicate and eight-spored. Large number of hyaline, septate, filiform paraphyses is also present among asci. Ascospores are ellipsoid or fusoid, hyaline, straight or slightly curved and unicellular which measure 18-22 m x 7-8 m.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Rust-</head><label></label><figDesc>Puccinia erianthi (Syn: P. melanocephala and P. kuehnii) Symptoms Minute, elongated, yellow spots (uredia), usually 2-10 x 1-3 mm appear on both the surfaces of young leaves. The pustules turn to brown on maturity. Late in the season, dark brown to black telia appear on the lower surface of leaves. In severse cases, the uredia also appear on the leaf sheath and the entire foliage looks brownish from a distance. Pathogen The mycelium is hyaline, branched and septate. P.kuehnii produces ovoid or pear shaped, single celled uredospores measuring 29-57 x 8-37 m with apical thickening and golden yellow in colour. Teliospores are produced in scanty which are yellow in colour, club shaped, two celled, smooth walled and measuring 24-34 X 18-25 m single celled, dark yellow coloured with 4 equatorial pores. Teliospores are produced in abundance, which are pale to brick colour, two celled, smooth walled and slightly constricted at septum. Occurrence of pycnial and aecial stages and the role of alternate host are unknown.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>such canes are cut transversely or split open longitudinally, a dull yellow bacterial ooze comes out from the cut ends and bacterial pockets are seen inside the slitted cane. The fibro vasuclar bundles are deep red and internodal cavities formed in the severe cases are filled with yellow coloured bacterial gums.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Clavibacter xyli sub sp. xyli (Rickettsia Like Organism -RLO) Symptoms Diseased clumps usually display stunted growth, reduced tillering, thin stalks with shortened internodes and yellowish foliage. Orange-red vascular bundles in shades of yellow at the nodes are seen in the infected canes. Pathogen The pathogen (Clavibacter xyli sub sp. xyli) is a RLO known to be present in the xylem cells of infected plants. They are small, thin, rod shaped or coryneform (0.15 to 0.32 m wide and 1.0-2.7 m long) and Gram positive.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>complex disease caused by the nematode Pratylenchus sp. associated with Fusarium sp.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>virus remains viable in the plant debris in the soil as the source of inoculum as the longevity of the virus is very high. It is capable of remaining infective when stored dry for over 50 years. The virus has a wide host range, affecting nearly 50 plant species belonging to nine different families. The virus is not seed-transmitted in tobacco but tomato seeds transmit the virus. No insect vector known to transmit the virus.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>infections may occur at any stage, when young plants are infected the entire plant remains very much dwarfed. Curling of leaves with clearing and thickening of veins; twisting of petioles; puckering of leaves; rugose and brittle and development of enations are the important symptoms of tobacco leaf curl disease.Three forms of leaf curl expression are observed. First the leaf margins curl downward towards the dorsal side and show thickening of veins with enation on the lower surface. Second crinkle form shows curling of whole leaf edge towards dorsal side with enation on the veins and the lamina arching towards the ventral side between the veinlets. Third the transparent symptom shows the curling of leaves towards the ventral side with clearing of the veins and enations are absent. Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri Pathogen It is caused by Tobacco leaf curl geminivirus. Virions are geminate, non-enveloped, 18 nm diameter circular ssDNA genome.The virus is a white fly transmitted Geminivirus as genome.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>affected tobacco plants are stunted and show withering and drooping of leaves to wilting. These indicate underground parasitism of the tobacco roots by the parasite. The young shoot of the parasite emerges from the soil at the base of the plants 5-6 weeks after transplanting. Normally, it appears on clusters of 50-100 shoots around the base of a single tobacco plant. The plants which are attacked very late exhibit no external symptoms but the quality and yield of leaves are reduced. Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri Parasite It is a total root parasite. It is an annual, fleshy flowering plant with a short, stout stem, 10-15 inches long. The stem is pale yellow or brownish red in colour and covered by small, thin, brown scaly leaves and the base of the stem is thickened. White-coloured flowers appear in the leaf axils. The floral parts are well developed with a lobed calyx, tubular corolla, superior ovary, numerous ovules and a large four-lobed stigma. The fruits are capsules containing small, black, reticulate and ovoid seeds.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Lesions produced by A. arachidis are brown in colour and irregular in shape surrounded by yellowish halos. Symptoms produced by A. tenuissima are characterized by blighting of apical portions of leaflets which turn light to dark brown colour. Lesions produced by A. alternata are small, chlorotic, water soaked, that spread over the surface of the leaf. The lesions become necrotic and brown and are round to irregular in shape. Veins and veinlets adjacent to the lesions become necrotic. Lesions increase in area and their central portions become pale, rapidly dry out, and disintegrate. Affected leaves show chlorosis and in severe attacks become prematurely senescent. Lesions can coalesce, give the leaf a ragged and blighted appearance.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>charcoal rot -Rhizoctonia bataticola (Pycnidial stage: Macrophomina phaseolina) Symptoms The pathogen is seed-borne and primarily causes seedling blight and collar rot in the initial stages. The grown up plants also show symptoms after flowering stage. The infected plants show drooping of leaves and death occurs in patches. The bark of the lower stem and roots shreds and are associated with a large number of sclerotia. Dark coloured, minute pycnidia also develop on the lower portion of the stem.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Initial symptoms of the disease appear 40 days sowing. The infected plants can be identified by their sickly appearance. Plants dry up due to the disease infestation. The lower portion of stem is covered with white or brownish white fungal colonies. In extreme cases the plants wilts and dies. Dark brown lesions appear on the base of the stem near ground level, leading to withering. Large numbers of sclerotia are seen.SymptomsDiseases of Field Crops and Their ManagementGoogle -HortiAgri12. Diseases of SesamumRoot rot or stem rot or charcoal rot -Macrophomina phaseolina (Sclerotial stage:Rhizoctonia bataticola)SymptomsThe disease symptom starts as yellowing of lower leaves, followed by drooping and defoliation. The stem portion near the ground level shows dark brown lesions and bark at the collar region shows shredding. The sudden death of plants is seen in patches. In the grown-up plants, the stem portion near the soil level shows large number of black pycnidia.The stem portion can be easily pulled out leaving the rotten root portion in the soil. The infection when spreads to pods, they open prematurely and immature seeds shriveled and become black in colour. Minute pycnidia are also seen on the infected capsules and seeds. The rotten root as well as stem tissues contains a large number of minute black sclerotia. The sclerotia may also be present on the infected pods and seeds.PathogenThe pathogen produces dark brown, septate mycelium showing constrictions at the hyphal junctions. The sclerotia are minute, dark black and 110-130 m in diameter. The pycnidia are dark brown with a prominent ostiole. The conidia are hyaline, elliptical and single celled.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>-</head><label></label><figDesc>Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. sesami Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri Symptoms Black coloured lesions appear on the stem near the soil level. The disease spreads further and affects branches and may girdle the stem, resulting in the death of the plant. Leaves may also show water-soaked patches and spread till the leaves wither. Infection may be seen on flowers and capsules. Infected capsules are poorly developed with shriveled seeds. Pathogen The fungus produces non-septate, hyaline mycelium. The sporangiophores are hyaline and branched sympodially and bear sporangia. The sporangia are hyaline and spherical with a prominent apical papilla. The oospores are smooth, spherical and thick walled.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>symptoms starts with vein clearing of leaves .The disease manifests itself mostly during flowering stage, when the floral parts are transformed into green leafy structures, which Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri 141 Www.HortiAgri.Com grow profusely. The flower is rendered sterile. The veins of phylloid structure are thick and prominent. The plant is stunted with reduced internodes and abnormal branching. Pathogen It is caused by pleomorphic mycoplasma like bodies present in sieve tube of affected plants, now designated as a phytoplasmal disease.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Diseases of Field Crops and Their ManagementPathogenThe pathogen produces endophytic, septate mycelium. Conidiophores are short, hyalineand branched at the base. Conidia are borne singly or in chains at the tips of conidiophores. The conidia are hyaline, irregularly oblong with pointed ends, sometimes rounded to flattend ends, unicellular or 1-3 septate. The perfect stage of the fungus produces perithecia containing many asci. The ascospores are hyaline and usually two celled.Favourable ConditionsWet humid conditions during winter cotton season,  Intermittent rains during North-East monsoon season,  Low temperature (20-30˚C) during October-January,  Close planting, excessive application of nitrogenous fertilizers,  Very early sowing or very late sowing of cotton</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Moderate temperature of 25-28˚ C.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Diseases of Field Crops and Their ManagementPathogen It is caused by Cotton leaf curl virus -a begomovirus of family geminiviridae. The virions are typical geminate particles, ss circular DNA, bipartite genome with DNA-A and DNA-B components.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Elimination of volunteer perennial cotton and alternate hosts including malvaceous hosts like wild okra  Use of fungus Paecilomyces farinosus which parasitizes B.tabaci. It brings down vector population.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Grow resistant cultivars like Sharad, Jawahar, Maruthi, Malviya Arhar-2, C-11, Pusa-9, Narendra Arhar-1 and Birsa Arhar-1 Dry root rot -Macrophomina phaseolina (Sclerotial stage: Rhizoctonia bataticola) Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri Pathogen Fungus produces hyaline, coenocytic mycelium. The sporangiophores are hyaline bearing ovate or pyriform, non-papillate sporangia. Each sporangium produces 8-20 zoospores. Oospores are globose, light brown, smooth and thick walled.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>groups and several sori coalesce to cover a large area of the lamina. In the late season, teliosori appear on the leaves which are linear and dark brown in colour. Intense pustule formation causes drying and shedding of leaves. Pathogen It is autoecious, long cycle rust and all the spore stages occur on the same host. The uredospores are unicellular, globose or ellipsoid, yellowish brown with echinulations. The teliospores are globose or elliptical, unicellular, pedicellate, chestnut brown in colour with warty papillae at the top. Yellow coloured pycnia appear on the upper surface of leaves. Orange coloured cupulate aecia develop later on the lower surface of leaves. The aeciospores are unicellular and elliptical.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>root rot-Rhizoctonia bataticola (Pycnidial stage: Macrophomina phaseolina) Symptoms The disease symptom starts initially with yellowing and drooping of the leaves. The leaves later fall off and the plant dies with in week. Dark brown lesions are seen on the stem at ground level and bark shows shredding symptom. The affected plants can be easily pulled out leaving dried, rotten root portions in the ground. The rotten tissues of stem and root contain a large number of black minute sclerotia.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="5,109.50,154.56,402.35,287.64" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="8,86.83,154.79,439.85,278.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="12,109.50,154.79,427.75,298.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="21,67.55,270.25,410.90,398.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="23,203.20,115.85,303.15,180.90" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="29,174.00,72.00,283.15,252.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="43,73.50,72.00,443.10,328.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="45,109.50,132.94,358.60,217.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="48,73.50,92.70,450.70,280.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="54,112.50,72.00,281.75,211.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="70,204.75,112.67,239.55,218.13" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="89,132.75,258.28,347.55,341.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Tikka leaf spots Early leaf spot: Cercopora arachidicola</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>(Sexual Stage: Mycosphaerella arachidis) Late leaf spot: Phaeoisariopsis personata (Syn : Cercospora personata) (Sexual stage : Mycosphaerella berkeleyii)</note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0">Www.HortiAgri.Com</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anthracnose -Colletotrichum tabacum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initially, infection starts on lower leaves as pale-brown circular spots of 0.5 mm diameter with papery depressed centres outlined by slightly raised brown margin. The leaf-spots may remain small with white areas in the centre or coalesce to form large necrotic lesions. Under continuous humid weather, dark brown or black, elongated, sunken necrotic lesions appear on midrib, petiole and stem resulting in petiole and stem rot. Such seedlings do not establish in the field if planted. Primary infection starts from affected bits of aerial parts left in the soil in the previous season. The pathogen is not seed-borne but persists in the soil on dried plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Raised seed beds and rabbing with farm wastes help in reducing the initial infection</p><p>• Removal and destruction of all diseased debris minimises the pathogen in the soil.</p><p>• Rogueing diseased seedlings especially with necrotic lesions on stem</p><p>• Protective spraying with Bordeaux mixture at 1.0% (2-2-500) or Zineb @ 2 kg/ha</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wild fire -Pseudomonas tabaci</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The leaf spots may occur at any stage of plant growth including the nursery seedlings.</p><p>Dark brown to black spots with a yellow halo spreads quickly causing withering and drying of leaves. In advanced cases, lesions develop on the young stem tissues leading to withering and drying of the seedlings. In the fields, initially numerous water soaked black spots appear and latter become angular when restricted by the veins and veinlets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Cultural practices such as deep' covering or burial of organic matter before planting, nondirting cultivation by avoiding movement of soil up around the base of plants and preventing accumulation of organic debris are extremely useful in reducing the disease.</p><p>• Crop rotation with wheat, corn and soyabean may minimize the incidence of stem rot.</p><p>• Seed treatment with Carbendazim / Thiram / Captan @ 2-3 g/kg seed.</p><p>• Seed treatment with Trichoderma viride formulation (4g/kg) followed by application of 2.5kg Trichoderma viride formulation mixed with 50kg farm yard manure before sowing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wilt -Fusarium oxysporum and F. solani</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Germinating seeds are attacked by the pathogens shortly before emergence. There is general tissue disintegration and the surface of the seedling is covered with sporulating mycelium. Damping off symptoms characterized by brown to dark brown Water soaked sunken lesions on the hypocotyl which later encircle the stem and extend above the soil level. Roots are also attacked, especially the apical portions. The affected seedlings become yellow and wilted.</p><p>The leaves turn greyish green and the plants dry up and die. The roots and stems show internal vascular browning and discolouration. These fungi are also commonly associated with pod rot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Seed treatment with systemic fungicides like Carbendazim at 2g/kg seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anthracnose -Colletotrichum dematium</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri Small water-soaked yellowish spots appear on the lower leaves which later turn into circular brown lesions with yellow margin 1 to 3 mm in diameter. In some cases lesions enlarge rapidly become irregular and cover the entire leaflet, and extend to the stipules and stems. Brownish grey lesions occur on both the surfaces of leaflets. Infection spreads to stipules, petioles and branches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen is seed, soil and air-borne.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep summer ploughing.</p><p>• Use healthy certified seeds.</p><p>• Removal of plant debris.</p><p>• Seed treatment with copper oxychloride at 3g/kg seed or carbendazim at 2g/kg seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yellow mould -Aspergillus flavus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Seed and un-emerged seedlings attacked by the pathogen are rapidly shriveled and dried.</p><p>Brown or black mass covered by yellow or greenish spores may be seen. Decay is most rapid when infected seeds are planted. After seedling emergence cotyledons already infected with the pathogen, show necrotic lesions with reddish brown margins. This necrosis terminates at or near the cotyledonary axis. Under field conditions the diseased plants are stunted, and are often</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Foliar application of Mancozeb (2kg/ha) or Copper oxychloride (2kg/ha) or Carbendazim (500g/ha).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Indian Peanut Clump Disease -Peanut Clump virus</head><p>Earlier this disease was confused with groundnut rosstte. Now it is recognized as a distinct virus causing clump disease. The leaves turn very dark and plants become severely stunted. The disease is soil borne and transmitted by a fungus, Polymyxa graminis. The pH of the soil affects transmission. It is also transmitted by seed. The virus is rod shaped, 190-245nm long x 21nm wide, not enveloped, ssRNA genome.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Other virus diseases of minor importance occurring on groundnut are:</head><p>Peanut chlorotic streak (caused by Caulimovirus, occurs only in India), Peanut green mosaic and mottle (caused by a Potyvirus), peanut stunt (caused by Cucumovirus), groundnut chlorotic spot (caused by a Potexvirus), groundnut eye spot (caused by Potyvirus) and groundnut ringspot.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out the self-sown castor crops and other weed hosts.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb at 2kg/ha or Propioconazole 1l/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf blight-Alternaria ricini</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>All the aerial parts of plants viz., leaves, stem, inflorescences and capsules are liable to be attacked by the pathogen. Irregular brown spots with concentric rings form initially on the leaves and covered with fungal growth. When the spots coaleasce to form big patches, premature defoliation occurs. The stems, inflorescences and capsules are also show dark brown lesions with concentric rings. On the capsules, initially brown sunken spots appear, enlarge rapidly and cover the whole pod. The capsules crack and seeds are also get infected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Alterneria leaf spot with concentric rings</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The pathogen produces erect or slightly curved, light grey to brown conidiophores, which are occasionally in groups. Conidia are produced in long chains. Conidia are obclavate, light olive in colour with 5-16 cells having transverse and longitudinal septa with a beak at the tip.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High atmospheric humidity (85-90 %).</p><p>• Low temperature (16-20˚C)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives on hosts like Jatropha pandurifolia and Bridelia hamiltoniana.</p><p>The pathogen is externally and internally seed-borne and causes primary infection. The secondary infection is through air-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with captan or thiram at 2g/kg.</p><p>• Remove the reservoir hosts periodically.</p><p>• Spray mancozeb at 2kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Brown leaf spot -Cercospora ricinella</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears as minute brown specks surrounded by a pale green halo. The spots enlarge to greyish white centre portion with deep brown margin. The spots may be 2-4 mm in diameter and when several spots coalesce, large brown patches appear but restricted by veins.</p><p>Infected tissues often drop off leaving shot-hole symptoms. In severe infections, the older leaves may be blighted and withered.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spots on leaf</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The pathogen hyphae collect beneath the epidermis and form a hymenial layer. Clusters of conidiophores emerge through stomata or epidermis. They are septate and un branched with deep brown base and light brown tip. The conidia are elongated, colourless, straight or slightly curved, truncate at the base and narrow at the tip with 2-7 septa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen remains as dormant mycelium in the plant debris. The disease mainly spreads through wind borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Drying and death starts from apex and progress. Infected capsules discoloured and drop easily.</p><p>Sudden wilting of plants in patches under high moisture stress coupled with high soil temperature. Plant exhibit symptoms of drought and drooping of leaves. At ground level black lesions are formed on the stem. Young leaves curl inwards with black margins and drop off later, such branches Die-back. Entire branch and top of the plant withers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Affected plant showing drooping of leaves</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Grow tolerant and resistant varieties like Jyothi, Jwala, GCH-4, DCH-30 and SHB-145.</p><p>• Avoid water logging.</p><p>• Destruction of crop debris.</p><p>• Selection of healthy seed.</p><p>• Providing irrigation at critical stages of the crop.</p><p>• Treat the seed with thiram @ 2g/kg or carbendazim at 2g/ kg seed.</p><p>• Seed treatment with Trichoderma viride formulation at 4g/kg of seed.</p><p>• Soil drenching with Carbendazim (1g/1 litre of water) 2-3 times at 15 days interval.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial leaf spot -Xanthomonas campestris pv. ricinicola</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The pathogen attacks cotyledons, leaves and veins and produces few to numerous small round, water-soaked spots which later become angular and dark brown to jet black in color. The spots are generally aggregated towards the tip. At a later stage the spots become irregular in shape particularly when they coalesce and areas around such spots turn pale-brown and brittle. Bacterial ooze is observed on both the sides of the leaf which is in the form of small shining beads or fine scales.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pustules on lower leaf surface</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Field sanitation help in minimizing the yield loss as pathogen survives on seed and plant debris.</p><p>• Hot water treatment of seed at 58˚C to 60˚C for ten minutes.</p><p>• Grow tolerant varieties.</p><p>• Spray Copper oxychloride 2kg/ha or Streptocycline 100g/ha or Paushamycin 250g/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wilt -Fusarium oxysporum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>When seedlings are attacked cotyledonary leaves turn to dull green colour, wither and die subsequently. Leaves are droop and drop off leaving behind only top leaves. Diseased plants are sickly in appearance. Wilting of plants, root degeneration, collar rot, drooping of leaves and necrosis of affected tissue and finally leading to death of plants. Necrosis of leaves starts from margins spreading to interveinal areas and finally to the whole leaf. Spilt open stem shows brownish discolouration and white cottony growth of mycelia much prominently in the pith of the stem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Moisture stress and higher temperature favour development of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives in soil and in infected crop residues through sclerotia and pycnidia. The pathogen is seed-borne and it serves as primary source of infection. Wind-borne conidia cause secondary spread. The soil borne sclerotia also spreads through rain splash, irrigation water and implements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Closer planting of the seedling should be avoided.</p><p>• Optimum nutrition should be provided to maintain the plant vigour.</p><p>• Whenever the soil becomes dry and the soil temperature rises then irrigation should be provided.</p><p>• Seed treatment with Trichoderma viride formulation at 4 g/kg seed.</p><p>• In endemic areas long crop rotation should be followed.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim or Thiram at 2/kg • Spot drench with Carbendazim at 500 mg/litre.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf blight -Alternaria helianthi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The pathogen produces brown spots on the leaves, but the spots can also be seen on the stem, sepals and petals. The lesions on the leaves are dark brown with pale margin surrounded by a yellow halo. The spots later enlarge in size with concentric rings and become irregular in shape. Several spots coalesce to show bigger irregular lesions leading to drying and defoliation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives in the volunteer sunflower plants and in infected plant debris in the soil as teliospores. The disease spreads by wind-borne uredospores from infected crop.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Use of tolerant and resistant varieties</p><p>• Crop rotation should be followed.</p><p>• Previous crop remains should be destroyed.</p><p>• Removal of crop residues</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb at 2kg/ha. Head rot -Rhizopus sp.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The affected heads show water soaked lesions on the lower surface, which later turn brown. The discoloration may extend to stalk from head. The affected portions of the head become soft and pulpy and insects are also seen associated with the putrified tissues. The larvae and insects which attack the head pave way for the entry of the fungus which attacks the inner part of the head and the developing seeds. The seeds are converted into a black powdery mass.</p><p>The head finally withers and droops down with heavy fungal mycelial nets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Pathogen produces dark brown or black coloured, non-septate hyphae. It produces many aerial stolens and rhizoids. Sproangia are globose and black in colour with a central columella.</p><p>The sporangiospores are aplanate, dark coloured and ovoid.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Prolonged rainy weather at flowering.</p><p>• Ddamages caused by insects and caterpillars.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus survives as a saprophyte in host debris and other crop residues. The disease is spread by wind blown spores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with thiram or carbendazim at 2g/kg.</p><p>• Control the caterpillars feeding on the heads.</p><p>• Spray the head with Mancozeb at 2kg/ha during intermittent rainy season and repeat after 10 days, if the humid weather persists.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mildew -Erysiphe cichoracearum</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease produces white powdery growth on the leavesWhite to grey mildew on the upper surface of older leaves. As plant matures black pin head sized are visible in white mildew areas. The affected leaves more luster, curl, become chlorotic and die.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Structure of Rhizopus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Infection occurs in the crop in the month of July and August.</p><p>• The fungus survives through sclerotina in soil and plant debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep summer ploughing.</p><p>• Complete field and crop sanitation.</p><p>• Use of resistant or tolerant varieties.</p><p>• Collect and destroy plant debris.</p><p>• Apply Trichoderma on seed and soil to reduce wilt.</p><p>• Apply and incorporate fungus Coniothyrium minitans before sowing as it invades and destroy the pathogen in the soil.</p><p>• Seed treatment with Pseudomonas fluorescens or P.putida strains protect sunflower from Sclerotinia infection during seedling stage.</p><p>• Seed treatment with captan or thiram at the rate of 3 g/kg of seed.</p><p>• Drenching the base of the plant with chestnut compound 3 g per litre of water.</p><p>• Seed treatment with carbendazim at 0.2% followed by the addition of Trichoderma harzianum 10 g/kg soil and spraying Carbendazim at 0.2 % to 15 days old seedling. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Necrosis -Tobacco streak virus (TSV)</head><note type="other">Symptoms</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces macroconidia, microconidia and chlamydospores. Macroconidia are falcate shape, hyaline and 5-9 celled. Microconidia are hyaline, thin walled, unicellular and ovoid. The dark walled chlamydospores are also produced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the soil in the infected plant debris. It is also seed-borne and primary infection occurs through infected seeds or through chlamydospores in soil. The secondary infection may be caused by conidia disseminated by rain splash and irrigation water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Thiram or Carbendazim at 2g/kg</p><p>• Seed treatment with Trichoderma viride at 4g/kg.</p><p>• Apply heavy doses of green leaf manure or farm yard manure.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stem blight -Phytophthora parasitica var. sesami</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Verticillium wilt -Verticillium dahliae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The symptoms are seen when the crop is in squares and bolls. Plants infected at early stages are severely stunted. The first symptoms can be seen as bronzing of veins. It is followed by interveinal chlorosis and yellowing of leaves. Finally the leaves begin to dry, giving a scorched appearence. At this stage, the characteristic diagnostic feature is the drying of the leaf margins and areas between veins, which gives a "Tiger stripe" or "Tiger claw" appearance.</p><p>The affected leaves fall off leaving the branches barren. Infected stem and roots, when split open, show a pinkish discolouration of the woody tissue which may taper off into longitudinal streaks in the upper parts and branches. The infected leaf also shows brown spots at the end of the petioles. The affected plants may bear a few smaller bolls with immature lint. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Cercospora gossypina</head><p>Round or irregular grayish spots with dark brown or blackish borders appear on older leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Myrothecium leaf spot -Myrothecium roridum</head><p>Reddish spots of 0.5 mm-1 cm diameter may appear near the margins of the leaves. The affected portions fall off leaving irregular shot holes in the leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rust -Phakopsora desmium</head><p>Yellowish brown raised pustules appear on the lower surface of leaves with rusty spores. Several pustules join to give rusty appearence to entire leaf. The sori may also develop on bolls.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sooty mould -Capnodium sp.</head><p>Dark specks appear on the leaves and bolls, slowly spread and black powdery growth covers the entire leaf area and bolls.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>The disease occurs both in young seedlings and grown up plants. <ref type="bibr">Infected</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Prolonged drought followed by irrigation.</p><p>• High temperature of 28-35˚C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The primary spread of the disease is by seed and soil. Secondary spread is by air-borne conidia. The pathogen survives as sclerotia in the soil as facultative parasite and in dead host debris.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 162 Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• Treat the seeds with carbendazim or thiram at 2g/kg or pellet the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4 g/kg (10 6 cfu/g).</p><p>• Apply heavy doses of farm yard manure or green leaf manure like Gliricidia maculata at 10 t/ha or apply Neemcake at 150 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Powdery mildew -Leveillula taurica</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>White powdery growth of the fungus can be seen on the lower surface of leaves. The corresponding areas in upper surface show pale yellow discoloration. The white powdery mass consists of conidiophores and conidia of the fungus. In severe cases, the white growth can be seen on the upper surface also. The severe infection of the fungus leads to premature shedding of leaves and plant remains barren.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus is intercellular and absorbs nutrition through haustoria. The conidiophores, which arise through stomata, are hyaline, long, non septate, slender and rarely branched and bear single conidium at the tip. The conidia are hyaline, single celled and elliptical or clavate. The</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri fungus also produces black, globose cleistothecia with simple myceloid appendages. They contain 9-20 cylindrical asci. Each ascus contains 3-5 ascospores which are also hyaline and unicellular.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Dry humid weather following rainfall.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the soil through cleistothecia and ascospores from asci infect the first lower most leaves near the soil level. Secondary spread is by air-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>Spray Carbendazim 500g/ha or Wettable sulphur 2 kg/ha at the initiation of the disease and repeat after 15 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stem blight -Phytophthora drechsleri fsp. cajani</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initially purple to dark brown necrotic lesions girdle the basal portion of the stem and later may occur an aerial parts. Initially lesions are small and smooth, later enlarging and slightly depressed. Infected tissues become soft and whole plant dies. In grown up plants, infection is mostly confined to basal portions of the stem. The infected bark becomes brown and the tissue softens causing the plant to collapse. In leaf, localized yellowing starts from the tip and margin and gradually extends towards the mid-rib. The centre of the spots later turn brown and hard. The spots increase in size and cover a major portion of the lamina, leading to drying.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conidia and conidiophores</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces large number of whip-like, hyaline, 7-9 septate conidia in groups on the conidiophores which are light to dark brown in colour.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected plant tissues. The disease is spread by airborne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove the infected plant debris and destroy.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 2 kg or Carbendazim 500 g/ha soon after the appearance of symptom and repeat after a fortnight.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sterility Mosaic Disease (SMD) -Pigeonpea sterility mosaic virus (PPSMV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The Symptoms are characterized by bushy and pale green appearance of plants.The excessive vegetative growth, stunting, prominent mosaic on leaves and reduction in leaf size. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>It is not transmitted by infectious sap. It is transmitted by an eriophyid mite, Aceria cajani in a semi persistant manner, mites retaining the virus 12-13 hours, eggs of mites do not transmit. The self grown redgram plants and perennial species act as source of virus inoculums.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out infected plants up to 40 days after sowing.</p><p>• Spray Monocrotophos at 500 ml/ha soon after appearance of the disease and if necessary, repeat after 15 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Seedling blight -Sclerotium rolfsii</head><p>Small brown water soaked dots appear near collar region, expands to irregular necrotic spots leading to girdling of stem and death of seedling.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Brown blotch -Colletrtrichum capsici</head><p>Purple brown discolouration occurs mainly on pods but also on petioles, leaf veins, stems and peduncles. Pods become distorted and have black fruiting bodies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anthracnose -Colletotrichum lindemuthianum (Glomerella cingulata)</head><p>Black lesions develop on stem which spreads to leaf petiole and leaves. Black sunken lesions also develop on pod.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stem rot -Pythium aphanidermatum</head><p>Seedlings of 2-3 weeks old are severely attacked at collar region and death occurs immediately. Greyish green water soaked lesions develop on adult plants, leading to girdling of stem.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Alternaria alternata</head><p>Water soaked, circular to irregular spots occur. The centre of the spot is straw coloured with raised reddish brown margins.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Halo blight -Pseudomonas phaseolicola</head><p>Small brown spots appearon leaves and develop a chlorotic halo. The spots extend and form dried brown zone. Brown elongated streaks appear on petioles, stem and pods.</p><p>There are two other virus diseases reported on pigeonpea, mosaic and yellow mosaic transmitted by aphids and whiteflies which are of sporadic occurrence only.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="15.">Diseases of Black gram Powdery mildew -Erysiphe polygoni</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Small, irregular powdery spots appear on the upper surface of the leaves, sometimes on both the surfaces. The disease becomes severe during flowering and pod development stage. The white powdery spots completely cover the leaves, petioles, stem and even the pods. The plant assumes greyish white appearance; leaves turn yellow and finally shed. Often pods are malformed and small with few ill-filled seeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus is ectophytic, spreading on the surface of the leaf, sending haustoria into the epidermal cells. Conidiophores arise vertically from the leaf surface, bearing conidia in short chains. Conidia are hyaline, thin walled, elliptical or barrel shaped or cylindrical and single celled. Later in the season, cleistothecia appear as minute, black, globose structures with myceloid appendages. Each cleistothecium contains 4-8 asci and each ascus contains 3-8 ascospores which are elliptical, hyaline and single celled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Warm humid weather.</p><p>• The disease is severe generally during late kharif and rabi seasons.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The Pathogen is an obligate parasite and survives as cleistothecia in the infected plant debris. Primary infection is usually from ascospores from perennating cleistothecia. The secondary spread is carried out by the air-borne conidia. Rain splash also helps in the spread of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and destroy infected plant debris.</p><p>• Spray Carbendazim 500g or Wettable sulphur 2kg or Tridemorph 500 ml/ha at the initiation of disease and repeat 15 days later.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anthracnose -Colletotrichum lindemuthianum (Sexual stage: Glomerella lindemuthianum)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The symptom can be observed in all aerial parts of the plants and at any stage of crop growth. The fungus produces dark brown to black sunken lesions on the hypocotyl area and cause death of the seedlings. Small angular brown lesions appear on leaves, mostly adjacent to veins, which later become greyish white centre with dark brown or reddish margin.</p><p>The lesions may be seen on the petioles and stem. The prominent symptom is seen on the pods. Minute water soaked lesion appears on the pods initially and becomes brown and enlarges to form circular, depressed spot with dark centre with bright red or yellow margin. Several spots join to cause necrotic areas with acervuli. The infected pods have discolored seeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cleistothecium Conidia and conidiophores</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus mycelium is septate, hyaline and branched. Conidia are produced in acervuli, arise from the stroma beneath the epidermis and later rupture to become erumpent. A few dark coloured, septate setae are seen in the acervulus. The conidiophores are hyaline and short and bear oblong or cylindrical, hyaline, thinwalled, single celled conidia with oil globules. The perfect stage of the fungus produces perithecia with limited number of asci, which contain typically 8 ascospores which are one or two celled with a central oil globule.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• High relative humidity (Above 90 per cent),</p><p>• Low temperature (15-20˚ C)</p><p>• Cool rainy days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus is seed-borne and cause primary infection. It also lives in the infected plant tissues in soil. The secondary spread by air borne conidia produced on infected plant parts. Rain splash also helps in dissemination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and destroy infected plant debris in soil.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim at 2 g/kg.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>• Spray Carbendazim 500g or Mancozeb 2kg/ha soon after the appearance of disease and repeat after 15 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Cercospora canescens</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Small, circular spots develop on the leaves with grey centre and brown margin. Several spots coalesce to form brown irregular lesions. In severe cases defoliation occurs. The brown lesions may be seen on petioles and stem in severe cases. Powdery growth of the fungus may be seen on the centre of the spots.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces clusters of dark brown septate conidiophores. The conidia are linear, hyaline, thin walled and 5-6 septate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Humid weather and dense plant population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives on diseased plant debris and on seeds. The secondary spread is by air-borne conidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and burn infected plant debris.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb at 2 kg/ha or Carbendazim at 500 g/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected debris and also as facultative parasite in soil. The primary spread is through seed-borne and soil-borne sclerotia. The secondary spreads is through pycnidiospores which are air-borne.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with carbendazim + thiram at 2 g/kg (1:1 ratio) or pellet the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4 g/kg (10 6 cfu/g) or Pseudonomas fluorescens @ (10 6 cfu/g) of seed.</p><p>• Apply farm yard manure or green leaf manure (Gliricidia maculata) at 10 t/ha or neemcake at 150 kg/ha. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mungbean Yellow mosaic disease -Mungbean yellow mosaic virus (MYMV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Use increased seed rate (25 kg/ha).</p><p>• Rogue out the diseased plants at weekly interval up to 45 days after sowing. Cultivate seed crop during rabi season.</p><p>• Remove weed hosts periodically.</p><p>• Spray methyl demeton on 30 and 40 days after sowing at 500 ml/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf curl / Necrosis -Groundnut bud necrosis virus (GBNV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Upward cupping and curling of leaves with vein clearing. Infected leaves turn brittle and sometimes show vein necrosis on the under surface of the leaves, extending to the petiole. Plants affected in the early stages of growth develop top necrosis and die. Plant may produce a few small and malformed pods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>It is caused by Groundnut bud necrosis virus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The virus is transmitted by thrips viz., Frankliniella schultzii, Thrips tabaci and Scirtothrips dorsalis. The virus survives in weed hosts, tomato, petunia and Chilli.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out infected plants up to 30 days after sowing.</p><p>• Remove the weed hosts which harbour virus and thrips.</p><p>• Spray imidachlor at 500 ml/ha on 30 and 45 days after sowing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ascochyta leaf spot -Ascochyta phaseolorum</head><p>Small irregular spot with grey to brown centre and yellow border. They rapidly enlarge to produce very large brown lesions with concentric markings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial blight -Xanthomonas phaseoli</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="16.">Diseases of Green gram Powdery mildew -Erysiphe polygoni</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Powdery mildew is one of the widespread diseases of several legumes in green gram.</p><p>White powdery patches appear on leaves and other green parts which later become dull colored.</p><p>These patches gradually increase in size and become circular covering the lower surface also.</p><p>When the infection is severe, both the surfaces of the leaves are completely covered by whitish powdery growth. Severely affected parts get shriveled and distorted. In severe infections, foliage becomes yellow causing premature defoliation. The disease also creates forced maturity of the infected plants which results in heavy yield losses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus is ectophytic, spreading on the surface of the leaf, sending haustoria into the epidermal cells. Conidiophores arise vertically from the leaf surface, bearing conidia in short chains. Conidia are hyaline, thinwalled, elliptical or barrel shaped or cylindrical and single celled. Later in the season, cleistothecia appear as minute, black, globose structures with myceloid appendages. Each cleistothecium contains 4-8 asci and each ascus contains 3-8 ascospores which are elliptical, hyaline and single celled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• The pathogen has a wide host range and survives in oidial form on various hosts in offseason.</p><p>• Secondary spread is through air-borne oidia produced in the season</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The fungus is an obligate parasite and survives as cleistothecia in the infected plant debris. Primary infection is usually from ascospores from perennating cleistothecia. The secondary spread is carried out by the air-borne conidia. Rain splash also helps in the spread of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Use resistant varieties</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears as circular reddish brown pustules which appear more commonly on the underside of the leaves, less abundant on pods and sparingly on stems. When leaves are severely infected, both the surfaces are fully covered by rust pustules. Shriveling followed by defoliation resulting in yield losses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>It is autoecious, long cycle rust and all the spore stages occur on the same host. The uredospores are unicellular, globose or ellipsoid, yellowish brown with echinulations. The teliospores are globose or elliptical, unicellular, pedicellate, chestnut brown in colour with warty papillae at the top. Yellow coloured pycnia appear on the upper surface of leaves. Orange coloured cupulate aecia develop later on the lower surface of leaves. The aeciospores are unicellular and elliptical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable Conditions</head><p>• Cloudy humid weather,</p><p>• Temperature of 21-26˚C</p><p>• Nights with heavy dews.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The pathogen survives in the soil as teliospores and as uredospores in crop debris.</p><p>Primary infection is by the sporidia developed from teliospores. Secondary spread is by windborne uredospores. The fungus also survives on other legume hosts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove the infected plant debris and destroy.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb 1 2 kg or Carbendazim 500 g or Propiconazole 1L/ha kg/ha, immediately on the set of disease and repeat after 15 days.</p><p>• Use tolerant varieties.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Dry root rot -Rhizoctonia bataticola (Pycnidial stage: Macrophomina phaseolina)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease symptom starts initially with yellowing and drooping of the leaves. The leaves later fall off and the plant dies with in week. Dark brown lesions are seen on the stem at ground level and bark shows shredding symptom. The affected plants can be easily pulled out</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri leaving dried, rotten root portions in the ground. The rotten tissues of stem and root contain a large number of black minute sclerotia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces dark brown, septate mycelium with constrictions at hyphal branches. Minute, dark, round sclerotia in abundance. The fungus also produces dark brown, globose ostiolated pycnidia on the host tissues. The pycnidiospores are thin walled, hyaline, single celled and elliptical.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• Day temperature of 30˚C.</p><p>• Prolonged dry season followed by irrigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected debris and also as facultative parasite in soil. The primary spread is through seed-borne and soil-borne sclerotia. The secondary spread is through air-borne pycnidiospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim + Thiram at 2 g/kg or pellet the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4 g/kg or Pseudonomas fluorescens @ 10g/kg of seed.</p><p>• Apply farm yard manure or green leaf manure (Gliricidia maculate) at 10 t/ha or neem cake at 150 kg/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Yellow mosaic disease -Mungbean yellow mosaic virus (MYMV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Initially small yellow patches or spots appear on green lamina of young leaves. Soon it develops into a characteristics bright yellow mosaic or golden yellow mosaic symptom. Yellow </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Transmitted by whitefly, Bemisia tabaci under favourable conditions. Disease spreads by feeding of plants by viruliferous whiteflies. Summer sown crops are highly susceptible. Weed hosts viz., Croton sparsiflorus, Acalypha indica, Eclipta alba and other legume hosts serve as reservoir for inoculum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out the diseased plants up to 40 days after sowing.</p><p>• Remove the weed hosts periodically.</p><p>• Increase the seed rate (25 kg/ha).</p><p>• Grow resistant green gram variety like Pant Moong-3, Pusa Vishal, Basanti, ML-5, ML-337, PDM-54 and Samrat.</p><p>• Cultivate the crop during rabi season.</p><p>• Follow mixed cropping by growing two rows of maize (60 x 30 cm) or sorghum (45 x 15 cm) or cumbu (45 x 15 cm) for every 15 rows of black gram or green gram.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Thiomethoxam-70WS or Imidacloprid-70WS @4g/kg • Spray Thiamethoxam-25WG @ 100g or Imidacloprid 17.8% SL @ 100 ml in 500 lit of water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf crinkle disease -Urdbean leaf crinkle virus (ULCV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Crinkling and rugosity in older leaves becomes severe and leaves thickened. Crinkling and curling of the tips of leaflets are seen. Petioles as well as internodes are shortened. Infected plant gives a stunted and bushy appearance. Flowering is delayed, inflorescence, if formed, are malformed with small size flower buds and fail to open.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>Casual organism of the disease is not yet ascertained work is in progress in different laboratories.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>Presence of weed hosts like Aristolochia bracteata and Digera arvensis. Kharif season crop and continuous cropping of other legumes serve as source of inoculum. The virus is seed-Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri borne and primary infection occurs through infected seeds. Perhaps white fly, Bemisia tabaci helps in the secondary spread. The virus is also sap transmissible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Use increased seed rate (25 kg/ha).</p><p>• Rogue out the diseased plants at weekly interval up to 45 days after sowing. Cultivate seed crop during rabi season.</p><p>• Remove weed hosts periodically.</p><p>• Spray Methyl demeton on 30 and 40 days after sowing at 500 ml/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf curl / Necrosis -Groundnut bud necrosis virus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Upward cupping and curling of leaves with vein clearing. Infected leaves are brittle and sometimes show vein necrosis on the under surface of the leaves, extends to the petiole. Plants affected in the early stages of growth develop top necrosis and die. Plant may produce a few small and malformed pods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Caused by groundnut bud necrosis virus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease Cycle</head><p>The virus is transmitted by thrips viz., Frankliniella schultzii, Thrips tabaci and Scirtothrips dorsalis. The virus survives in weed hosts, tomato, petunia and Chilli.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out infected plants up to 30 days after sowing.</p><p>• Remove the weed hosts which harbour virus and thrips.</p><p>• Spray Imidachlor at 500 ml/ha on 30 and 45 days after sowing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ascochyta leaf spot -Ascochyta phaseolorum</head><p>Small irregular spot with grey to brown centre and yellow border. They rapidly enlarge to produce very large brown lesions with concentric markings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial blight -Xanthomonas phaseoli</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Circular, reddish brown spots appear on leaves, enlarge to form irregular brown lesions.</p><p>Water soaked, sunken spots with red border occur on pods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces hyaline to brown and septate mycelium. Pycnidia are spherical to sub-globose with a prominent ostiole. Pycnidiospores are hyaline, oval to oblong, straight or slightly curved and single celled, occasionally bicelled.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• High rainfall during flowering.</p><p>• Temperature of 20-25˚C.</p><p>• Relative humidity of 60%.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected plant debris as pycnidia. The pathogen is also externally and internally seed-borne. The primary spread is from seed-borne pycnidia and plant debris in the soil. The secondary spreads is mainly through air-borne pycnidiopores (conidia).</p><p>Rain splash also helps in the spread of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Remove and destroy the infected plant debris in the field.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with Thiram 2g or Carbendazim 2 g or Thiram + Carbendazim (1:1 ratio) at 2 g/kg.</p><p>• Exposure of seed at 40-50˚C reduced the survival of A. rabiei by about 40-70 per cent.</p><p>• Spray with Carbendazim at 500 g/ha or Chlorothalonil 1kg/ha.</p><p>• Follow crop rotation with cereals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rust -Uromyces ciceris-arietini</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The infection appears as small oval, brown, powdery lesions on both the surface, especially more on lower surface or leaf. The lesions, which are uredosori, cover the entire leaf surface. Late in the season dark teliosori appear on the leaves. The rust pustules may appear on petioles, stems and pods. The pycnial and aecial stages are unknown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The uredospores are spherical, brownish yellow in colour, loosey echinulated with 4-8 germ pores. Teliospores are round to oval, brown, single celled with unthickened apex and the walls are rough, brown and warty.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mode of Spread and Survival</head><p>The fungus survives as uredospores in the legume weed Trigonella polycerata during summer months and serve as primary source of infection. The spread is through wind-borne uredospores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Destory weed host.</p><p>• Spray Carbendazim 500 g/ha or Propiconazole 1L/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wilt -Fusarium oxysporum f.sp. ciceris</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease occurs at two stages of crop growth, seedling stage and flowering stage stage.</p><p>The main symptoms on seedlings are yellowing and drying of leaves, drooping of petioles and rachis, withering of plants. In the case of adult plants drooping of leaves is observed initially in upper part of plant, and soon observed in entire plant. Vascular browning is conspicuously seen on the stem and root portion</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces hyaline to light brown, septate and profusely branched hyphae.</p><p>Microconidia are oval to cylindrical, hyaline, single celled, normally arise on short conidiophores. Macroconidia which borne on branched conidiophores, are thin walled, 3 to 5septate, fusoid and pointed at both ends. Chlamydospores are roughwalled or smooth, terminal or intercalary, may be formed singly or in chains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• High soil temperature (above 25˚C).</p><p>• High soil moisture.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The disease is seed and soil borne. The primary infection is through chlamydospores in soil, which remain viable upto next crop season. The secondary spread is through irrigation water, cultural operations and implements.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim or Thiram at 2 g/kg or Carbendazim 1 g+Thiram 1g/kg or treat the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4 g/kg (10 6 cfu/g) Pseudonomas fluorescens @ 10g/kg (10 6 cfu/g) of seed.</p><p>• Apply heavy doses of organic manure or green manure.</p><p>• Grow resistant cultures like ICCC 42, H82-2, Avrodhi, Alok Samrat, Pusa-212, JG-322, GPF-2, Haryanachana-1 and Kabuli chickpea like Pusa-1073 and Pusa-2024. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The virus is transmitted by Aphis craccivora.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Rogue out the infected plants.</p><p>• Spray Monocrotophos at 500 ml/ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Collar rot -Sclerotium rolfsii</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>It comes in the early stages i.e up to six weeks from sowing. Drying plants whose foliage turns slightly yellow before death, scattered in the field is an indication of the disease. Seedlings become chlorotic. The joint of stem and root turns soft slightly contracts and begins to decay.</p><p>Infected parts turn brown white. Black dots, like mustard in shape known as sclerotia are seen appearing on the white infected plant parts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable conditions</head><p>• High soil moisture, low soil pH and high temperature.</p><p>• The presence of undecomposed organic matter on the soil surface and high moisture at the time of sowing and at the seedling stage • Disease incidence is higher when sown after rice or early sown crop.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep pluoghing in summer.</p><p>• Avoid high moisture at the sowing time.</p><p>• Seedlings should be protected from excessive moisture.</p><p>• Destroy the crop residues of last crop and weeds before sowing and after harvest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 191 Www.HortiAgri.Com</p><p>• All undecomposed matter should be removed from the field before land preparation.</p><p>• Treat the seeds with a mixture of Carbendazim + Thiram (1:1) @ 2g per kg of seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Minor diseases</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Foot rot -Operculella padwickii</head><p>Rotting is evident from collar region onwards. Internal brown discolouration appears above the rotton portion (only on bark portion).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Stemrot -Sclerotinia sclerotiorum</head><p>The disease appears mostly on stems rot of adult plants as water soaked lesion on upper parts of stem. The affected portion is covered with white cottony growth and black sclerotial bodies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bacterial leaf blight -Xanthomonas campestris pv. cassiae</head><p>Small water soaked lesions develop on leaves with chlorotic haloes which later turn to dark brown spots. Post emergence seedling rot is also common.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bean Common Mosaic -Virus</head><p>Stunted, bushy appearance of plant with mosaic mottling. Vector : Aphis gossypii and A. craccivora.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri Www.HortiAgri.Com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="18.">Diseases of Soybean Dry root rot -Macrophomina phaseolina</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease symptom starts initially with yellowing and drooping of the leaves.</p><p>The leaves later fall off and the plant dies with in week. Dark brown lesions are seen on the stem at ground level and bark shows shredding symptom. The affected plants can be easily pulled out leaving dried, rotten root portions in the ground. The rotten tissues of stem and root contain a large number of black minute sclerotia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>The fungus produces dark brown, septate mycelium with constrictions at hyphal branches. Minute, dark, round sclerotia in abundance. The fungus also produces dark brown, globose ostiolated pycnidia on the host tissues. The pycnidiospores are thin walled, hyaline, single celled and elliptical</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• Day temperature of 30˚C</p><p>• Prolonged dry season followed by irrigation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected debris and also as facultative parasite in soil. The primary spread is through seed-borne and soil-borne sclerotia. The secondary spread</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri 193 Www.HortiAgri.Com is through seed-borne and soil-borne sclerotia. The secondary spreads is through pycnidiospores which are air-borne.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim or Thiram at 2 g/kg or pellet the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4 g/kg or Pseudonomas fluorescens @ 10g/kg of seed.</p><p>• Apply farm yard manure or green leaf manure (Gliricidia maculata) at 10 t/ha or neem cake at 150 kg/ha. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Wilt</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>Temperature of 20-25˚C and moist humid weather.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>The fungus survives in the infected stubbles in the field. The primary spread is through soilborne chlamydospores and infected seeds. The secondary spread is through conidia by irrigation water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Treat the seeds with Carbendazim or Thiram at 2 g/kg or treat the seeds with Trichoderma viride at 4 g/kg.</p><p>• Spot drenching with Carbendazim at 0.5 g/litre.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Leaf spot -Cercospora sojana</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Light to dark gray or brown areas varying from specks to large blotches appear on seeds. The disease primarily affects foliage, but, stems, pods and seeds may also be infected. Leaf lesions are circular or angular, at first brown then light brown to ash grey with dark margins. The leaf spot may coalesce to form larger spots. When lesions are numerous the leaves wither and drop prematurely. Lesions on pods are circular to elongate, light sunken and reddish brown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head><p>Google -HortiAgri Www.HortiAgri.Com</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favourable conditions</head><p>• Fungus survives in infected seeds and in debris.</p><p>• Warm, humid weather favor disease incidence</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Use resistant varieties.</p><p>• Use healthy or certified seeds.</p><p>• Rotate soybean with cereals.</p><p>• Completely remove plant residue by clean ploughing the field soon after harvest.</p><p>• Destroy last years infected stubble.</p><p>• Seed treatment with Thiram + Carbendazium (1:1) @ 2g/kg seed.</p><p>• Spray Mancozeb @ 2g/L or Carbenzadium (500 mg/L).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mosai -Soybean mosaic virus (SMV)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Diseased plants are usually stunted with distorted (puckered, crinkled, ruffled, narrow) leaves. Pods become fewer and smaller seeds. Infected seeds get mottled and deformed. Infected seeds fail to germinate or they produce diseased seedlings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pathogen</head><p>It is caused by Soybean mosaic virus -a potyvirus. Flexuous particles 750 -900nm long, ss RNA genome .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disease cycle</head><p>Soybean mosaic virus is seed borne. The SMV can be transmitted through sap, 32 aphid species are involved in transmission.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Favorable conditions</head><p>• Temperature around 18 o C • Humid weather.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management</head><p>• Deep summer ploughing.</p><p>• Use resistant or tolerant varieties.</p><p>• Use healthy/certified seeds.</p><p>• Keep the field free from weeds.</p><p>• Rogue out infected plants and burn them</p><p>• Pre-sowing soil application of Phorate @ 10 kg/ha.</p><p>• Two foliar sprays of Thiamethoxam 25 WG @ 100 g/ha or Methyl demeton 800 ml/ha at 30 and 45 days after sowing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Google -HortiAgri</head><p>Youtube -HortiAgri Google -HortiAgri Anroid App -HortiAgri anilrana13014@gmail.com 8126503283</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">On leaf, the lesions are round or elongated, bearing irregularly depressed brown spot and surrounded by a brownish red margin. Similar spots may appear on the stem and pods. The spots on the stem and pods have pycnidia arranged in concentric circles as minute block dots. When the lesions girdle the stem, the portion above the point of attack rapidly dies. If the main stem is girdles at the collar region, the whole plant dies</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Diseases of Bengal gram Ascochyta blight -Ascochyta rabiei Symptoms All above ground parts of the plant are infected</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Symptoms Diseases of Field Crops and Their Management Google -HortiAgri</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
