<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<settlement>Gujarat, Maharashtra, Tamilnadu, Bihar</settlement>
									<region>Karnataka</region>
									<country>U.P. and Orissa</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D004C90213FA3851BDB6FEDF3D171E92</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:40+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>Order : Coleoptera : Family: Scarabaeidae Hindi name : Safed gidar other species: H. serrata fabr. Anomala bengalensis blanch Odontotermes obesus</term>
					<term>Microtermes sp</term>
					<term>Isoptera: Termitidae Bark eating caterpillar</term>
					<term>Indarbela quadrinotata</term>
					<term>Lepidoptera : Metarbelidae</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>ENTO.311 pests of crops and stored grains and their management 3(2+1) LOCUSTS  The larger grasshoppers which form swarms are called locusts and there are three species of the family -Acrididae found in India. (i) Desert locust, Schistocerca gregaria (Forskal) (ii) Bombay-locust, Patanga succincta Linnaeus (iii) Migratory locust, Locusta migratoria(Linnaeus).</p><p> Of these, the desert locust is the most important. There are very few records of swarms involving other locusts, particularly of the migratory locusts. The first and second species are important in Maharashtra, Gujarat and Rajasthan but the desert locust is of all India importance. In fact, it is an international pest and efforts are being made constantly to control it through the International Locust Control Organization of the Food and Agriculture Organization.</p><p>Desert locust, Schistocerca gregaria (Forskal) (Orthoptera : Acrididae)</p><p>The desert locust is found in two phases i.e. the solitary phase and the gregarious phase. Individuals having characteristics in between the two are often placed under the transient phase.</p><p>Mark of identification: The nymphs of the gregarious phase are yellow or pink, with distinct black markings, whereas the color of the solitary hoppers varies according to the color of the surrounding vegetation.</p><p>The gregarious adults are pink on emergence, gradually turning grey and ultimately yellow, when sexually mature. The adults of the solitary phase remain greenish grey throughout their life.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle:</head><p>A single female may lay up to 11 egg-pods, each pod containing up to 120 eggs. A female normally lays 500 eggs in about 5 pods. Before egg laying the female, with the help of her ovipositor, bores a hole into the loose sandy soil, 5-10 cm deep. Having laid a pod, she secretes a frothy material over. The eggs, which hardens on drying and makes the pod water-proof while laying eggs, the females may be sitting very close to one another and as many as 5,000 eggs may be laid one square meter. The egg, resembling grain of rice, is lightly curved and 79 mm long. The duration of the egg stage depends upon the soil conditions, temperature and moisture. The eggs laid in February and March hatch in 3-4 weeks and those laid 1n May-September hatch in 12-15 days. The nymphs, at the time of emerging, break the egg-shell and creep out of the holes. The duration of the nymphal (hopper) stage lasts 6-8 weeks in spring and 3-4 weeks in summer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>The locust is harmful in both the hopper and the adult stages. These gregarious and voracious feeders eat almost any vegetation, except a few plant species such as vegetation, except a few plant species such as ak (Calotropis procera), dharek (Melia azedarch), neem (Azadirachta indica), dhatura (Datum stramonium), etc. When in swarms, they can consume all the green vegetation and cause a famine. In addition to the damage to crops, orchards, forests, etc., the locust can be nuisance in houses, as these creatures climb over the walls, invade kitchens, storerooms and even enter into the beds. They fall into wells by the million and thus make water unfit for drinking If an army of hoppers or adults marches on to the railway lines, all trafiic is suspended because the crushed hoppers cause slippery Management: Management operation can be carried out against all stages of the locust, the most practicable and effective measures are against the nymphs. Eggs. If eggs are laid in a well-defined area, a trench may be dug around it, so that the young nymphs on emerging drop into it and can be buried alive, filling the ditch with soil. If these trenches are heavily dusted with lindane, it may not be necessary to bury the nymphs. Nymphs. The hopper stage is the most vulnerable and control measures are most effective before the second moult. The nymphs may be destroyed either with chemicals or by using mechanical methods: (i) The principal mechanical method of control lies in digging trenches in front of the moving army of nymphs and driving them into these trenches, with brooms or with twigs of trees and then, buried alive. The nymphs can also be guided to the trenches along metal or canvas barriers 45 cm high. Two barriers, one, on each side of the army of the marching hoppers are so fixed that they converge on a narrow gap that leads to a trench in which they drop. The trench should be deep enough to accommodate a large number of hoppers most of which would then die under the weight of their own fellow creatures. Later, the trench can be filled with earth. In the early stages, a trench 30-45 cm wide and 60 cm deep, 18 sufficient but when the hoppers are older, the width should be 57 cm and the depth more than 60 cm. (ii) At night when the hoppers rest on bushes, they can be burnt with flame-throwers.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>POLYPHAGOUS PESTS</head><p>There are many polyphagous pests which damage a number of crops and cause substantial losses. Important polyphagous pests are as follows : (iii) Lindane (2%), in an oil medium, is also effective _ when sprayed with an aeroplane on top of a flying swarm. Lindane 20 EC 1n water suspension can also be sprayed on locusts, on the ground. Anti-Locust Organization. The Anti-Locust Organisation in India consists of (a) The Central AntiLocust Organization, and (b) the State AntiLocust Organizations.</p><p>(a) Central AntiLocust Organization. This organization is handled by the Plant Protection Adviser to the Government of India, who is also the Director of Locust Control, having his headquarters at Faridabad (Haryana). The Directorate is required to:</p><p>• Record the weekly density of locusts per unit area in the breeding areas located 1n India and to carry out control operations there.</p><p>• Interpret the records and pass on the information on locust movements to the various State Locust Control and Warning Officers and to the revenue authorities of the concerned districts before the locust reaches there so that arrangements for control can be made in advance. •Keep watch on the coming swarms of extra-Indian origin, their direction and size. * Give technical and material assistance to the various States.</p><p>•Coordinate the Antilocustwork 1n India by issuing a fortnightly bulletin on the locust situation both in India and in foreign countries.</p><p>In India, the work of this organization extends both to the scheduled desert areas where locusts breed and to the cultivated areas where they do the damage.</p><p>In the scheduled desert areas, (a) the Central Anti-Locust Organization operates over an area of 2,05,785 square kilometers in the States of Rajasthan, Haryana, Maharashtra and Gujarat. This area is divided into 10 zones which are grouped into 4 circles with headquarters at Bikaner, Jodhpur, Barmer and Palanpur (Gujarat). The responsibility of the control work is entrusted to the Locust Entomologist in charge of the circle. (b) State Anti-Locust Organization In the scheduled area of the desert as well as in the adjoining States where locusts cause damage; there are State Anti-Locust Organizations to take suitable measures against the swarms. The State organization is headed by the Locust Control and Warning Officer, who 1s well connected with the local revenue authorities, from the Deputy Commissioner to the Tehsildar and Patwari. When the latter official receives information from district headquarters warning him of a 16cust invasion; he alerts the villagers to be ready with machines and insecticides, kerosene, flamethrowers, spades, etc. When the swarm actually arrives, the farmers try to kill it as well as they can and then the Patwari intimates the Locust Control Officer and his own Deputy Commissioner of the extent of success achieved. In case the swarm settles down to lay eggs, the Locust Control Officer or his staff visits the place to devise suitable control measures.</p><p>The head is dark brown with strong mandibles and prominent thoracic legs. The total larval period varies from 8-10 weeks. The grub construct an earthen cell in which it passes a quiescent pre pupal stage which lasts for one to 6 weeks. The freshly formed pupa is light yellow and extremely tender, but as it grows older it turn brown. It is of execrate pupa i.e. the appendages are free from the body. The pupal duration ranges from 14 day. The freshly formed beetle is cream coloured but mature beetle has brown colour and elytra gets hardened. Generally the adults male are smaller than the females. The adult beetles remain in soil until the next years of summer rains. The total life cycle is completed from 90-108 days and all the known species in india have one generation in a year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>RED HAIRY CATERPILLARS</head><p> Red hairy caterpillar, Amsacta moorei (Lepidoptera: Arctiidae)  Bihar hairy caterpillar, Spilarctia obliqua Walker (Lepidoptera: Arctiidae)  The red hairy caterpillar or katra is widely distributed in the Orient, including India. It is a polyphagous insect and feeds on all kinds of vegetation growing during the Kharif season. Its attack is particularly serious on sunhemp, maize, sorghum, glwra, mung, math and sesamum.</p><p> The moths are stoutly built and have white wings with black spots. The outer margins of the fore wings, the anterior margin of the thorax and the entire abdomen are scarlet red.There are black bands and dots on the abdomen. The full grown caterpillars are reddish-amber to olive green and the body is covered with numerous long hairs arising from the fleshy tubercles.</p><p>6. Soldiers. The soldiers develop from unfertilized eggsand remain comparatively underdeveloped. They are the most specialized members of the community and can be readily recognized by the large head and strongly characterised sickle-shaped mandibles. Life-cycle. In the rainy season when atmospheric conditions are favorable, the colonizing forms leave their parent colony. As they are weak fliers, they do not travel a long distance unless aided by wind. As a rule, a particular species_ swarms at about the same time of season. The members of the swarm comprise individuals of both sexes. They are attracted to light where they mix with individuals of the neighboring swarms. A great majority of them fall prey to many types of predators and only a few individuals survive in the end. Sooner or later the survivors fall down and cast their wings and mate before or after shedding them. Both the male and female participate in the early operations of forming a nest by excavating small burrows or galleries or the nuptial chambers. In the beginning only a few eggs are laid and are looked after by them and the newly hatched nymphs are fed by the parents themselves. They develop into Workers and then take over all the brooding. During the first season, the reproductive castes are usually not produced. Gradually, the queen grows in size and the number of eggs laid increases.</p><p>The eggs hatch after one week during the summer and within 6 weeks the larvae develop to form soldiers or workers, as the case may be. The reproductive castes when produced, mature in 1-2 years. The queen is capable of laying many millions of eggs during her life, which is very difficult to estimate, but probably 6-9 years is the approximate span. The nests of many termites grow fungus gardens in the center, near about the 'royal chamber'. The fungus grows into a comb like structure and is fed to the royal pair and the larvae.</p><p>Damage. The termites live on cellulose which they obtain from dead and living vegetable matter to obtain their food, they destroy wood-work, household articles, fences and wooden poles that come into contact with the soil. They also damage fruit and shade-trees, crops such as sugarcane, chilies, wheat and peas. Management of Termites 1. When a colony is established, it is not so easy to eradicate the pest. The only sure method is to reach the center of the nest and kill the queen and the complementary forms. Since the termite tunnels run for hundreds of meters, it the wood and in the crevices is the only remedy. For a lasting relief the nests should be located in the vicinity and destroyed by flooding them with the insecticide emulsions. 2. To avoid the attack of white-ants in cultivated fields, care should be taken not to use green manure or raw farmyard manure. <ref type="bibr">3</ref>. Insecticidal control (a) Fruit trees <ref type="bibr">(1)</ref> In new plantations, the pits should be treated with 0.2 per cent lindane emulsion or crudeoil emulsion before planting the trees. This is done by thoroughly mixing 0.25 kg of crude-oil emulsion and a little arsenic in about 4 baskets of subsoil taken from the pit. The treated soil is returned to the pit.</p><p>(2) To protect the tree trunks, spraying them with 1 per cent lindane is effective.</p><p>(3) To protect the roots, 0.5 per cent chlorpyriphos or lindane or 3 per cent sanitary fluid in the irrigation basin should be applied.</p><p>(b) Field crops (i) (ii) Soaking the emulsion in furrows at the time of planting, savsugarcane setts in 0.5 per cent lindane/chlorpyriphos suspension or 0.25 per cent lindane/chlorpyriphoses them from termite attack. (iii), Wheat seed treatment before sowing, with 160 ml emulsion of chlorpyriphos in one liter of water spraying on thinly spread out 40 kg seeds with a water emulsion of chlorpyriphos 20EC remains effective for the crop season. Termite damage in standing wheat crop can be minimized by application of 5 liters of lindane 20EC per hectare into irrigation water or field spreading of one liter of lindane 20EC .mixed with sand or soil, followed by light irrigation.</p><p>(3) Buildings (i) A galvanized sheet of iron with its outer edge turned downwards when placed just above the damp-proof layer makes the house white-ant-proof. Wooden structures such as doorframes should not directly touch the ground and should be raised on a cement layer.</p><p>(ii) An insecticidal barrier between the ground and woodwork in building should be made by treating the soil beneath the building and around foundations with 0.5 per cent chlorpyriphos or lindane. The solution should be applied at the rate of 5 liters per m2. . • This is the commonest and most destructive fruit-fly of musk melon and other cucurbits.</p><p>• Host Plant: Tomato, chillies, guava, citrus, pear, fig, cauliflower, etc.In northwestern India, it is very common on late-sown melons that ripen after the monsoon rains begin. Two other allied species common in India are Dacus ciliatis Loew and Bactrocera dorsalis (Hendel).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Marks of identification:</head><p>• Larva:Maggots are legless and appear as headless, dirty-white wriggling creatures, thicker at one end and tapering to a point at the other. A full-grown maggot is 9-10 mm long and 2 mm broad in the middle. Adult : The adult flies are reddish brown with lemon-yellow markings on the thorax and have fuscous areas on the outer margins of their wings.</p><p>The eggs hatch in 1-9 days and the maggots bore into the pulp, forming galleries. The attacked fruits decay because of secondary bacterial infection. The larvae are full-grown in 3 days during summer and 3 weeks during winter. The mature larvae come out of the rotten fruits and jumps in soil. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>The maggots pollute and destroy fruits by feeding on the pulp. The damage caused by this fruit-fly is most serious in melons and after the first shower of the monsoon, the infestation often reaches 100 per cent. Other cucurbitaceous fruits may also be infested up to</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management:</head><p>The regular removal and destruction of the infested fruits helps in the suppression of this pest. Frequent raking of the soil under the vine or ploughing the infested field after the crop is harvested can help in killing the pupae. Apply the bait spray containing 50 ml of malathion 50 EC + 0.5 kg of gur /sugar in 50 litres of water per ha. When the attack is serious, it should be repeated at weekly intervals. Spraying the bait on the lower surface of the leaves of maize plants grown at distance of 8-10 cm as trap crop has been found to be effective as the flies have the habit of resting on such tall plants.</p><p>• The two species, red pumpkin-beetle, A .foveicollis and blue pumpkin-beetle, A. atripennis Fabricius are common in Northwestern India, the former being more important. Damage is caused by grubs as well as by beetles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Marks of identification:</head><p>• Larva: The grubs lead a subterranean life and when full-grown, they measure about 12 mm in length and 3.5 mm across the mesothorax. They are creamy white, with a slightly darker oval shield at the back. • Adult The beetles feed on those parts of the plant which are above the ground. They are oblong and 5-8 mm long. Their dorsal body surface is brilliant orange red and ventral surface is black, being clothed in short white hair.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life-cycle:</head><p>The beetles are found concealed in groups under dry weeds, bushes and plant remains or in the crevices of soil. They resume activity as soon as the season warms up and in their life span of 60-85 days, they lay about 300 oval yellow eggs singly or in batches of 8-9 in moist soil, near the base of the plants.</p><p>The eggs hatch in 6-15 days and the grubs remainbelow the soil surface feeding on roots, underground stems of creepers and on fruits lying in contact with the soil. They are full-grown in l3-25 days and pupate in thickwalled earthen chambers in the soil, at a depth of about 20-25 cm.</p><p>The pupal stage lasts 7-17 days and the beetles, on emergence, begin to feed and breed. The life-cycle is completed in 26-37 days and the pest breeds five times from March to October.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Egg 6-15 D</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">G</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adult</head><p>Pupa7-17 D Grub 13-25 D</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>The beetles are very destructive to cucurbitaceous vegetables, particularly during March-April when the creepers are very young.</p><p>The grubs damage the plants by boring into the roots, underground stems and sometime into the fruits touching the soil.</p><p>The beetles injure the cotyledons, flowers and foliage by biting holes into them. The early sown cucurbits are so severely damaged that they have to be resown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management:</head><p>After harvesting the infested fields, plough deep to kill the grubs in the soil. Sow the crop in November to avoid damage by this pest. Red Vegetable Mite, Tetranychus telarius Linnaeus (Acari: Tetranychidae)</p><p>• The red vegetable mite, also called the two-spotted spider mite, is world-wide. The large scale use of chlorinated hydrocarbon insecticides for the control of various other pests leads to the multiplication of mites, since they are less toxic to mites and especially since they kill large number of the natural enemies of mites.</p><p>• Host plants: The mite is a polyphagous pest and is known to feed on 183 species of plants including cucurbits, brinjal and okra on which it is occasionally very serious.</p><p>• Marks of identification: Nymph: A fully developed nymph is microscopic and measures about 0.33 mm in length. It is light brown and has two eye-spots, four pairs of legs and is quite active.</p><p>• Adult: The adult malemeasures about 0.52 mm in length and 0.30 mm in breadth. The body of the female is oval, pyriform and variable in colour. It may be ferruginous red, greenish amber or rusty green. Two large pigmented Spots are present on the body.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>The damage is caused both by the nymphs and adults.</p><p>All the active stages usually feed on the underside of the leaves by sucking cell sap.</p><p>Gradually, the infested leaves dry up and the webbing interferes with plant growth. There is a poor setting of the fruits and the yield is considerably reduced. Management. Spray 625 ml of dimethoate 30EC or oxydemeton methyl 25EC in 250 litres of water per ha and repeat spray at 10-day interval.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pests of Mango (Mangifera indica : family : anacardiacea)</head><p>• Mango is considered to be the king of all fruits in south Asia. India is the largest producer and exporter of mango in the world. Mango is rich source of vitamin A and vitamin C. There are a number of insect pests of this fruit and over 175 species of insects have been reported damaging mango tree but the most abundant and destructive at the flowering stage are the mango hoppers.Important pests of mango are as follows;   • This insect is triangular in shape being broader at anterior end narrower towards the posterior. Adults of the larger mango hopper I. clypealis measure 6.3 mm length are grayish.</p><p>• Freshly hatched nymphs are wedge shaped and whitish in colour with two small red eyes. • Gradually with each moulting, the colour changes to yellow, yellowish green, green and ultimately greenish brown.</p><p>• A. atkinsoni adult is about 5.1 mm long. It differ from the larger species by the absence of a central longitudinal dark streak on the scutellum. • Adults of mango hoppers are light greenish-brown with black and yellow markings.</p><p>Life-cycle. This pest is active practically throughout the year but during the hot months of May-June and the cold month of October-January, only the adults are found sitting in thousands on the bark of trunk, branches etc.</p><p>The adult surviving winter emerge in February from underneath the bark of tree and other places of shelter. They cluster on the floral buds and start sucking the cell-sap .</p><p>When the infloresence appears, they start laying eggs in them in the second or third week of February and continue to do so for some weeks. The eggs are deposited singly and since they are embedded in plant tissues, it is extremely difficult to observe them under natural conditions. They commence feeding on inflorescence, quickly suck the cell sap and excrete honeydew ,which serve as a medium for the development of shooty mould, Chaetothyrium mangiferae.</p><p>This gives dull blackish look to the mango trees. The smoky black appearance persists for many months until the fruits are mature and the crop is almost over. The full fed nymph then moult and give rise to winged hoppers. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adult</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Idioscopus clypealis (1 generation), Amritodus atkinsoni(3 generation)</head><p>Damage: Mango hoppers are the most destructive pests of fruit tree. Injury to the inflorescence and young shoots is caused by egg laying and feeding.</p><p>The voracious feeding nymphs are particularly harmful. They cause the inflorescence to wither and turn brown. Even if the flowers are fertilized, the subsequent development and fruit setting may ceases.</p><p>A sooty mould develops on patches of honey dew exuded by the nymphs.</p><p>As the wind blows, the young fruits and dried inflorescence break of the axil and fall to the ground. The growth of the young trees is much retard and the older tree does not bear much fruits. Damage to mango crop may be as high as 60 per cent. Management : (1) do not go for high density planting as it provides favourable habitat for hopper multiplication.</p><p>(2) do not give regular irrigation and split doses of nitrogenous fertilizers.</p><p>(3) Avoid water logged and or damp condition. (4) Pruning of branches may be done in the winter to have better light interception.</p><p>(5) spray 2 liters of malathion 50 EC or Carbaryl 50 WP 2.5 kg in 1250 liters of water.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mango mealybug</head><p>Mango mealybug, Drosicha mangiferae (Hemiptera) : Margarodidae.</p><p>• The mango mealybug , besides mango, attacks 62 other plants, including such trees as jack-fruit, the banyan, guava, citrus spp. and jamun.</p><p>• Mark of identification: The wingless females are oval, flattened and have body covered with a white mealy power. The male have one pair of black wings and are crimson red in coolur.</p><p>• Life cycle: The eggs are generally deposited in April-May in soil up to 15 cm within silken pures. The dead body of the female is often found sticking to them. They hatch at the end of December or in January (hatching period 7-9 month) and, in a given locality continue to hatch for about one month. Thus, the nymph appears before the fresh growth of flowers on mango trees and nymphal period of female lasts for 15-35 days with 3 instars and male nymphal period lasts for 1 Week with 4 instar and a pupal period as well. The adult duration is 22-47 days. The young nymphs assend and congregate on the panicles where they feed on cell-sap and pass through three stages. At the time of moulting the young nymphs wander away from the original feeding places in search if suitable shelters such as cracks and crevices in trunk .</p><p>After moulting, they again seek suitable feeding-sites. The third stage nymphs, however, stick to their original feeding places and destined to be females, continue feeding. The mating takes place soon after emergence of the males at a time when the females are not fully developed. The males fly about large numbers, apparently in search of their mates. They have a very strong sex instinct and during the life span of about one week they mate frequently. The female mature after 15-35 days and lay eggs for 22-47 days during April-May.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>The nymphs and adult females are destructive and they suck plant juice, causing tender shoots and flowers to dry up. The young fruits also become juiceless and drop off. The pest is responsible for causing considerable loss to the mango growers and when there is a</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management:</head><p>(1) Remove weeds from orchards which acts as additional hosts for mealybug</p><p>(2) Ploughing of orchards during summer exposes eggs to natural enemies and extreme sun heat.</p><p>(3) Nymphs should be prevented from crawling up the tree by appling 8 cm wide sticky bands with alkthene or plastic sheets around the trunk about 1 meter above the ground level during second week of December .</p><p>(4) The nymphs found congregating below the lower edges of alkathene band should be killed mechanically or by spraying them with 500 ml of methyl parathion 50 EC in 1250 l of water per ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mango stem borer:</head><p>Mango stem borer, Batocera rufomaculata, Batocera rubus (Coleoptera : Cerambycidae) • Host Plant: Mango stem bore is a pest of mango, fig and other tree in northwestern part of the India.</p><p>• Mark of identification : The adults are 5 cm long and 2 cm breath, yellowish brown longicorn beetles, well built, and large. The beetle is provided with long legs and antennae and a dirty white band, extending from the head to tip of the body on each side. A number of dirty yellowish spots are present on the elytra. The full grown larva is a stout, yellowish-white, fleshy grub, measuring about 6cm in length.</p><p>• Life cycle : The adult deposit eggs under the loose bark in a wounded or diseased portion of the trunk or branch. The eggs hatch in7-14 days. The grub are equipped with strong biting mouth parts and they penetrate into the stem or even the roots, feeding on woody tissues. Winter is passed in the grub stage in that very burrow. They make large galleries for feeding. The full grown larva then hollow out a cell for pupation. The larval stage probably lasts more than a year and the pupal stage last about one month.</p><p>The life cycle may be completed in 1-2 year. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grub</head><p>More than a year</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mango wilting due to infestation by stem borer</head><p>Damage :Although the borer is not very common, yet whenever it appears in the main trunk or a branch, it invariably kill the host. Though the external symptoms of attack are not always visible, the site can be located from the sap or frass that come out of the hole.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management :</head><p>(1) Cut and destroy the infested branches with grub and pupa within.</p><p>(2) Remove frass near the hole on main stem and inject 4 ml of methyl parathion 50 EC mixed in one litre of water into the hole and plug it with mud.</p><p>Damage. The damage is caused by both maggot and adults. The adults feed on exudation of ripe fruits and honeydew of various insects. The punctures for egg laying made by the females attract fermenting microorganisms. The maggot destroy the pulp making it foul smelling and discoloured. The fruit develop brown rotten patches on them and fall to the ground ultimately. The infested fruits become unmarketable and at times almost all of them contain maggots. Management : (1) Avoid infestation of fruit flies by early harvesting of mature fruits.</p><p>(2) To prevent the carryover of the pests, collect and destroy all fallen infested fruits twice in a week.</p><p>(3) Plough round the tree during winter to expose and kill the pupae.</p><p>(4) Monitor the fruit fly population in orchards by using methyl eugenol traps.</p><p>(5) Spray    • Management : (1) a thorough clean cultivation/ sanitationof orchard is essential in reducing the pests infested fruits and bury them in at least 60 cm deep pit. The pit may be covered with clay after every 2-3 days and should not be allowed uncovered for a longer period. (2) Avoid taking rainy season crop which may get heavily infested by the pest.</p><p>(3)Plough and stir the soil well before june-july to expose and kill pupae.</p><p>(4) harvest the fruit when slightly hard and green in colour.</p><p>(5) Fix methyl eugenol based PAU fruit fly traps @ 40/ ha in the first week of july and recharge the same if required. (6) in orchards spray 3.15 liters of fenvalrate 20 EC in 1250 litres of water/ ha at weekly intervals on ripening fruits from july onwards till the rainy season crop is over, fruit should be harvested at least after 7 days of spray.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>The young larvae feed only on fresh leaves and the terminal shoots. Habitually, they feed from the margin inwards to the midrib in later stages, they feed on mature leaves and sometimes the entire plant may be defoliated. This pest particularly devastating in nurseries and its damage to foliage seems to synchronize with fresh growth of citrus plants in April and August-September. Heavily attacked plants bear no fruit. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adul t</head><p>Management:</p><p>(1)The egg parasitoids associated with this pests are Trichogramma evanescens and Telenomus sp while the larvae is parasitized by Brachymerria sp.</p><p>(2) hand picking of various stages of the pest in nurseries and field and their destruction will suppress their population.</p><p>(3) Spray Bacillus thuringiensis , DD-136 and neem seedextract (3%) give effective control.</p><p>(4) spray following insecticide% (a) quinalfps 25 EC @ 2.0 liters (b) Indoxacarb 1 ml/lit of water should be sprayed.</p><p>Damage:Thick ribbon like, silken webs are seen running on the bark of the main stem especially near the forks. The larva also make holes as many as 16 may be seen in a tree, one caterpillar occupying each hole. A severe infestation may result in the death of the attacked stem but not of the main trunk. There may be interference with the translocation of cell sap and thus arrestation of growth of the tree is noticed with the resultant reduction in its fruting capacity. Management: <ref type="bibr">(1)</ref>Clean cultivation is essential to prevent infestation of these borers.</p><p>(2)As soon as infestation is noticed, kill the caterpillars mechanically by inserting an iron spike into the holes made by these caterpillars.</p><p>(3) During February -March insert into the borer holes insecticidessoaked cotton sweb or plugs (with the help of metallic spike) and plaster on the outside with mud.</p><p>(4) The insecticides for 10 litres of water are 2 ml dichlorvos 76 EC or 5 ml methyl parathion or 10 ml monocrotofos 36 SL . These chemicals should be applied after removing webbings.</p><p>(5) Treat all alternate host plants in the vicinity of the orchard.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pest of Pomegranate</head><p>Anar Butterfly, Virachola Isocrates or Deudorix Isocrates (Lepidoptera: lycaenidae) • Appearance: Butterfly: Male is bluish-vilot while , Female is brownish violet, with an orange patch on fore wings . • Host Plant: Apple, ber, citrus,guava, litchi,loquat,mulberry, peach, pear, plum, sapata, tamarind. • Caterpillar, dark brown and have short hair and whitish patches all over the body. This is a polyphagous pest.</p><p>• Life cycle: The female butterfly lays shiny white oval shaped eggs on the calyx of flower and on small fruits. • The eggs hatch in 7-10 days. The larval period lasts for 18-47 days • They pupate inside the fruit but occasionally may pupate outside even attaching themselves to the stalk of the fruit. Damage: The caterpillar damage the fruit by feeding inside and riddling through the ripening seeds of pomegranate. As many as eight caterpillars may be found in a single fruit. The infested fruits are also attacked by bacteria and fungi which cause the fruit to rot. The affected fruits ultimately fall off and give an offensive smell. This pest causes 40 to 90 per cent damage.</p><p>Management:(1) Bagging of fruits before maturity will help in checking damage.</p><p>(2) Collection and destruction of fallen infested fruits prevent build up of the pest.</p><p>(3) Remove flowering weeds especially of compositae family. Spray young fruits with 1.75 liters of qunalphos 25 EC in 1250 liters of water per ha during May-June at 15 days interval. 2-3 sprays are enough.</p><p>Pests of Ber (Zizyphus mauritiana, family: Rhamnaceae) Ber fruitfly, Carpomyia visuviana (Diptera: Tephritidiae) Appearance: Adult fly: Brownish yellow, with brown longitudinal stripes on the thorax surrounded by black spots on the side and back of the body. Greyish brown spots on the wings and bristly hairs on the tip of the abdomen. Larvae: Creamy white and slightly smaller than the other fruit flies. Host plant: Zizyphus mauritiana,Z. jujube and Z. sativa. Active period: August to mid November.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adult</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ber fruitfly</head><p>Life cycle: The flies lays eggs in skin of fruit. The egg hatch in 2-3 days .The larval period lasts for 7-10 days. The pupal stage lasts for 14-30 days.There are 2 to 3 brood in a year. The pest is active in winter and hibernate in the soil from April to August in the pupal stage in the soil. Such fruits rot near the stone. There are as many as 18 maggots have been recorded in a fruit.</p><p>The fruit become deformed and there is no further growth of the fruit in the vicinity of this puncture. Fleshy varieties of ber are more seriously damaged than the less fleshy ones.</p><p>The attacked fruits are rotten near the stones and emit a strong smell.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management:</head><p>(1) Collect and destroy the fallen infested fruits at alternate days.</p><p>(2) Rake the soil around the trees during the summer to expose the pupas to heat and natural enemies.</p><p>(3) To escape egg laying on fruits, do not allow the fruits to ripe on the tree, harvest at green and firm stage. (4) Spray 1.25 liters of dimethoate 30EC in 750 liters of water ha 1 during pea fruit stage. • Damage:As a result of the numerous galleries made by the feeding caterpillars, the foliage dries up. infested tree can be located or recognize from the dried up patches in the fronds. In cases of severe attack due to large scale drying of leaflets, the whole plantation presents a burnt up appearance from a distance, results in a considerable reduction in yield. • Management: apply 2.5 liters of chloropyrifos 20 EC in 625 litres of water per ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pests of coconut</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pests of apple</head><p>San jose scale, Quadraspidiotus perniciosus ( Hemiptera : Diaspididae) Appearance: The scale which forms a covering on the body of the insect is black or brown. Underneath, a lemonyellow insect is visible when the covering is lifted.</p><p>Host plant: Prefer Rosaceae family plants such as plum, pear, current, willow, hawthorn and rose.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle:</head><p>The San jose scale gives birth to young ones, each female may give birth to 200-400 nymphs. They become full-grown in 3-40 days and the females again start giving birth to young ones within the next 10-14 days. The gravid mothers live for about 50-53 says. The male hardly live for 24-32 hours. Four over lapping generations are completed in a year. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>The nymph find a suitable place on the host, they insert their mouth parts in to the plant tissue and benign to feed by sucking the cell-sap. All the parts of the plant above the ground are attacked and the injury is due to loss of the cell-sap . At first, the growth of the infested plant is checked, when the scale increases in number, the infested plant may die.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management:</head><p>(1) Sanitation of orchard, infested pruned material should be collected and brunt.</p><p>(2) The parasite Encarsia perniciosi and Aphytis sp. Proclia may be released to checke the overwintering on the wild host plant.</p><p>(3) To check the plant in nursery, apply carbofuran granules @ 0.75-1.0 g a.i. per plant.</p><p>(4) Spray 625 ml of methyl parathion 25EC in 500 liters of water.</p><p>(5) Spray diesel oil emulsion+Bordeaux mixture (diesel oil 68 ltrs+ copper sulphate 15 kg +unslacked lime 3.37 kg) to be emulsified and diluted 5-6 times before spraying.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damaging symptoms</head><p>Winged Adult</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Woolly apple aphid</head><p>Woolly apple aphid, Eriosoma lanigerum (Hemiptera : Aphididae)</p><p>• Appearance: Purplish aphid covered with white cottony mass.</p><p>• Host plant: Apple, pear, crab-apple, howthorn and mountain ash etc Damage: Both nymphs and adults suck the cell-sap from the bark of the twigs, fruit stalk, calyx and from the roots underground. Swelling or knots appear on the roots which hinder the normal plant functions. Owing to the loss of cell-sap, the twigs also shrivel and the young nursery plants may die quickly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management:</head><p>(1) Use of resistant root stock like Golden Delicious and Northern Spy.</p><p>(2) Release specific parasitoid Aphelinus mali which attacks the 4 th and 5 fth stage nymph.</p><p>(3) Select healthy plants from nursery and treat them with chloropyriphos 0.5 % before planting. (5) Carry out fumigation against root forms with paradichlorobenzene granules in 15 cm deep trench dug around the infested tree,about 2 meters from it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pests of ornamental crops</head><p>• Rose is an important ornamental crop grown throughout India in open and greenhouse conditions. The crop is attacked by a large number of pests. In the present lecture students will be taught about the host range, identification, nature of damage, life cycle and management of different pests attacking this crop.</p><p>• Distribution: In India this aphid has been reported on rose in Punjab, Delhi, Karnataka, Mysore, Andhra Pradesh and Nilgiri hills • Host: Rose • Mark of Identification: Small (about 2.5 to 2.6 mm long) wingless aphids having elongated body, large red eyes, black cornicles and a yellowish green tip of abdomen.</p><p>• Damage:The aphids suck the sap from the tender parts Particularly to leaves,tender buds, and twigs, resulting in the disfigurement and withering of flowers. Each aphid makes several punctures producing wounds.A black fungus also develops on the honey dew giving ugly appearance to the plant. Deteriorates the market value of the produce.</p><p>• • Damage: Both nymphs and adults suck the cell sap from the under surface of leaves. The infested leaves become pale yellow then turn brown and ultimately dry up after shriveling.</p><p> This pest appears from March to June Adult females lay eggs on the upper surface of leaves  The incubation period is 8-10 days  There are five nymphal instars  nymph period is 15-27 days  The full developmental life cycle is completed on a single leaf.  The pest over winters in egg stage.</p><p>• Management: Spray dimethoate @ 0.05% and Oxy de meton methyl 0.03%. (500-600ml insecticide /ha)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Jasmine budworm (Hendecasis duplifascialis)</head><p>• Mark of Identification of the pest:</p><p>Larva is yellowish green in colour with pale body hairs and black head. Adult -small white moth with black wavy lines on hind wings and abdomen.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Symptoms of damage :</head><p>Caterpillar makes hole on the flower bud and feeds on the inner content. The larva feeds voraciously on the corolla leaving only the corolla tube in mature buds. In case of younger buds, the larva remain outside the buds and feed in the inner floral whorl through a small hole in the corolla tube. The infested flower turns violet and eventually dries out. A single larva may damage 6 flower bud. During heavy infestation, the adjacent buds along the inflorescence are webbed together by silken thread. buds. Larva attacks 2 -3 buds Petals are eaten by the larvae.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• Management</head><p> Collect and destroy the damaged buds with larvae  Use light trap to attract and kill the adult moths  Spray NSKE 5% or malathion 50EC 2ml/lit  Spray 500 ml of Dimethoate 30 EC or cypermethrin 25EC in 500lt of water/ hac.  Proper pruning and hygienic maintenance of bushes Life cycle: The freshly laid eggs are round, creamy and glued to flower buds. The eggs hatch in 2.6 to 3.5 days and the larvae passes through five instar. The total larval duration varies from 11.5 to 17.0 days depending up on the jasmine species. The pupal stage lasts 6.5 to 9.0 days and the life cycle is completed in 21 to 29 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pest of spices and condiments</head><p>• India is the home of spices, is the largest producer and consumer of spices. During 2012-13, spices were grown in 3.08 million ha and production was 5.74 million tonnes • Since spices come from different parts of plants, belonging to a number of families, the pests that have adopted themselves to feeding on these aromatic plants are also of different types. Apart from the field pests of the Spice plants, a number of insect pests of stored products also damage spices in storage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Fennel aphid</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hyadaphis coriandri Das. (Hemiptera:</head><p>Aphididae)</p><p>• Mark of identification: The first instar nymphs are dull white and became light green in the second instar. The third instar nymphs and adults turned green. Adult: Adults are yellow-green in color, dusted with greyish wax. • Biology:</p><p>• Egg: The females produce wingless off spring which are mated by the males and then lay hard-shelled eggs on the branches. The eggs initially are greenish, but soon turn black. In this form the aphids survive the winter. In Spring the eggs hatch to wingless females which produce winged off spring by parthenogenesis. • Nymph: There were three nymphal instars. The first instar nymphs were dull white and became light green in the second instar. The third instar nymphs and adults turned green. Adult: Adults are yellow-green in color, dusted with greyish wax. They have short, dusky, slightly swollen, siphunculi (or cornicles) that are about twice as long as wide. • Natural enemies of aphid:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle</head><p> Parasitoids: Lysiphlebus sp, Diaeretiella sp, Aphelinus sp, Aphidius colemani etc.  Predators: Ladybird beetle, lacewing, spiders, hover fly etc.</p><p>• Cultural control:</p><p>• Spray pressurized water • Use yellow and blue sticky traps @ 4-5 traps/acre for aphid and thrips, respectively, before flowering.</p><p>• Biological control: • Release Coccinella septumpunctata @ 2000 beetles/ acre (2 releases at 15 days interval) • Chemical control: Spray systemic insecticide.</p><p>Seed Midge, Dasyneura leguminicola (Lint.) (Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</p><p>• This is a tiny, delicate, mosquito like fly that has a bright-red abdomen. It lays eggs on or near the flower heads of clover crops, principally red clover. The newly hatched larvae wriggle into the unopened flowers. They suck the sap from the ovaries and keep the ovules from undeveloping. • The seed crop may be heavily damaged or destroyed.</p><p>• Life cycle: Development of the clover midge is closely correlated with weather and is particularly dependent on rainfall. Three generations are produced each year in the Northwest. The seed crop is grown from May to August; it is the summer generation of midges that damages it.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">G Egg</head><note type="other">Maggot Pupa Adult</note><p>Control is effected by timing the appearance of the flower heads so that the midges find few suitable heads on which to lay their eggs. Pasturing the field in the fall after the seed crop is harvested or in the spring before the seed growth is started will prevent most midges of the fall or spring generations from finding suitable flower heads. In consequence, the summer generation of midges will be small, and little damage will be done to the seed crop</p><p>• Clipping the spring hay growth for mulch about May 20 times the seed growth so that neither the spring nor summer generation midges find suitable flower heads. If a hay crop is raised first, cutting and removing it promptly from the field in early June will kill most of the mature spring-generation larvae in the crop as well as time the blooming of the seed crop so that most summer generation midges will have disappeared before the flowers become attractive for midge oviposition. • It is important to remove the hay promptly because the mature spring-generation midge larvae, needing the moisture to move, will leave the flower heads for the soil and develop into adults if enough rain falls on the hay</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ex.No.18. STUDY OF COLEOPTERAN, LEPIDOPTERAN AND OTHER STORED GRAIN PESTS</head><p>Define storage insect pests.</p><p>• Insects like beetles, moths attack and destroy the grain products in storage bins, mills, warehouses and stores, such insects are commonly called as insect pests of storage.</p><p>• They may be grouped as Primary storage pests: and Secondary storage pests.</p><p>• Primary storage pests: The primary storage pests can attack the sound grains only. • Secondary storage pests: It can attack either the broken grains or the grain already damaged by primary storage pests.</p><p>• They may be grouped as internal feeders and external feeders.</p><p>• Internal feeders: The larvae of these pests feed entirely within the kernels or grain of stored materials ex, Rice weevil ( Sitophilus oryzae),</p><p>Lesser grain borer ( Rhyzopertha dominica), Gram dhora ( Callosobruchus chinensis), Mung dhora(Callosobruchus analis ), Angoumois grain moth( Sitotroga cerealella). • External feeder: The larvae and adults feed on the grain from outside,ex Red rust floor beetle( Tribolium castaneum), Khapra beetle( Trogoderma granarium), Rice moth( Corcyra cephalonica), Almond moth( Ephestia cautella), Indian meal moth( Plodia interpunctella).</p><p>• Storage insects belong to generally two orders namely coleoptera (beetle pests) and lepidoptera (moth pests).</p><p>• In storage, insects cause damage by feeding on grains causing weight loss and loss in quality as they deplete the nutrients.</p><p>• They contaminate the grains with their dead bodies, cast skins, excreta and with their webbings. • • The grains and grain products get bad colour, odour and taste.</p><p>• Under severe infestation, grains become unfit for consumption.</p><p>• Some of the storage insects are known to infest the grains in the field itself. eg. Weevils, Bruchids, Angoumois grain moth, etc). </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adult Egg</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grub Pupa</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle and Damage</head><p>This is the most destructive pest of stored grains throughout the world.</p><p>Both adult and grub causes damage.</p><p>The rice weevil may be found in the field as well.</p><p>The rice weevil breeds from April to October,and hibernate as adult in winter.</p><p>The female lays eggs on the grain by making depression by their maindible.</p><p>A single female lay 400 eggs, the egg hatch in 6-7 days.</p><p>The young grub bore into the grain (25-35 days)where they feed and grow to maturity .</p><p>They pupate in side the grain the pupal stage last 6-14 days .</p><p>On emergence, the adult weevil cuts its way out of the grain and live fore 4-5 months.</p><p>3-4 generations are completed in a year. Sitophilus granaries this is the allied species of Rice weevil. • The beetle is dark brown or black, measures 3 mm long with a cylindrical body.</p><p>• The head is bent under the thorax.</p><p>• Antenna is 3-segmented serrate, grub small and white in colour with bent body.</p><p>• Both adults and grubs bore into the cereal grain and feed inside making irregular holes.</p><p>• It is a serious pest of cereals including paddy. Pupa: Grub enters the grain after 3 rd instar for pupation in Grain, 3-6 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Larva Pupa Adult</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Egg</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grub</head><p>Adult: Brown to blakish beetle, 39-87 days at different temperature.</p><p>Nature of damage: Grub+adult, holes,both feed inside the grain, Powder. • Beetles are small, elongate rust red coloured measuring 3-4 mm in length.</p><p>• Grub is flat, dull yellowish and body covered with setae.</p><p>• Both adults and grubs are external feeders, feeding on broken grains, oilseeds, oil cakes, dried fruits, nuts and processed products like flours, soji, atta, maida etc.</p><p>• It also imparts bad smell to the commodity.</p><p>• The two species occur together and they can be distinguished based on the antennae. Trogoderma granarium (Everts.) (Dermestidae:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Egg</head><p>Coleoptera)</p><p>• Beetle is reddish brown to black; oval shaped measuring 1.5-3.0 mm with clubbed antennae.</p><p>• Larva campodeiform yellowish white covered with long brown hairs.</p><p>• Larva (yellowish-white) is the damaging stage, feeds on many kinds of grains wheat and other grains like sorghum, barley ,rice.</p><p>• The damaging stage is grub only.</p><p>• The attacked wheat loose their commercial value and ultimately become unfit for human consumption.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adult Egg</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Larva</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pupa</head><p>• This is a major pest of stored wheat.</p><p>• Damage is caused by only Larval stage.</p><p>• The grub attacks embryo points first.</p><p>• Germination point of grain is greatly destroyed.</p><p>• Infestation occurs in superficial layer upper 50 cm. • They can survive for 4 years, living for the greater part of it even without food. • Egg, larva and adult stages are susceptible to oxygen.</p><p>Khapra beetle Trogoderma granarium : (coleoptera: Dermestidae)</p><p>• Larvae: 4 mm, yellowish-white,and brownish head at young stage. Yellowish-brown transverse bands across the body, long hairy bristle on the body.</p><p>• The adult is small dark brown beetle,2-3 mm long. The entire body is clothed in fine hairs.</p><p>• The insect breed from April to October.</p><p>• The female lay white translucent eggs in the grain singly or in cluster of 2-5.</p><p>• A female may lay 13-35 eggs which hatch in 3-5 days in June and 6-10 days in October.</p><p>• The male larvae complete its development in 20-30 days while female larvae in 24-40 days.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage</head><p>• The greatest damage is done in Summer from July to October. • The grub eat the grain near the embryo. They confined themselves to the upper 50 cm layer of the grain. • In severe infestation the grain is reduced to mere frass. • Since the larvae are positative thermotactic, they can be collected by merely placing gunny bags on a heap of grain. • White eggs are visible on grains.</p><p>• Adults don't feed, grubs bore into the grain feeding on the internal content.</p><p>• Affected grains show circular emergence holes.</p><p>• Adults are stout bodied beetles with serrate or pectinate antennae.</p><p>• Wings short and exposing the tip of the abdomen uncovered (Pygidium).  (Gelechiidae: Lepidoptera)</p><p>• This is a small moth; yellowishbrown or straw colour with a wing expanse of 1 cm.</p><p>• Wings are narrow pointed and fringed long hairs along the posterior margin.</p><p>• It is an internal feeder.</p><p>• Larva is the damaging stage, which bores into a number of cereals like wheat maize sorghum, barley oat.</p><p>• Neat emergence holes are seen on grains. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Larva</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MANAGEMENT OF STORED GRAIN PESTS</head><p>Hundreds of species of are associated with stored grains. Only 50 of these species are considered as injurious to food grains in terms of quality and quantity of food grains. Disinfestation of stores/receptacles a) Before the use, the receptacles (gunny bags)/store rooms/godown should be disinfested with approved insecticides, viz. Malathion 50 EC @ 10 ml/l or Dichlorvos 76 WSC @ 7 ml/l and apply @ 3 lit/100 m2.</p><p>Chemical control measures a)If produce is meant for seed purpose, mix 1 kg of activated kaolin or malathion 5 %D @250 gm for every 100 kg of seed and store in gunny or polythene bags. b)If produce is meant for grain purpose, For Cereals mix 1 kg of activiated kaolin or 1 kg neem seed kernels for every 100 kg of grain and store in gunny or polythene bags. For Pulse grains -mix 1 kg of activated kaolin or 1 kg edible oil or 1 kg Acorus calamus (Bhaje) powder for every 100 kg of grain. (groundnut, sesamum or mustard oil @ 0.25 to 0.50% can protect pulse from pulse beetle, upto 6 months).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Legal method</head><p>* Entry of an insect which is not found in the particular area can be prevented by the impositionof Destructive Insect Pests Act 1914.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Curative measures:</head><p>The infestation of stored grain insect pests can be controlled by the following methods. Hence, timely detection of the stored grain insects will help to prevent heavy losses.</p><p>• TNAU is one of the pioneering institutes in India in the development of detection devices for stored grain insects.</p><p>• These devices exploit the wandering behaviour of the insects and help in timely detection of insects in stored produce leading to timely control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• These include TNAU probe trap, TNAU pit fall trap, two in one model trap, indicator device, Automatic insect removal bin, UV light trap technology, Egg</head><p>removal device and Stack Trap.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• These devices have been widely used in many places and have received State and National recognitions.</head><p>• Hence, the Department of Agricultural Entomology, Centre for Plant Protection Studies, TNAU, Coimbatore has developed a "KIT" named as TNAU Stored Grain Insect Pest Management -Kit containing prototypes of all the devices along with a CD-Rom about the devices and how to use them.</p><p>• This kit will be of great use in popularization of the technologies across the country.</p><p>• The kit will be an ideal "hands -on training" tool for Education, Extension centers (KVK, Plant clinic, save grain centers) and also for private warehousing.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. OTHER STORED GRAIN PESTS I) RODENTS:</head><p>Rodents include rats, bandicoots, gerbils, Squirrels and Porcupines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rats Bandicoot Gerbil</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Squirrel Porcupines</head><p>A) Rats:</p><p>• Some of them occur in houses and others in fields and stores.</p><p>• Some of them burrow the land, floors, feed on grains, cause spillage of grains and collapse of stacks.</p><p>• In the field, they are serious pests on many cereals and oilseed crops.</p><p>• They contaminate the food stuffs with urine, hairs and their excreta.</p><p>1. The house mouse: Mus musculus L.</p><p>• It can live indoors in close association with the house rat.</p><p>• It is the smallest measuring 2-3 inches.</p><p>• It destroys clothes, sacs, paper etc. and feeds on food materials.</p><p>Mus musculus L.</p><p>2. House rat: Rattus rattus L.</p><p>• It is the commonest house rat distributed all over India and the world.</p><p>• It weighs 150-300 g with slightly longer tail.</p><p>• It can occur in fields of coconut and other crops.</p><p>• It cannot burrow but can make nest in the trees.</p><p>3. Brown or Norway rat: Rattus norvegicus W.</p><p>• It is found mainly at ports in tropical countries.</p><p>• As compared to R. rattus, it has blunt muzzle, smaller ears and tail.</p><p>• It is also found in Sewers. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>White rat Rattus norvegicus</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Yellow stem borer (Scirpophaga incertulas) (Lepidoptera; Family -Pyralidae)</head><p> The yellow stem borer is a specific pest of rice and is common in all the Asian countries. The caterpillars alone are destructive and, when fullgrown, they measure about 20 mm and are dirty white or greenish yellow, having brown head and pronotum. The adults have a wing expanse of 25-45 mm and are yellowish white with orange yellow front wings. The females have a prominent tuft of brownish yellow silken hair at the tip of their abdomen. The female moth is bigger than the male moth and has a centrally situated black spot on each of the forewings.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II) BIRD PESTS:</head><p>• Birds are important pests in fields and cause severe damage to the crops at milky stage, sometimes the damage being very severe in crops like sunflower, jowar, pulses and also in fruits.</p><p>• They also feed on stored grains in store houses and threshing yards.</p><p>• Some birds feed on crop pests and are thus beneficial (eg. Myna).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Storage structures and methods of grain storage</head><p>• Grain storage</p><p>• Parameters : The store must satisfy the following parameters as far as possible: (a) The grain must be kept dry; (b) The grain should be kept at a uniform temperature; (c) The grain should be protected from insect attack; (d) Rodents and birds should be excluded. It is evident from previous sections that, in many cases, facilities for drying and storage are found in one and the same structure. Combining these functions is economical and allows further conditioning at later stages if required.</p><p>• For example, if a hot spot develops in a storage bin, it can easily be ventilated again. It may also be possible to provide some low-volume ventilation in an otherwise pure storage system. • However, there are situations where storage is considered quite separately from drying, ranging from the storage of naturally dried crops to the storage of grain from a continuousflow or batch dryer. • The size and type of a storage facility is likely to be dictated by: i.</p><p>total volume of crop/produce to be stored; ii.</p><p>the storage requirements for the crop/produce to be stored; iii. the unit cost of various types of storage; iv. the form in which the crop/produce is stored, i.e. cob maize versus shelled maize, or bagged wheat versus bulk wheat.</p><p>• The volume of the store required can be estimated from the expected yield and the land area. • A comparison between different forms of storage is normally made by calculating costs per tonne of capacity. • The form of storage depends not only on how the crop is harvested, the volume and the way it is delivered to the market, but also on the overall cost. • Where drying is a problem, bag storage has the advantage of allowing a higher moisture content than bulk storage. • For maize, the requirement for safe storage is a maximum of 15 per cent and 12 percent moisture content respectively. In general terms, the respective advantages and disadvantages of bag and bulk storage are: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grain storage structures</head><p>Grain is generally stored either in bags or in bulk. A combined system of bag-cum-bulk storage is also practiced in some parts of the country. In villages the bulk storage system is more common than the storage in bags which is considered to be a practicable method of storing grain in the government godowns as well as in trade. There main following three types of storage structures for storage of grains. Improved storage structures are the storage structures for storage of food grains. In this type of storage structures there are some improvements made in traditional storage structures. This type of storage structures having a higher storage capacity and long term storage of food grains than traditional storage structures. Improved type of storage structures having capacities is generally 1.5 to 150 tonnes. The storage of grain is generally done in one of the following storage structures in the different rural and urban regions of India in bulk, bag as well as bag and bulk storage. 1 Pusa bin Pusa bin is like other traditional storage structures made of mud. To make the storage structure moisture proof a plastic film is used in all the inner sides of the bin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2">Brick and cement bin</head><p>These type of storage structures are very strong and effect of seasons on these is minimum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3">Bunker Storage</head><p>These type of storage structure is used for long term storage and a larger volume of grains storage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">'CAP' Storage structures</head><p>The word 'CAP' is used for cover and plinth, plinth from the bottom and cover from the top. This type of open storage is considered as transit storage and serves the purpose of storage of food grains in bags for short period.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pusa bin</head><p>• This ia a rectangular structure of 1.7 m x 1.2 m x 7 cm thick. • This design consists of two bricks walls of 10 cm thick each using sun dried brickswith polythene sheet sandwitch in between. The structure is condtructed on a brick masonary plateform plastered with cement mortar. A mud slab is provided as top on wooden frame structure.the polythene sheet is also provided at the top qnd the base to make the structure completely moisture proof and air gtight. • When the structure is filled with grain the main hole is finally sealed with a square piece of polythene film.</p><p>Bulk storage installations.</p><p>• In bulk storage structure , large scale storage instalations with adequate storage and mechanical grain handling facilities are used by grain handling authorities in the countries like Food Corporation of India, Marketing Cooperative Federations, central and state wherehousing corporations etc. • The storage bins or silo have a capacity of 10,000 each and provide for bulk storage of grain. The elevators are provided with mechanical operations for receving and issuing out grain with the help of a mechanical system on scientific lines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Domestic metal bins</head><p>• Several types of domestic designs of metal bins have been developed, the capacity of which range from 3 to 27.5 quintals. These are indore bins and may be kept in room or varandaqh under a roof. The bins are made from galvanized iron sheets and are moisture, rodent and insect proof. These are found suitable for storage of wheat, paddy,maize, pulse and seed grains.</p><p>In India, for larger volume of food grains are to be stored in bulk is 'silo' and conventional godowns (Shed) designed for bagged storage. The godowns side walls are of brick or stone masonry and sloped roofing in asbestos or Corrugated Galvanized Iron (CGI) sheets over steel trusses. Silos are constructed from steel or reinforced concrete. There are a cluster of adjoining silos in any modern large/ capacity processing plant. The modern permanent storage system should be selected for the safe keeping of stored grains and other products. The modern storage structures should be selected on the basis of first on quality and then on cost considerations. There are following types of modern storage structures. 1 Silo type of storage structures Silos/bins are classified into two groups depending upon the relative dimensions of the container. These are classified as, (1) deep bins and (2) shallow bins. Farm silos is a farm structure used to store and protect the animal fodder so that it is preserved in an ideal condition for farm animals. Animal fodder is cut and packed in the air tight silo to allow a partial fermentation to occur. The storage fodder is known as silage. There are two types of farm silos i) Tower silos and ii) Horizontal silos.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1">Tower silos</head><p>Cylindrical Shpe and made of masonary, wood or metal Cost of construction is comparatively much higher than that of horizontal type. Loading of animal fodder is difficult. Mechanical loader or a large capacity of blower is essential. This type of storage structures are not recommended under Indian conditions.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2">Horizontal silos:</head><p>In horizontal silos pit type, bunker type and trench or stake type of storage structures used for storage of animal fodder. There are surface as well as below ground (underground) types of storage structures used on most of dairy farms as temporary and permanent storage structures for silage. The spoilage of silage and dry matter losses of these silos ranges between 20 to 30 percent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.1">Pit Silos</head><p>• Permanent pit silo is a circular deep well which is lined all around the side, and sealed from bottom, so that water may not rise in to it. • Made in areas where the soil is deep and the water table is very low.</p><p>• Made of bricks, stones or concrete, and either cement or lime can be used as a binding material. • A 22.5 cm thick wall will be used satisfactory up to 15 meter depth.</p><p>• The entire surface which is coming in contact with the silage should be plastered to make it smooth, air tight and water tight. • Simple roof is made over the silo to protect the silage from sun and rain.</p><p>• Corrugated metal sheet dome or half pitch roof with ample overhang on all the sides are most economical and provide more space for filling. • Stairs may be built along with wall for removing silage from the silo.</p><p>• The diameter of a silo is usually limited to 6 m and its depth is kept 2 to 3 times that of diameter. • When the silo is opened for removing the silage, nobody should enter till the gases are removed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.2">Trench Silos</head><p>• Unlined trench silo can be made easily without involving any investment on building materials such as brick, cement and sand. • Unlined silos give more spoilage and are likely to have caved side walls due to excessive rain and tend to become muddy at the bottom. So, lined trench silos are therefore become popular. • The walls of the trench silos can be lined with brick, concrete or cement plaster with reinforcing wire mesh. • If possible the silo should be roofed.</p><p>• Drains should be made around trench to intercept surface water.</p><p>• To facilitate drainage it is desirable to locate the trench silo on slopping ground. • Capacity is depends on size of herd and number of day the silage is fed in a year. • It is always economical to construct only one trench silo, even if it is quite larger. • Sidewalls are given generally 33 per cent slope.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Principles of stored grains pest management A. Preventive measures</head><p> Remove all debris -cracks, crevices and corners  Threshing floor or yards free from insect infestation  Clean the machines, harvester and thresher  Truck, trolleys or bullock carts free from infestation  Clean the godown or storage structure before storing  Metal sheet -25 cm height -bottom of the wood in doors  Fix up wire meshes -windows, ventilators, gutters, drains etc -rats, birds, and squirrels control  Remove dirt, rubbish, sweepings and webbings from the godown  Close rat burrows -a mixture of broken glass pieces and mud and plaster with cement  They feed (maggot) inside the main shoot for 6-10 days and, when full grown, they may pupate either inside the stem or come out and pupatein the soil. The pupal period in the summer lasts about 7 days. Several generations are completed in a year. In northern India, the pest over-winters in the pupal stage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Damage</head><p>The insect attacks the young crop when it is in the six-leaf stage. As the maggots feed on the main shoot, the growing point is destroyed and by the time they pupate, the plant is almost dead. The young plants show typical dead-heart symptoms. When the attacked plants are somewhat older, tillers are produced, which mature later than the main crop. The total loss in yield is sometimes as high as 60 per cent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Management</head><p>i. Seed coating with imidacloprid 600 FS @ 15 ml per kg seed or isofenphos 5G @ 30 g per 100 g seed provides protect on against shoot fly upto 2 weeks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MAIZE (Zea mays, Family : Gramineae)</head><p> More than 130 insects have been recorded causing damage to maize in India.</p><p>Among these, about half a dozen pests are of economic importance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Maize borer, (Chilo partellus) (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae)</head><p> It is the most destructive pest of maize and sorghum in Sri Lanka, India, Pakistan, Afghanistan, Uganda, Central and East Africa. It is found throughout India. This insect has also been recorded on bajra(Pennisetun typhoides), sugarcane, Sudangrass, baru (Sorghum halepense), sarkanda (Saccharum munja) and some other grasses.  The grown up caterpillars are about 20-25mm long and dirty greyish white, with blackhead and four brownish longitudinal stripes on the back.</p><p>The adults are yellowish grey moths, about 25 mm across the wings when spread.</p><p> Life-cycle: The eggs are laid in overlapping clusters of in rows on the undersurface of the leaves during April-May. A female lays over 300eggs during its life-span of 2-12 days and the eggs hatch in 4-5 days in summer.</p><p>The young larvae first feed on the leaves, making a few shot holes and then bore their way downwardthrough the central whorl as it opens</p><p>The larva becomes full-fed in 14-28 days, passing through six stages and after making a hole in the stem pupates inside it. The life-cycle is completed in about 3 weeks and there are probably 5 generations in a year. The full-grown caterpillars of the last generation hibernate in stubble, stalks, etc., and remain there till the next spring.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage</head><p>The damage is done by the caterpillars by feeding inside the stem and producing 'deadhearts'. About 25-50 per cent of the plants are destroyed. Management i. The potential for carry over may be reduced by destroying the stubble,weeds and other alternate hosts of the stem borer by ploughing the field after harvest. ii. Removal and destruction of dead-hearts and destruction of infested plants showing earlyp in-hole damage has been found to be successful practice in reducing the pest incidence. iii. Destruction of crop residues and chopping of stems harbouring diapausing larvae can be very effective in reducing borer population. iv. Release laboratory bred adult populationsof Trichogramma spp. at the first sight of egg masses of maize borer and synchronize the release of Apanteles sp. or Microbracon sp. adults with the larval (a) Spray the crop 2-3 weeks after sowing or as soon as borer injury to the leaves is noticed with any of the following synthetic pyrethroids using 300 litres of water per ha. fenvalerate 20EC@ 100 ml/ha, cypermethrin 10EC 100 ml/ha or deltamethrin 2.8EC @200 ml/ha. Usually, no additional spray or granular application is required after the spray with pyrethroids. (b) Alternatively, the crop should be sprayed with any of the following insecticides:, monocrotophos 36SL @ 275 ml/ha, or carbaryl 50WP @ 250 g/ha.</p><p>(c) After this spray, apply twice at 7-10 days intervals any of the following insecticides in the whorls of only infested plants that show fresh borer injury in the central leaves: fenitrothion or trichlorphon 5 D or trichlorphon 4G. In case of dust, mix it with equal quantity of moist soil before application. Apply a pinch of this mixture to the whorl of plants. Usually1.5-2.5 kg of the insecticide would be required per ha for one application. Apply granules to the whorl of plants@0.5-1.25 kg/ha per application through a bottle with a few holes in its cap.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SUGARCANE INSECT PESTS</head><p> In India, sugarcane is produced in both tropical and subtropical regions. The major  Sugarcane growing districts Kurukshetra, Yamunanagar, Karnal, Sonipat, Rohtak, Faridabadand Panipat in which farming of this crop is done. Besides sugar, cane juice possesses severalvitamins and minerals that provide immense health benefits for people suffering from variety of conditions. Among various limiting factors for low yield of pulse crops, the incidence of insect pests assumes high significance. These are describing as below: i. after which the larvae pupates in the tunnel within the sugarcane stalk where they had been feeding before. Total 4-5 generation in a year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Early Shoot Borer (Chilo infescatellus) ii. Internode Borer (Chilo Saccharifagus Indicus) iii. Top Borer (ScirpophagaExcerptalis) iv. Scale Insect (MelanaspisGlomerata) v. Pyrilla (Pyrilla purpusilla Walker) vi. Termites ( Odontotermes assmuthi) vii. Whitefly (Aleurolobus barodensis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage Symptoms:</head><p>Shoot borer infestation is high during pre-monsoon period (April-June) when ambient temperature remains usually high with low relative humidity. Borer attacks the cropduring the early part of cane growth, before internode formation.</p><p>Larvae enter the cane internally through one or more holes in the stalks (shoot) just above the ground level and bores downwards as well as upwards killing the growing point this leads to gaps in the field. Thus,it cuts of the central leaf spindle, which eventually dries forming a 'dead heart'. Dead heart in1-3 month old crop, whichcan be easily pulled out, dead heart emits an offensive odour. Asingle caterpillar may destroy three or four shoots before it pupate. Borer activity decreases appreciably with the onset of monsoon. Management:</p><p>(1) February -March: At the time of sowing Setts are treated with 2.5 L chlorpyriphos 20 EC or 600 ml fipronil 5 EC (Reagent) (for sandy soil 700 ml) in 600-1000 Lwater per acre. Spray on the furrow with the help of knapsack sprayer or use 150 ml imidachloprid 200 SL in 250-300 L water or 8 kg Dursban 10G / 10 kg fipronil 0.3 G / 7.5 kgSevidol 4G per acre.</p><p>(2) April-June: When the soil testing is not done at the time of sowing treat the setts withabove any one insecticide. In May-June giving irrigation at 10 days intervals to protect thecrop SUGARCANE Whitefly (Aleurolobus barodensis, Hemiptera, Aleyrodidae)</p><p>• Identification: Nymph of the whitefly is 3mm long oval, scale like in form and black in color and has a silvery grey waxy coating on the body. The adults are small delicate, pale yellow and their wings have a white mealy appearance, molted with black dots. They move about briskly, but they are not easily noticed in the field. (1) Sometimes leafhopper will be attacked in April to June. Spray 1000 ml mlmalathion 50 EC in 400 L water per acre.</p><p>(2) Epiricania melanoleuca and Epipyrops melanoleuca,@4000-5000 cocoons or 4-6 lakh eggs/ha. biological agent control the Pyrilla spray with Malathion 50 EC in 800-1000 ml /ha in 400 liter of water</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pests of pulses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Gram pod borer,Helicoverpa armigera Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)</head><p>The gram pod-borer or the gram caterpillar is cosmopolitan and is serious pest of chickpea, pigeon pea, mungbean, urdbean, lentil soybean and cowpea. The insect has also been found damaging cotton, sorghum, okra, maize, tomato, berseem, sunflower and wheat also.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification:</head><p>The moth is stoutly built and is yellowish brown. The forewings are marked with greyish wavy lines and black spots of varying size on the upper side and a black kidney shaped mark and a round spot on the underside. The hind wings are whitish and lighter in colour with a broad blackish band along the outer margin. The caterpillars when full-grown, are 3.5 cm in length, being greenish with dark broken grey lines along the sides of the body.</p><p>The female moths lay yellowish-white eggs on the under surface of leaves, shoots, stems, or in the soil. This cutworm is a sporadic pest of major importance. In some years, 50 per cent of the gram crop may be destroyed. The caterpillars spend the day hiding near and about the plant bases. They remain in the top 5-10 cm of the soil near the plants that might have been cut the night before. At night, they come out and become active, cutting down the young plants of gram, potato, vegetable seedlings, etc. just above or slightly below the surface of the soil they seem to be very voracious eaters and they cut more plants than they can consume.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management.</head><p>The pest can be controlled with fenvalerate .4D @ 25 kg per ha or spray 80ml fenvalerate 20 EC or 50 m1 cypermethrin 25 EC or 150 ml decamethrin 2.8EC in 100 litres of water per ha.</p><p>• Distribution : Tropical and sub-tropical part of the world.</p><p>• Host plant : Pulses, Tobacco, Castor, Groundnut, Tomato, Sunflower, Cabbage and Cruciferous plants. • Mark of identification : Caterpillar is 35-40 mm in length and they are velvety black with yellowish-green dorsal stripes and lateral white bands.</p><p>• Moth is 22 mm long and measure 40 mm across the spread wings.</p><p>The fore wings have beautiful golden and greyish brown pattern.</p><p>• This a polyphagous pests breeds throughout the year. The female are active at night and lay 300 eggs in cluster. The eggs cluster are covered by brown hairs.</p><p>• They hatch in 3-5 days. They pass through six stage and become fully develop in 15-30 days.</p><p>• The larva enter the soil where they pupate. The pupal stage lasts for 7-15 days. The moth live for 7-10 days.</p><p>• The life cycle is completed in 32-60 days and the pest complete 8 generation in a year.</p><p>• The natural enemies ,Compoletis and Eriborus and Rogus sp are associated with larvae.</p><p>Damage:</p><p>• The damaging stage of this pest is caterpillar.</p><p>• The larvae feed gregariously for the first few days and then dispers to feed individually. • The larvae feeds on leaves and fresh growth.</p><p>• They are mostly active at night and causes extensive damage, particularly in tobacco nurseries.</p><p>• Remove the egg masses and cluster of larvae and destroy them. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pest of oil seed crop</head><p>Among the principal commercial crops grown in India, the oilseeds occupy a prominent place with a production of 25.1 million tonnes from an area of 23.4 million ha in 2003-04. These crops are damaged by a number of pests, of which mustard aphid, mustard sawfly and the painted bug are more serious. The insect breeds parthenogenetically and the females give birth to 26-133 nymphs. They grow very fast and are full-fed in 7-10 days. About 45 generations are completed in a year. The winged forms are produced in autumn and spring, and they spread from field to field and from locality to locality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Damage.</head><p>Both the nymphs and adults suck cell-sap from leaves, stems, inflorescence or the developing pods. Due to the very high population of the pest, the vitality of plants is greatly reduced. The leaves acquire a curly appearance, the flowers fail to form pods and the developing pods do not produce healthy seeds. The honey dew excreted by the aphids provides congenial conditions for the growth of sooty mould on the plant. In case of severe infestation the crop yield may be reduced by even 80 per cent or more.  Management. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Early sowing reduces the incidence of mustard aphid</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.Painted bug, Bagrada hilaris (Burmeister)</head><p>(Hemiptera : Pentatomidae)</p><p> The painted bug is a serious pest of cruciferous crops and is widely distributed in Myanmar, Sri Lanka, India, Iraq, Arabia and East Africa. Besides cruciferous crops, it has also been observed feeding on rice, sugarcane, indigo and coffee.</p><p> Mark of identification  Damage.</p><p>The painted bug appears at two stages of crop growth, i.e. seedling and maturity and many times infestation is carried even to threshing floor. Both nymphs and adults suck cell sap from the leaves and developing pods, which gradually wilt and dry up. Severe attack at seedling stage may even kill the plants. The nymphs and adult bugs also excrete a sort of resinous material which spoils the pods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Management:</head><p>Clean cultivation and quick threshing of harvested crop helps in lowering the incidence of the pest. Spray one litre of malathion 50EC or quinalphos 25EC in 150-200 litres of water per ha once in October and again in March-April. The coccinellid beetle, Menochilus sexmaculatus (Fabricius) (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae) and lschiodon javana (Wiedemann) (Diptera: Syrphidae) are the main predators of this aphid pest.  Damage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GROUNDNUT (Arachis</head><p>The nymphs and adults suck the sap, usually from the underside of leaves. Infestation in the early stages causes stunting of the plants as well as reducing their vigour. When the attack occurs at the time of flowering and pod formation, the yield is reduced considerably. Infestation on the groundnut crop usually occurs 4-6 weeks after sowing. The aphid is also vector of rossette disease of groundnut.  Management.</p><p>As soon as the pest appears on growing points, spray 625 ml of malathion 50EC or 425 ml of dimethoate 3OEC or 425 ml of oxydemeton methyl 25EC in 200 litres of water per ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.SOYBEEN GIRDLE BEETLE Obereopsis brevis</head><p>(Gahan) (Coleoptera :Cerambycidae)</p><p> Identification. The adult is a small black beetle with hard shell-like exterior and rather on antennae. The freshly emerged adult is yellow, red, brown on the head thorax and bases of elytra. The larva is white, soft-bodied worm with a dark head.  Host plants. This is an important pest of soybean and also attacks cowpea and lablab.  Life-history. The ovipositing female beetle girdles the stem twice and makes it 3 punctures Just above the lower ring before inserting a single egg through the largest whole into the pith. This results in dropping of the upper part of the stem. A female beetle lays 7 -13 eggs and they hatch in 4-5 days. The larva tunnels upwards and downwards within the stem and a single larva can destroy the whole plant.</p><p>• The larval period lasts 34-47 days. Over-wintering takes place as the full-grown larva within the feeding tunnel in a gall-like chamber near the base of the plant in the girdled portion of the stem which has fallen out or under plant debris. The Pupal period is 8-11 days. Damage. The attack of this insect begins initially in the last week of July to fortnight of August. The female of this insect feeds on the xylem of the stem. The larvae further and fill these with excreta.</p><p>The leaves and the growing point get damaged. The grub tunnel the stem and plants dry up. In later stages, the plant is cut at about 15-25 cm above the ground and broken stems can be seen in the field. Management. Trizophos 0.05% quinalphos0.05%, Monocrotophos @ 2ml/ lit of water, Imidacloprid @ 0.3 ml / lit of water Acetamiprid @ 0.5 gm / lit of water etc .</p><p>CASTOR (Ricinus communis L; Family: Euphorbiaceae)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.Castor semilooper, Achaea janata (Linnaeus) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)</head><p>This is a serious pest of castor in all parts of India and Pakistan and has also been reported from Sri Lanka and Thailand.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mark of identification:</head><p>The adult of A. janata is a pale reddish brown moth with a wing expanse of 6-7 cm. The wings are decorated with broad zig-zag markings, a large pale area and dark brown patches. The full grown larva is dark and is marked with prominent blue-black, yellow and reddish stripes.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Life cycle.</head><p>A female lays up to 450 eggs during its life span. The egg, being </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">Castor capsule borer, Conogethes puntiferalis ( Lepidoptera : pyralidae )</head><p> This bore is distributed throught India wherever castor is grown such as Utter Pradesh, Bihar, Orissa, Maharastra, Gujarat, Karnataka, Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu.</p><p> Mark of identification  The full-grown caterpillar measures 25-30 mm in length, is radish brown, with black blotches all over the body and a pale stripes on the lateral side. The moth are orange yellow with black markings on both the wings.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Life cycle.</head><p>The moth lays eggs on leaves and other soft parts of the plant.</p><p>The eggs hatch in about a week (7days).</p><p>The larvae passes through 4-5 instars and are full fed in 2-3 weeks. Pupation takes place inside the seed or some times in the frass.</p><p>The pupal stage lasts about a (7 days) week.</p><p>The life cycle is completed in 4-5 week and 3 generation are completed in a year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage.</head><p>The attack by this borer is recognized from a distance by the webbed capsule heads. The yield is reduced considerably since the capsules and seeds within are damaged.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Management.</head><p>(1) it is advisable that the infested shoots and capsules may be collected and destroyed.  The sesame leaf and pod caterpillar is a serious and regular pest of til (S. indicum) and is also distributed throughout India. This species has also been reported from Europe, Africa, Cyprus, Malta, Indonesia and South-east Africa.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mark of Identification:</head><p> The caterpillars are pale yellow, when young, but gradually become green and develop black dots all over the body. The fullgrown larva measures 14-17 mm. The moth is a small insect with a wing span of about 2 cm having dark brown markings on the wing-tips.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Life cycle.</head><p>Females lay up to 140 eggs singly on the tender portions of plants at night. The eggs are shiny, pale-green and they hatch in 2-7 days, depending upon the season. On emerging, the young larva, which measures about 2 mm in length, feeds for a little while on the leaf epidermis or within the leaf tissue. Soon after, it binds together the tender leaves of the growing shoot with the help of silken threads and continues to feed in the webbed mass.</p><p> The size of this rolled mass increases gradually as the caterpillar grows older. It becomes full-grown in about 10 days in summer, but the period may be prolonged to 33 days in winter.</p><p> The grown-up larvae creep to the ground and pupate in silken cocoons in soil.</p><p> Sometimes, pupation also takes place in the plant itself. Pupal development is completed in 4-20 days, depending upon the season.</p><p> In summer, a generation is completed in about 23 days but in the winter it takes about 67 days.</p><p> Damage.</p><p>Young caterpillars feed on leaves. They also bore into the shoots, flowers, buds and pods. An early attack kills the whole plant, but infestation of the shoots at a later Stage hampers further growth and flowering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> Management.</head><p>Spray the crop twice (first at pest appearance and then at flowering stage) with 250 ml of fenvalerate 20EC or 375 ml of deltamethrin 2.8 EC or, thrice with 500 ml of cypermethrin 10EC at pest appearance, flowering and pod formation in 250 liters of Water per ha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PESTS OF COTTON</head><p> COTTON (Gossypium spp.: Family :Malvaceae) Although India occupies the largest area in the world under cotton, it ranks third in production. More than 1326 species of insects have been reported attacking cotton in the World However, in India, only 162 species have been recorded, among which only 15 species may be called as major pests due to their occurrence in serious proportions almost every year. 1. Pink bollworm, Pectinophora gossypiella (Saunders) (Lepidoptera -Gelechiidae) 2. Spotted bollworms, Earias insulana (Boisduval) and E. Vittella (Fabricius) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) 3. American bollworm, Helicoverpa armigera (Hubner) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) 4. Cotton leafhopper, Amrasca biguttula biguttula (lshida) (Hemiptera Cicadellidae) 5. Cotton whitefly, Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) (Hemiptera : Aleyrodidae 6. Cotton aphid, Aphis gossypii Glover (Hemiptera: Aphididae) The cotton leafhopper is widely distributed in India and is the most destructive pest of American cotton in the north-western regions. Besides cotton, it also feeds on okra, potato brinjal and some wild plants, like hollyhock, kangi buti, etc. Adults are about 3 mm long and greenish yellow during the summer, acquiring a reddish tinge in the winter.</p><p>Life cycle. The females lay about 15 yellowish eggs on the underside of the leaves, embedding them into the leaf veins. The eggs hatch in 4-11days and give rise to nymphs which are wedge-shaped and are very active. They suck cell-sap from the underside of the leaves and pass through six stages of growth in 7-21 days. On transformation into winged adults, they live for 5-7 weeks, feeding constantly on the plant juice. The pest completes seven generations in a year.</p><p>Damage.Injury to plants is caused both by the nymphs and the adultswhich suck sap from the foliage and probably also due to the injection of toxins into the plant tissues. The attacked leaves turn pale and then rust-red. With change in appearance, the leaves also turn downwards, dry up and fall to the ground. Owing to the loss of plant vitality, the cotton bolls also drop off, causing upto 35 per cent reduction in yield.</p><p>Management. Grow American cotton varieties which are resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack. In Punjab, recommended varieties are F1861, F1378, F846, LH1556 and hybrid LH144, all of which are moderately resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack.</p><p>Spray against leafhopper should be done only at economic threshold level of 1-2 nymphs per leaf or when second grade injury symptoms (yellowing and curling at margins of leaves) appear in 50 per cent of the plants. Any one of the following insecticides can be used in 250 litres of water per ha: 750 ml of formothion 25EC or oxydemeton methyl 25EC, 625 ml of dimethoate 30EC, 100 m1 of imidacloprid 200 SL, 50g of acatamiprid 20SP, 100g of thiamethoxam 25WG. At the time of sowing, smear the cotton seed with imidacloprid 75WS@ 5g/kg seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Cotton whitefly, Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) (Hemiptera : Aleyrodidae)</head><p> This pest is distributed throughout the northern and western regions of the Indian Subcontinent and is a very serious pest of American cotton, particularly in the dry areas. Apart from cotton, this insect also feeds on various other plants such as cabbage, cauliflower, sarson, toria, melon, potato, brinjal, okra and some weeds.  In the winged stage, they are 1.0-1.5 mmlong and their yellowish bodies are slightly dusted with a white waxy powder.They have two pairs of pure white wings and have prominent long hind wings.  Life-cycle : Females lay stalked eggs singly on the underside of the leaves, averaging 119 eggs per female. The eggs hatch in 3-5 days during summer, 5-33 days in winter. The nymphs feed on cell-sap and grow into three stages to form the pupae within 9-14 days in summer and in 17-81 days in winter. In 2-8 days, the pupae change into whiteflies. The total life-cycle is completed in 14-122 days and 11 generations are completed in a year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage.</head><p>The damage is caused by both the nymphs and the adults by sucking the sap from the leaves. Insects exude honeydew which attracts sooty mould. Therefore, in severe infestation, the plants not only become weak, but the mould interferes with the normal photosynthesis resulting in poor growth and yield of cotton. B. tabaci is known to transmit number of virus diseases including the cotton leaf curl, the leaf curl disease of tobacco, the vein clearing disease of okra and the leaf curl of sesame.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management.</head><p>Grow American cotton varieties which are resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack. In Punjab, recommended varieties are F1861, F1378, F846, LH1556 and hybrid LH144, all of which are moderately resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Red cotton bug, Dysdercus koennigii ( Hemiptera:</head><p>Pyrrhocoridae)</p><p>• This insect is widely distributed in India and is a minorpest of cotton in the Punjab and UP. Apart from cotton it feeds on okra, maize, pearmillet,etc. The bugs are elongated slender insect crimson red with white bands across the abdomen. The membraneous portion of their fore wings, antennae and scutillum is black. Both adults and their nymphs feed on the cell-sap of cotton, hollyhock, wheat, maize, pearlmillet, clovers etc. • Life cycle : This insect is active throughout the year and passes winter in the adult stage. In spring the bugs becomes active and lays, egg on an average , 100-130 eggs in moist soils or in crevices in the ground. The eggs are spherical , bright yellow and are laid in the in cluster or in loose irregular masses of 70-80 eggs each. They hatch in 7-8 days and the young nymphs have flabby abdomens, but as they grow older, they become more slender and develop black markings on the body. There are five nymphal stages and the development is completed in 49-89 days. In summer, the life of an adult is very varaible, but in winter, it may live up to three months .The predacious bugs like Antilochus cocqueberti and Harpactor costalisfeed on nymph and adults.</p><p>• Damage : the insect sucks the cell-sap from the leaves and green bolls of cotton. Heavily attacked bolls open badly and the lint is of poorer quality. The seeds produced may also have low germination and less oil. The bugs stain the lint with their excreta or body juice as they are crushed in the ginning factories. The staining of lint by the growth of certainbacteria inside the bolls is also believed to be initiated by these bugs. • Management. Any one of the following insecticides can be used in 250 litres of water per ha: 750 ml of formothion 25EC or oxydemeton methyl 25EC, 625 ml of dimethoate 30EC, 100 m1 of imidacloprid 200 SL, 50g of acatamiprid 20SP, 100g of thiamethoxam 25WG. At the time of sowing, smear the cotton seed with imidacloprid 75WS@ 5g/kg seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Pink bollworm, Pectinophora gossypiella (Saunders) (Lepidoptera -Gelechiidae)</head><p>• The pink bollworm is one of the most destructive pests 0f Cotton and is found in America, Africa, Australia and Asia. It is highly destructive in India and Pakistan. • The adult is a deep brown moth, measuring 8-9 mm across the spread wings.</p><p>There are blackish Spots on the fore wings, and the margins of the hind wings are deeply fringed. • Life-cycle. The females lay whitish, flat eggs singly on the underside of the young, new shoots, flower buds and the young green bolls. The eggs hatch in one week and the caterpillars, on emergence, are white and turn pink as they grow older. Soon after emergence, the larvae enter the flower-buds, the flowers or the bolls. The holes of entry close down, but the larvae continue feeding inside the seed kernels. They become full-grown ( 8-10 mm) in about two weeks and come out of the holes for pupation on the ground, among fallen leaves, debris, etc. Within one week, the moths emerge to start the lifecycle all over again By October-November, 4-6 generations are completed.</p><p> Full-grown larvae of the last generationdo not, however, pupate. Just a few of them reach the ground, but the great majority keep feeding inside the bolls and connecting to produce what are known as the 'double seeds'. The hibernating larvae lie curled in double seeds for many months and after passing the winter, they emerge as moths. The last life-cycle is very long covering 5-10 months, although during the active season, the life cycle is short, taking only 3-4 weeks.</p><p>The pest passes through several broods during its active period. (i) Cultural and mechanical control. The carryover and multiplication of this pest can be appreciably reduced by the following cultural and mechanical control measures:</p><p>1. Pick the seed cotton completely. Partially unpicked locule (burs) should not be left on the plants.</p><p>2. After the last picking, sheep, goats and other animals should be let into the cotton fields to feed on the plant debris and unopened bolls. Goats are most effective as they can browse even on the standing plants. <ref type="bibr">3</ref>. The leftover, unopened and partially picked bolls should be dislodged by beating against the ground or by plucking them. The burs and bolls so collected should be burnt immediately. <ref type="bibr">4</ref>. Cut the cotton sticks 5-6 cm below ground level to prevent their re-growth. <ref type="bibr">5</ref>. Do not keep the cotton sticks in the fields. Stack them in the Village premises. This would reduce the number of focal points from which initial infestation spreads to the fields. 6. Plough the cotton fields deep by the end of February, preferably with a furrowturning plough. 7. Crushing of cotton seed should be completed before sowing of cotton begins in the area and seed left uncrushed should be sun-dried in thin layers for three consecutive days in the middle of April or fumigated to kill the diapausing larvae of the pink bollworm. For fumigation one 3-g aluminium phosphide (Celphos) tablet should be used per cubic meter of space giving an exposure period of 48 hours or 2 tablets per cubic meter of space with an exposure of 24 hours. 8. The seed should be acid-delinted or fumigated before sowing. 9. Replace the cotton seed by seed-cake for feeding the animals. 10. The damage of the pest can be reduced by sowing short-duration varieties and by early termination of last irrigation to the crop.</p><p>• (iii) Chemical control. In case the bollworm damage exceeds 5 per cent, the crop should e Sprayed immediately and thereafter at 10 day interval with any of the following insecticides in 315-375 litres of water per ha. • (a) Organochlorine. Same insecticide should not be sprayed repeatedly to avoid the development of pesticide resistance and appearance of secondary pests. Also, avoid using insecticides of the same group in more than three sprays.</p><p>(ii) Biological control. The releases of Trichogramma spp. @ 1,50,000 parasitized eggs ha at weekly intervals have proved promising for bollworm control. Gray, Sida spp) particularly when cotton or okra is not growing in that locality.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>• (ii) The withering tops of the plants damaged by the spotted bollworm during</head><p>June-July should be removed and destroyed to check the multiplication of the pest in the initial stage. • (iii) Chemical control measures are same as in case of pink bollworm. The economic threshold level is 10 percent incidence in shoots or reproductive parts. • (iv)Trichogramma chilonis and Trichogramma brasilience are the egg parasitoid against spotted boll worm.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">American bollworm, Helicoverpa armigera (Hubner) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)</head><p>Mark of Identification:-The moth is stoutly built and is yellowish brown with a V shaped speck on fore wing. Hind wings are whitish and lighter in color with broad blackish band along outer margin.</p><p>Caterpillar :-greenish with dark broken grey lines along the side of the body (35 cm long). Damage:-Small puncture may be seen on bolls .Larva seen feeding on the bolls by thrusting the head in boll and half body hanging outside. The larvae first feed on the leaves than on the bolls.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle:-</head><p>Moth lays eggs on tender parts of plant They pupate in soil ETL 5 % damage in fruiting bodies or 3-4 male moth / pheromone trap/ week 2-3 times Management:i.</p><p>Avoid mono and continuous cropping ii. Deep summer ploughing iii. Avoid mono cropping by growing 0f less preferred crops likegreengram, blackgram, castor, soyabeanalong with cotton as inter crops, border crop or alternate crop. iv. Remove and destroy crop residue to avoid the carryover of the pest v.</p><p>Avoid the excessive use of nitrogen fertilizers vi. Water management to prevent excessive vegetative growth and larval harborage vii. Monitoring the pest through light and pheromone traps Inundative release of egg parasites Trichogrammaspp @1.5 lac/ha viii. Destroy the larvae by hand collection ix. 10-12 thousand chrysoperla/ Bigha, Apply NPV @ 0.75ml/l of water x.</p><p>Neem insecticide 300 ppm/5.0ml/lit water xi. Spray following Insecticides for control Quinolphos 25 EC -2 ml/lit, Malathion 50 EC -2 ml/lit, Deltamethrin 2.8 EC 1.0 ml/lit, Thiodicarb75 SP -1.75 gm/lit, Ethion 50 EC -3.0 ml/ lit, Indaxocarb 14.5 SC 1 ml/lit, Spinosad 45 SC -.33 ml/lit Alphamethrin 10 EC -0. The tomato fruit borer is cosmopolitan and is serious pest of Peas, tomato, cotton, maize, tobacco, safflower, groundnut, chillies,chickpea, pigeon pea, mungbean, urdbean, lentil soybean and cowpea. The insect has also been found damaging sorghum, okra, maize, berseem, sunflower and wheat also.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Identification:</head><p>The moth is stoutly built and is yellowish brown. The forewings are marked with greyish wavy lines and black spots of varying size on the upper side and a black kidney shaped mark and a round spot on the underside. The hind wings are whitish and lighter in colour with a broad blackish band along the outer margin. The caterpillars when full-grown, are 3.5 cm in length, being greenish with dark broken grey lines along the sides of the body.</p><p> Life-cycle.</p><p>The females lay eggs singly on tender parts of the plants. A single female may lay as many as 741 eggs in 4 days. The eggs are shining greenish yellow and are round.</p><p>They hatch in 2-4 days in April to October and 6 days in February and the young larvae feed on the foliage for some time and later on to the tomato fruit., with their bodies hanging outside. They move from fruit to fruit and are full-fed in 13-19 days and measure 35 mm in the last instar. The full-grown larvae come out of the fruit and pupate in the soil. In the active season, the pupal periodlasts 8-15 days, but in winter the duration is prolonged, particularly in northern India. Some of the pupae remain in a facultative diapause during November April in northern India. There may be as many as 8 overlapping generations in a year.  Campoletis chlorideae Uchida (Ichneumonidae) is a larval parasite of major importance. it may parasitize 50-60 per cent of H. armigera larvae.</p><p>Damage. Although they prefer food plants like gram and red gram, the larvae are polyphagous. They feed on the foliage, when young, and on the seed in later stages, and thus reduce yield. A single larva may destroy some fruit before it reaches maturity. Management.</p><p>i. Timely Transplanting of tomato, i.e. up to mid October or growing early maturing cultivars.</p><p>ii. Use of Helicoverpa-tolerant varieties.</p><p>iii. Mixed intercropping with non-preferred host plants like barley, wheat, mustard and linseed should be preferred over sole crop. iv. Hand picking of the older larvae during early hours of the day is helpful 35 these are less susceptible to insecticides. v. Apply nuclear polyhedrosis virus (NPV) @ 250-500 larval equivalents/ha alone or alongwith half dose of endosulfan 35EC (1.25 litrBS/ ha). Spraying should be carried out in the evening hours. vi. The fruit borer can be managed by spraying the insecticides at the economic threshold level. The recommended insecticides are 250 ml of fenvalerate 20EC or 200 ml of cypermethrin 25EC or 400 ml of deltamethrin 2.8EC in 625 liters of water per ha at the start of pod formation and repeat after two weeks, if necessary Alternatively. Apply fenvalerate 0.4 per cent dust @ 20 kg/ha or Malathion 5 per cent Dust @ 25 kg/ha or endosulfan @ 25 kg/ha. For consuming any part of the raw gram plant observe waiting period of 20 days after application of the insecticide. Wings : White with a pinkish or bluish tinge and have small hairs along the apical and anal margin. Caterpillar: Creamy white when young, but light pink when full grown. Host plant: Solanaceous plants and green pods of pea also.</p><p>Active period: March-April.    Central leaves of cabbage or cauliflower may be riddled and the vegetables rendered unfit for human consumption.</p><p>The pest is most serious when it appears on the early crop in August-September.</p><p>Management:-Remove and destroy all the remnants, stubble, debris, etc. after the harvest of the crop and plough the fields.</p><p>Tomato, when intercropped with cabbage, inhibits or reduces egg laying by diamond-back moth.</p><p>Indian mustard, which attracts 80-90 per cent diamond-back moths for colonisation, can be used as a trap crop. • Life-cycle:</p><p>• These insects are active during the winter and it is not known how they survive the heat of summer.</p><p>During the active period, they lay eggs on leaves of host plants and the caterpillars feed individually, biting holes of varying size according to the stage of their active development. When full-grown, they pupate in the debris lying on the ground. The moths are very active at dusk on flowers in gardens and public parks, where they are seen in hundreds during the spring season. • Management: Same as in case of cabbage caterpillar. The cotton leafhopper is widely distributed in India and is the most destructive pest of American cotton in the north-western regions. Besides cotton, it also feeds on okra, potato brinjal and some wild plants, like hollyhock, kangi buti, etc. Adults are about 3 mm long and greenish yellow during the summer, acquiring a reddish tinge in the winter.</p><note type="other">Larva Adult Damaging symptoms Tobacco Caterpillar Tobacco Caterpillar,</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life cycle.</head><p>The females lay about 15 yellowish eggs on the underside of the leaves, embedding them into the leaf veins. The eggs hatch in 4-11days and give rise to nymphs which are wedge-shaped and are very active. They suck cellsap from the underside of the leaves and pass through six stages of growth in 7-21 days. On transformation into winged adults, they live for 5-7 weeks, feeding constantly on the plant juice. The pest completes seven generations in a year. The damage is caused by both the nymphs and the adults by sucking the sap from the leaves. Insects exude honeydew which attracts sooty mould. Therefore, in severe infestation, the plants not only become weak, but the mould interferes with the normal photosynthesis resulting in poor growth and yield of cotton. B. tabaci is known to transmit number of virus diseases including the cotton leaf curl, the leaf curl disease of tobacco, the vein clearing disease of okra and the leaf curl of sesame.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage. Injury</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Management.</head><p>Grow American cotton varieties which are resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack. In Punjab, recommended varieties are F1861, F1378, F846, LH1556 and hybrid LH144, all of which are moderately resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack.</p><p>3. Red cotton bug, Dysdercus koennigii ( Hemiptera: Pyrrhocoridae) • Host Plant:This insect is minorpest of cotton .Apart from cotton it feeds on okra, maize, pearmillet,etc. The bugs are elongated slender insect crimson red with white bands across the abdomen. The membraneous portion of their fore wings, antennae and scutillum is black. Both adults and their nymphs feed on the cell-sap of cotton, hollyhock, wheat, maize, pearl-millet, clovers etc.</p><p>• Life cycle : This insect is active throughout the year and passes winter in the adult stage. In spring the bugs becomes active and lays, egg on an average , 100-130 eggs in moist soils or in crevices in the ground. The eggs are spherical , bright yellow and are laid in the in cluster or in loose irregular masses of 70-80 eggs each. They hatch in 7-8 days and the young nymphs have flabby abdomens, but as they grow older, they become more slender and develop black markings on the body. There are five nymphal stages and the development is completed in 49-89 days. In summer, the life of an adult is very varaible, but in winter, it may live up to three months .The predacious bugs like Antilochus cocqueberti and Harpactor costalisfeed on nymph and adults.</p><p>Damage : the insect sucks the cell-sap from the leaves and green bolls of cotton. Heavily attacked bolls open badly and the lint is of poorer quality. The seeds produced may also have low germination and less oil. The bugs stain the lint with their excreta or body juice as they are crushed in the ginning factories. The staining of lint by the growth of certainbacteria inside the bolls is also believed to be initiated by these bugs. Management. Any one of the following insecticides can be used in 250 litres of water per ha: 750 ml of formothion 25EC or oxydemeton methyl 25EC, 625 ml of dimethoate 30EC, 100 m1 of imidacloprid 200 SL, 50g of acatamiprid 20SP, 100g of thiamethoxam 25WG. At the time of sowing, smear the cotton seed with imidacloprid 75WS@ 5g/kg seed(Seed treatment).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Pink bollworm, Pectinophora gossypiella (Saunders) (Lepidoptera -Gelechiidae)</head><p>• The pink bollworm is one of the most destructive pests 0f Cotton and is found in America, Africa, Australia and Asia. It is highly destructive in India and Pakistan. • The adult is a deep brown moth, measuring 8-9 mm across the spread wings.</p><p>There are blackish Spots on the fore wings, and the margins of the hind wings are deeply fringed. • Life-cycle. The females lay whitish, flat eggs singly on the underside of the young, new shoots, flower buds and the young green bolls. The eggs hatch in 7days and the caterpillars, on emergence, are white and turn pink as they grow older. Soon after emergence, the larvae enter the flower-buds, the flowers or the bolls. The holes of entry close down, but the larvae continue feeding inside the seed kernels. They become full-grown ( 8-10 mm) in about two weeks and come out of the holes for pupation on the ground, among fallen leaves, debris, etc. Within one week, the moths emerge to start the life-cycle all over again By October-November, 4-6 generations are completed.</p><p> last generation do not, however, pupate. Just a few of them reach the ground, but the great majority keep feeding inside the bolls and connecting to produce what are known as the 'double seeds'. The hibernating larvae lie curled in double seeds for many months and after passing the winter, they emerge as moths.</p><p>The last life-cycle is very long covering 5-10 months, although during the active season, the life cycle is short, taking only 3-4 weeks. The pest passes through several broods during its active period. 3. The leftover, unopened and partially picked bolls should be dislodged by beating against the ground or by plucking them. The burs and bolls so collected should be burnt immediately. 4. Cut the cotton sticks 5-6 cm below ground level to prevent their re-growth. 5. Do not keep the cotton sticks in the fields. Stack them in the Village premises. This would reduce the number of focal points from which initial infestation spreads to the fields. 6. Plough the cotton fields deep by the end of February, preferably with a furrowturning plough.</p><p>7. fumigation of cotton seed should be completed before sowing of cotton begins in the area and seed should be sun-dried in thin layers for three consecutive days in the middle of April or fumigated to kill the diapausing larvae of the pink bollworm. For fumigation one (3-g) aluminium phosphide (Celphos) tablet should be used per cubic meter of space giving an exposure period of 48 hours or 2 tablets per cubic meter of space with an exposure of 24 hours. • (iv) At least 5-6 sprays are required for effective control of bollworms. Same insecticide should not be sprayed repeatedly to avoid the development of pesticide resistance and appearance of secondary pests. Also, avoid using insecticides of the same group in more than three sprays.</p><p>(ii) Biological control. The releases of Trichogramma spp. @ 1,50,000 parasitized eggs ha at weekly intervals have proved promising for bollworm control.  Spray following Insecticides for control Quinolphos 25 EC -2 ml/lit, Malathion 50 EC -2 ml/lit, Deltamethrin 2.8 EC 1.0 ml/lit, Thiodicarb75 SP -1.75 gm/lit, Ethion 50 EC -3.0 ml/ lit, Indaxocarb 14.5 SC 1 ml/lit, Spinosad 45 SC -.33 ml/lit Alphamethrin 10 EC -0.5 ml/ lit, Chlozopyriphos 20EC -5 ml/lit</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Habits of crow</head><p>• It has a habit of community roosting in towns and villages.</p><p>• A crow nest is in the form of a platform made of twigs with a cup like depression in the centre. • The nesting season is from April to June and 4-5 eggs are laid at a time. • Both sexes incubate and look after the young ones.</p><p>• The koel lays her own eggs and throws out crow eggs from the nest.</p><p>• The young ones of the koel are brought up by the crows.</p><p>• The koel acts as a biological parasite on the crow.</p><p>• The house crow is an omnivorous bird and feeds on dead rats kitchen scraps, locusts, termites, the eggs of other birds and ripening grains of maize and fruits.</p><p>• Dead crow hanging in the top of a pole can effectively be used as scare crow. • Destroy eggs and nest during June-August • The maize cobs on plants can be protected by wrapping one or two of the nearby leaves around them • A large wire -gauze case,2X1X1 meters ,having on one side a covering entrance, can be used as a trap for crows. • A piece of chapatti dipped in 0.3 percent methyl parathion placed on top of a roof is good bait.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mark of identification:</head><p>The female is ash to greyish brown above and fulvous ash-white below The male is 15 cm long, darker above , with blackish streaks on the wings and a black patch on the thorat and breast.</p><p>It has prominent white cheeks. Habits. This is most familiar bird in cities and villages alike. It breeds practically all year round and makes nest in the holes in walls or ceilings of houses by using straw, rubbish and feathers. The eggs are greenish white, blotched with brown.Three to five eggs are incubated at a time and several successive broods may be raised. They visit the ripening fields , particularly those of wheat in the spring season and cause much damage both by feeding and causing the grains to shed.</p><p>• Destroy eggs and nests during April-May and September-October. • Bajra seeds soaked in 0.3 percent methyl parathion emulsion and dried, are placed in small cups and hung from the rafters or branches of trees • Spraying the wheat crop when ears are in the milk stage with thiuram (TMTD)0.6 percent, repels the sparrows and protects the crop Blue rock pigeon,columba livia Gmelin (columbiformes; columbidae)</p><p>It is the most familiar bird near churches, temples, historical buildings with minarets, power houses, railway station, grain ware houses, etc. It is salty grey with a glistening metallic green, purple and magenta sheen on the neck and upper breast.</p><p>• The meat of the rock pigeon as well as that of the dove is quite tasty and ,therefore they can killed as game • The strategic places in power house should be protected by installing chicken wire-netting around the weak spots • Destroys eggs and nests • They can also be killed by feeding on poisoned bajra grains.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mark of identification:</head><p>This bird is commonly known as tota,it is grass green and possesses hooked red bil. The male has a black and rose-pink collar, whereas the female is plain. Habits : Their nests consists of natural or dug-out hollows in the trees and they also utilize holes in walls or rockes for this purpose there may be 4-6 pure-white rounded eggs in one clutch. Both male and female incubate and feed the young ones during the breeding seasoni.e. December to April. They gnaw and cut nearripe fruits such as guava, ber, mango, plum, peaches etc.the birds are equally destructive to ripening cobs of maize , juwar and bajara ears and are often seen carrying and flying with ears of wheat. In maize field, they are seen in large flocks and cause tremendous damage to the crop.</p><p>• The control measure include removal of nests and destruction of eggs with fumigation of eggs with aluminum phosphide at the rate of 0.5 g tablets per hole so as to kill the young ones. • Use gulel (slingshot) crackers and make noise to frighten them. • Killing them with shot-guns is very effective but expensive. • Dusting of malathion dust on cobs and head of maize and sunflower.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mark of identification,Habitate and Management</head><p>• Mark of identification: It is a dark brown bird with bright yellow bill,legs and patches around eyes. As it flies, large white patches become visible on the wings. It is about 22CM in length. The bird live in pairs or groups. It is found through out India, Myanmar, and Sri lanka. • Habits: It breeds from April-August, raising two broods in succession. The nests are built in tree-hollows and the hole in walls or celings. 4-5 glossy blue eggs are incubated at a time and both sexes participate in raising the young ones. This bird is carnivorous and feed on insects, earthworms, grasshoppers, fruits grains and kitchen scraps. They are pests and pick up all sorts grains from the threshing floors or from the field. They are seen in ripening maize, and wheat fields feeding on the grains.</p><p>• (1) Destroying the nests checks their multiplication.</p><p>• They can be killed by feeding them chapatti soaked in 1 per cent fenthion emulsion. • They can be killed by using Gulel Common weaver-bird: Plceus philippinus ( Passeriformes: Ploceidae)</p><p>• Mark of identification: It is dark streaked, fulvous brown above and plain white fulvous below. • It is the size of the house sparrow and its colour resembles the female sparrow when it is not in the breeding season. • It is distributed through out India, Pakistan, Myanmar, and srilanka. • Habits: The male built a number of intricately and compactly woven nets, which are retort shaped with a long vertical entrance tube. The nets are made of paddy leaves and grasses and are seen in clusters hanging on Ber or other medium sized tree near ponds or water holes. Mud is used for plastering the egg chamber on the inside. The female lays 2-4 eggs of pure white coloured. The breeding takes place from May-September. • The bird is active in the paddy season. Becasue it provide food and nesting materials. They can cause quite heavy damage particularly to the early ripening crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">House mouse (Mus musculus)</head><p>It is quick, tends to nibble and run rather than stay longer at food source. They can pass through a hole slightly less than 1.25 cm. They live mostly in houses. They produce 6-10 litter per year with 6-10 young ones per litter. They can climb easily and also can swim when necessary. They are distributed all over India and are omnivorous. Total length including tail is 8-22 cm with pointed snout. They are brownish grey above and whitish to light grey on belly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">House rat (Rattus rattus)</head><p>Lives in close association with human beings. Excellent climber and good swimmer. 4-6 litters / year and tail length 31-43 cm with pointed snout. Dark brownish above (dorsal) and dirty white on belly.</p><p>1. Soft furred field rat or grass rat (Millardia meltada) It occurs in irrigated fields but observed in pastures also. It is nocturnal and lives in simple burrows. It breeds through out the year with litter size of 2-10 young ones. It is small and slender. Adult weight is 100 gm. Total length including tail is 19-29 cm, tail length is 9-14 cm either equal or little shorter than head and body, moderately to poorly haired. The tail is dark above and pale below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Indian Mole Rat or Lesser Bandicoot Rat (Bandicota bengalensis)</head><p>It is an excellent swimmer, often living in flooded rice fields and bunds. Also occurs in the wheat crop fields and godowns. It is nocturnal and fossorial. They hoard large amounts of food in its burrows. Breeds commonly twice a year with 8-10 young ones in each litter. Adult weight is 325 gm. Length from nose to tip of tail is 36-48 cm. Tail is18-20 cm; less than or some times equal to length of head and body together, 160-170 rings clearly seen on scaly tail. Ear 2.5 to 2.6 cm in length, thick and opaque. Snout -short, stumpy, pig like. Fur and colour -thick, short and harsh, spines present, dark brown, pale brown or reddish above.</p><p>Soft -furred field rat, Rattus meltada, :Rodentia: Murinae.</p><p>• Its fur is soft and dark brownish greyexcept the belly which is pale grey. • These rats make simple burrows in the field as well as in the bunds.</p><p>• The tail is little shorter in length than the rest of the body.</p><p>• It produces young ones in two breedings season in North india.</p><p>• A female produces 1-4 litters during the breeding seasons. • This rat makes burrow which are smaller and narrower than those of B. bengalensis and T. indica. • There are 1-4 opening s to a burrow and they are always kept open, but a few bits of grasses are kept in front of the openings.</p><p>Indian gerbil, Tatera indica, Rodentia : Gerbillinae</p><p>• It is known as the antelope rat and is found in sandy soil.</p><p>• A poor swimmer, it is light brown or radish from the above and white on the belly. • It lives in the colony and female produces 1-3 liters, in field, there are 5-10 young ones per litter. • Its burrows are in sandy areas under the cover of a thorny bush or some vegetation. • The burrows are deeper and shorter in length than those of the mole rat. • It feeds on seeds in winter , stem, rhizomes and insects in the summer, and in leaves and flowers of plants in the monsoons.</p><p>Indian field mouse, Mus booduga, Rodentia : Murinae.</p><p>• It is found in dry as well as in the wetlands and is a fairly good swimmer. • It is brown from above and whitish or dull grey on the under side.</p><p>• The tail is equal to or shorter than the body and is dark above and pale below. • It makes small burrows without any branches having only one bed chamber. • The field mices live in pairs and produces young ones 6-13 per litter. • It feeds on paddy grains and at times steals from the food chamber of B. bengalensis.</p><p>• Cultural control : Deep ploughing up to 45 cm,reduction of size and trimming of bunds.</p><p>• Weed management, and removal of burrows .</p><p>• Mechanical control : rodent proof containers, plastering structure,traping of rats.</p><p>• Biological control : Snakes, owls, eagles, mangooses, cats checks the rat population.  Insects are also known as hexapoda owing to the presence of six legs. The true insects.</p><p>Mite:An organism whose body is divided into two region (cephalothorex and abdomen), four pairs of legs and sucking mouth parts and they have no antenna and compound eye.</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>1 . 2 .</head><label>12</label><figDesc>Desert locust-( Schistocerca gregaria), Bombay locust-( Patanga succincta Linnaeus), Migratory locust-( Locusta migratoria Linnaeus). Order-Ortoptera , family-Acrididae Rice grasshopper Hieroglyphus banian (Fabricius) and H. nigrorepletus Bolivar , order-Orthoptera: Family;Acrididae 3.White grub-( Holotrichia consanguinea blanch), Order-Coleoptera family-Scarabaeidae 4. Red hairy caterpillar-Amsacta moorei (Lepidoptera: Arctiidae) 5.Termite -Odontotermus obesus and Microtermus obesi , (isoptera : termitidae )</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>4 . 5 .</head><label>45</label><figDesc>To protect wood-work, paint it with solignum. The cupboards, almirahs, shelves, etc. should be sprayed with lindane or chlorpyriphos frequently. The place from where the galleries originate in the house should be either sprinkled over or injected with 0.5 per cent lindane or chlorpyriphos suspension in water. If wooden structures have already been attacked the injection of 0.5 per cent lindane or chlorpyriphos emulsions with a hypodermic needle into the wood and in the cervices is the only remedy. Mounds of termite, if any, in the area should be treated with 0.5 per cent chlorpyriphos or lindane after breaking open the earthen structure, and making holes with an iron bar. The insecticidal emulsion should be used at the rate of 4 liters per m of the mound Melon Fruit-fly, Bactrocera cucurbitae (Coquillett) (Diptera: Tephritidae)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>these are made possible by folding and unfolding the two ends of the elongated body. They bury themselves about 5 mm deep in the soil and pupate. The pupa are barrel-shaped, light brown and they transform themselves into winged adults in 6-9 days in the rainy season and 3-4 weeks in the winter. There are several generations in a year. Pupae are parasitized by Opius fletcheri Silvestri, O. compensatus Silvestri and O. insisus Silv. (Braconidae), Spalangia philippinensis Full. and Pachycepoideus debrius (Pteromalidae), Dirhinus giffardi Silvestri and D.Izonensis Rohw. (Chalcididae)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Apply 7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>0 kg of carbofuran 3G per ha 3-4 cm deep in the soil near the base of the plants just after germination and irrigate or spray 375 g of carbaryl 50 WP in 250 litres of water per ha.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The fly make cavities in the skin of fruit. The maggots feeds on the flesh of the fruit, making galleries toward the center.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>( 4 )</head><label>4</label><figDesc>During leaf fall stage spray the plants with methyl parathion 3.0 ltrs in 1250 ltrs of water per ha,spray oxydemeton methyl 25 EC 3.0 ltrs in 1250 ltrs of water for controlling root forms. Spray the plants with malathion 50 EC 2 ltrs in 1250 ltre of water during summer.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Damage symptoms: • Direct damage: Aphids damage plants by puncturing them and sucking their juices. They damage the young and soft parts of plants, such as new leaves and shoots. Signs of damage are leaves not opening properly and being smaller in size. Severe infestation can cause shoots to wilt and dry out. • Indirect damage: Aphids have wings and can move from plant to plant spreading viral diseases, picked up from infected plants. Aphids secrete a sugary liquid that stimulates black sooty mold growth. It can cover the surface of leaves which affects the way they absorb sunlight.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Damage 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Lesser grain borer: Rhizopertha dominica (Fabr.) (Bostrychidae: Coleoptera)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>, Brown head, Apodus (3 Instars 23-52 days at different tem.).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Damage 3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Red Rust flour beetle: Tribolium castaneum (Herbst); Tribolium confucium (Tenebrionidae: Coleoptera)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Damage 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>grain, flour,Maida and sujji. Active period: April to October Egg: White, translucent, sticky, slender (327-956 eggs) H.P =4-10 days. Grub: Whitish, cream coloured, worm like 6-7 moults ,22-25days. Pupa: pupation in the grain lying in grain or naked p.p.=5-9 days. Adult: Brown in colour, Secondary pest.Nature of damage: Grub: incapable of feeding on sound grain. Flour turn Greyish, mouldy and gives pungent odour, making unfit for human consumption. Larvae are negative phototactic and are found hidden in food. Khapra beetle:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Damage 6 .•</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Pulse beetle: Collosobruchus chinensis (Linn.) (Bruchidae: Coleoptera) These beetles exclusively feed on stored whole pulses like red gram, black gram, green gram, horse gram, cowpea etc.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Callosobruchus chinensis,Coleoptera: Bruchidae Host: Whole pulses Beans and Gram Eggs: Orange cream in colour and turn grayish white, singly, surface of pod or grain TotalEgg=34-113 H.P.= 7-14 days in April. 4-6 days in September and 8-16 days in November. Grub: Creamy white with black mouth parts, curved and fleshy 10-12 Aug-Sept 26-38 days in Nov, . Pupa: Under seed coat , in pupal cell P. P.= 4-28 days. Adult: Brownish grey coloured. Ivory spot on middle of dorsal surface. Adult is harmless A.P.=5-20 days. Pygidum: Elytera dose not cover the abdomen. Nature of damage: Grubs eat the grain by making cavity adult come out by making exit hole. The other species callosobruchus maculates.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head>Damage 2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Angoumois grain moth: Sitotroga cerealella Oliv.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>White eggs, singly or in batches Surface of grain, Store or Field, become Red later, 150 eggs H.P.=4-8 days . Larva: white with yellow head L.P. 21 days. Pupa: Pupate in cocoon inside the grain P.S 9-12 days. Adult: Yellowish Brown (dirty) wing, wins are narrow pointed and completely folded over back in sloping manner. Several generation is completed in a year. Nature of damage: Caterpillar, feed inside the grain and remain in a single grain only. Infestation remain to upper 30 cm depth only. Grain mite: Acarus siro: Acarina: • Grain mite: Acarus siro: Acarina: • Host: Cereals, grain, flour etc. • Adult: Pale straw coloured to dark Redish Brown.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A) Preventive or prophylactic measures B) Curative measures A) Preventive measures i.Hygiene or sanitation a)Threshing floor/ yard should be clean, free from insect infestation and away from the variety of village/granaries. b)Clean the harvesting and threshing machines before their use. c)Trucks, trolleys or bullock carts which are used for transportation of food grains should be made free form insect infestation. a)Storage structures/godowons should be kept clean. Maintenance of hygiene and sanitation in the store. Cracks and crevices and other holes in store house should be properly sealed and plastered. Food grains should be kept in stores which are rat and moisture proof. b)Whitewash the store rooms before storage of food grains. c)Proper stacking of the grain bags should be done with provision of dunnage materials leaving gangways or alleyway of 0.75 -1.0 m all around for aeration, inspection, prevention of moisture seepage and for fumigation and sprayings.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Non-chemical control measures Ecological control measures The infestation of stored grains from insect pests largely depends on the proper management of three factors viz. i)Temperature ii) Moisture content of grain iii)Availability of oxygen All these factors are required for normal rapid development and multiplication of insects. Hence, they have to be properly manipulated through design and construction of storage structures/godwons and storage practices so as to create ecological conditions unfavourable for attack by insects Stored Grain Insect Management Kit Food grains are stored for varying periods to ensure proper and balanced public distribution throughout the year. Among the biotic and abiotic factors which affects grains /seeds in storage, insect plays a major role in the deterioration of grains / seeds causing both qualitative and quantitative losses. Often the presence of insects in store houses are felt only when they are hovering and flying around, by which time enormous loss and population build up of insects might have occurred.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Rattus norvegicus 4 . 1 .</head><label>41</label><figDesc>Common field rat: Rattus meltada Gray • It has rounded earlobes and soft fur. • It is found in irrigated fields, bunds, hedges and grasslands. Brown plant hopper, (Nilaparvata lugens) (Hemiptera: Delphacidae)  The brown plant hopper is the most destructive pest of rice of high-yielding varieties of paddy in India. Both adults and nymphs feed on paddy, sugarcanes and grasses by sucking the cell sap. The brownish adults with brown eyes are 3.5-4.5 mm in length. The nymphs are brownish-black in colour and have greyish-blue eyes.  Life cycle  The females start laying eggs within 3-10 days of their emergence and deposit eggs in masses, by lacerating the parenchymal tissue. The number of eggs per mass varies from 2 to 11 and a female lays, on an average, 121 eggmasses. The eggs are somewhat dark and cylindrical, having two distinct spots. The incubation period ranges between 4 to 8 days. The nymphs, on emergence, start feeding on young leaves and after moulting 5 times, become adults in 2-3 weeks. The total cycle is completed in 18-24 days. Damage: Both the nymphs and adults cause damage by sucking cell sap from the leaves which turn yellow. If the insect attacks during the early stages of growth, the entire plantmay dry up. The population increases very rapidly and the rice fields start drying up in patches known as 'hopperburn'. The loss in yield may range from 10 to 70 per cent. This insect is known to transmit the grassy stunt virus disease of rice. Management: (i) Closer spacing of 15 x 10 cm creates favourable microclimate in field for rapid development of hopper population. Hence, a spacing of 20 x 15 cm should be followed.(ii) Alternate drying and wetting the field during peak infestation, and draining out the standingwater from the field 2-3 times checks the population of the hopper to a large extent. (iii) Three rleases of mirid bug, Cyrtorhinus lividipennis Reuter @100 bugs or 50-75 eggs/square meter at 10 day intervals have been found effective for the control of brown planthopper. (iv) Spray at economic threshold level of 5-10 insects per hill, 100 ml of imidacloprid 200SL, or 2.0 litres of quinalphos 25ECor 2.5 litres of chloropyriphos 20EC or 1.4 litres monocrotophos 36SL in 250 litres of water per ha. Repeat application if hopper population persists beyond a week after application. While spraying, nozzle should be directed at the basal portion of the plants.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Life-cycle : This pest is active from April to October and hibernates from November to March as a full-grown larva in rice stubble. The moths lay about 120-150 eggs on the underside of the leaves in 2-5 clusters of 60-100 eggs each. The eggs are covered with yellowish brown hair of the female tuft. They hatch in 6-7 days and the tiny black-headed caterpillars soon bore into the stem from the growing points downwards. The larva grows in 6 stages and is full fed in 16-27 days. It then constructs an emergence hole which is always located above the water level and pupates inside the attacked plant. Within 9-12 days( pupa), it emerges as a moth. The life cycle is completed in 31-46 days. There are 3 broods in Bengal, 2 in Orissa, 4-5 in Punjab, Andhra Pradesh and Tamil Nadu.  Damage:The larva feeds inside the stem causing drying of the central shoot or 'deadheart' in young plant and drying of the panicle or 'white ear' in older plant. Basmati varieties suffer heavy damage than coarse varieties.  Management: The removal and destruction of stubbles at the time of the first ploughing after harvesting the crop . (2.) Ploughing and flooding the field is also effective in killing the larvae. (3.) Since the eggs of stem borer are laid near the tip of leaf,clipping of tips of seedlings before transplanting can reduce the carryover of eggs to the field. (4.) Inundative releases of Trichogramma japonicum Ashmead @ 150,000 ha. during egg laying period (5.) The fields showing more than 5 per cent deadhearts should be sprayed with 875 ml of triazophos40EC or 2 litres of quinalphos 20AF or 1.4 litres of monocrotophos 36SLor 2.5 litres of chlorpyriphos 2OEC in 250 litres of water per ha. Same chemical should not used repeatedly.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>3 .</head><label>3</label><figDesc>Rice hispa, Dicladispa armigera, Coleoptera : Chrysomelidae  Rice hispa is distributed throughout India but often serious on young rice crop. The adult is a small bluish black beetle measuring 5 mm in length and is recognized by numerous short spines on the body. The legless, creamy-white larvae are not easily seen, because they are concealed inside the leaf tissue.  Life-cycle: The eggs are embedded in the leaf tissue towards the tip H. P.(3-5 Days). On hatching, the young grubs feed as leaf-miners, between the upper and lower epidermis ( grub period 15 days). The attacked leaves turn membranous, showing characteristic blisters or blotches. Later on, the attacked leaves wither and die. When the larvae are full-grown, they pupate inside(Pupal Period 3-5 days) and finally emerge as black beetles. The insect passes through about six generations in a year.  Damage: Apart from the damage caused by larvae as leafminers, the adults also feed on green matter and produce parallel whitish streaks on the leaves. The damage starts in nurseries and spreads to the rice fields. The infestation varies from 6 to 65 per cent.  Management i. The pest is suppressed if the infested leaf tips are clipped off and destroyed, while transplanting. ii. If the nursery beds are flooded, the beetles float and can be swept together with brooms and then destroyed. iii. Spray at economic threshold level (1 adult or1-2 damaged leaves per hill) with 300 ml of methyl parathion 50 EC or 625 ml of fenitrothion 50EC or chlorpyriphos 20EC or 2.5 litres of lindane 20EC in 250 litres of waterper ha. If the attack continues, repeat spray after two weeks.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_22"><head>• 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Plaster the cracks, crevices, holes and floors with cement • Dunnage leaving gangway or alleyway -0.75 to 1 m all around • Use rat and moisture proof storage structures • Disinfection of storage structure -Malathion 50 EC@ 3lit -100 m B. Curative methods I. Ecological methods • Temperature above 42 0 C and below 15 0 C -retards reproduction and development • Moisture content below 10 % • Dry the storage bags, bins etc., -sun light -kill the pests biostages • Reduce oxygen content -1% -increase the CO2 -the stages of insects II.Physical methods •Super heating system by infrared heaters -flour mills and food processing plants -55 -600 C -10 to 20 min -insect 's die •Modification of storage atmosphere •low oxygen (2.4%) and high carbon dioxide (9.0-9.5)adding CO2 -control the insects Seed purpose •Activated kaolin 1 kg or malathion 5 % D 250gm/ 100 kg of seeds Grain purpose •Activated kaolin 1 kg/100 kg of grain Pulse grain: Activated kaolin 1 kg/100 kg of grains or edible oil 1 kg / 100 kg of grain or Neem seed kernel 1 kg/100 kg of grain •Do not mix synthetic pyrethroids III.Cultural methods • Store the food grains in airtight containers • Split and store pulse grains -pulse beetle IV.Mechanical methods • Sieve and remove all broken grains • Stitch all torn out bags VI.Chemical methods •Treat the walls, dunnage materials and ceilings -malathion 50 EC 10 ml / lit or DDVP 76 WSC 7 ml / lit @ 3 lit spray fluid / 10 sq.m •Alleyways and gangways -malathion 50 EC 10 ml / lit or DDVP 76 WSC 7 ml / lit ( 1 lit of spray fluid/ 270M3 ) •Malathion 50 EC 10 ml / lit @ 3 lit of spray fluid / 100M2 over the bags •Do not spray insecticides directly on food grains •Knock down chemicals -lindane or pyrethrum -kill the flying insects• Seed protectants-Carbary ldust or pyrethrum dust • Shed fumigation -intensity of infestation • EDB ampoules @ 3 ml/ quintal-wheat and pulses ; 5 ml / quintal -rice and paddy • Do not recommend EDB -oil seeds and moist grains • Large scale storage-EDCT @ 30 -40 lit / 100 cubic meter • Small scale storage -EDCT @ 55 ml / quintal, Aluminium phosphide(ALP) @ 1-2 tablets / tonne-food grains lotCover fumigation • 1 tablets of ALP 3 g/ tonne of grains  Shed fumigation 21 tablets of ALP 3g/28 cubic meters ( exposer period :5 days) Sorghum shoot fly (Atherigona soccata)(Diptera : Muscidae)  The sorghum shoot fly, also known as the sorghum stem fly, is a widely distributed pest in Europe, Africa and Asia. In India, it is more serious in southern parts.Besides sorghum, it infests maize, wheat, broom corn, small millets (Panicum spp.) and grasses.  Life-cycle: The female fly lays approximately 40 eggs singly on the underside of the leaves during its life span of about one month. The eggs hatch in 1-2days and the tiny maggots creep out and reach in between the sheath and the axis, and bore into the stem.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_23"><head>1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Mask) viii. Leaf hopper, Pyrilla perpusilla ( Hemiptera : Lophopidae) Early shoot borer , Chilo infescatellus, Lepidoptera,Pyralidae Host Plant: Sugarcane, Maize, Bajara, Sarkanda,Baru and other grasses. Identification: caterpillar is 20-25 mm in length and dirty white in colour and have five light-violet longitudinal stripes on the body . Adult moth is straw colour fore wings and witish hind wing Life cycle:Moth lay eggs in the clusters of 11-36 eggs on the under surface of the leaves by the side of the mid rib. The eggs are creamy-white in colourand has scale like appearance. The larvae are dull white in colour with a number of brownish-red longitudinal stripes on the back and they bore a number of times, either in the same stalkor in the neighboring ones.Moth lays 300-400eggs on lower surface of leaves. Which hatch in 4-5 days. The larval period lasts for about 3-4 (21-28 days) weeks, the pupal period is 6-7 days</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_24"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A female lays up to 980 eggs in its life time. The eggs hatch in 4-7 days during summer and 10-14 days during winter. The larvae remain hidden in soil during the daytime and feed at night on young shoots or underground tubers. They are full grown in 4-7 weeks and then make earthen cells in the soil for pupation. The pupal stage lasts 12-15 days but during winter it extends up to 5 weeks. The life cycle is completed in 7 -11 weeks and there are generally two generations in a year.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_25"><head>2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>at many locations in India. Three rounds of manual removal (clipping) of aphid infested twigs at 15 day intervals starting with the first appearance of the post has been found effective if cheap labour is available. Menochilus sexmaculatus is a preadator of this aphid.Apply any one of the following insecticides when the population of the pest reaches 50-60 aphids per 10 cm terminal portion of the central shoot or when an average 0.5-1 cm terminal portion of central shoot is covered by aphids or when plants infested by aphids reach 40-50 per cent: (i) Foliar sprays. 625-1000ml of oxydemeton methyl 25EC, dimethonte 30EC, quinalphos 25EC, formathion 25EC, malathion 50EC; 940-1500 ml of chlorpyriphos 20EC in 200-315 litres of water per ha depending on the stage of the crop. (ii) Granular insecticides. 10 kg of phorate 10G, Mustard sawfly, Athalia Iugens (Klug) (Hymenoptera: Tenthredinidae) Host Plant: lt feeds on various cruciferous plants like mustard, toria, rapeseed, cabbage, cauliflower, knol-khol, turnip, radish, etc. Mark of Identification:The larvae are dark green and have 8 pairs of abdominal prolegs. A full-grown larva measures 16-18 mm in length. The adults are small orange yellow insects with black markings on the body and have smoky wings with black veins.  Life-cycle: The adults lay 30-35 eggs singly,in slits made with saw like ovipositors along the underside of the leaf margins. The eggs hatch in 4-8 days and the larvae feed exposed in groups of 3-6 on the leaves during morning and evening. They pass through seven stages and are full-grown in 16-35 days. The full-fed larvae descend the plant and enter the soil to a depth of 25-30 mm.  There, they pupate in water proof oval cocoons made of silk and emerge from them as adults in 11-31 days. Thus, the life-cycle is completed in 31-34 days. The pest completes 2-3 generations from October to March.  Damage. It is a serious pest of all crucifers at the seedling stage. The grubs alone are destructive. They bite holes into leaves preferring the young growth and skeletonize the leaves completely. The older plants, when attacked, do not bear seed.  Management. Clean cultivation and quick threshing of harvested crop helps in lowering the incidence of the pest. Spray one litre of malathion 50EC or or quinalphos 25EC in 150-200 litres of water per ha once in October and again in March-April.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_26"><head>4 .</head><label>4</label><figDesc>Groundnut aphid, Aphis craccivora Koch (Hemiptera: Aphididae) This is one of the most serious pests of groundnut. It also attacks peas, beans, pulses, safflower and some weeds. Mark of identification  Nymphs are brownish and The winged adults are soft-bodied insects with black wings and they reach the freshly germinated groundnut plants after overwintering on collateral host plants.  Life cycle. Even without fertilization the females may produce 8-20 young ones in a life span of 10-12 days.The young nymphs are brownish and they pass through four moults to become adults in 5-8 days. The apterous females start producing brood within 24 hours of attaining that stage. Breeding occurs almost throughout the year and both alatae and apterae are present.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_27"><head>about 1</head><label>1</label><figDesc>mm in length, is fairly large and also has on its surface a few ridges and furrows which radiate from the circular depression at the apex. The larva emerges by cutting a hole in the egg-shell in 2-5 days and devours it immediately. The larva feeds and moults 4-5 times and becomes full-grown in 15-20 days  The grown-up larva prepares a loose cocoon of coarse silk and some soil particles, and pupates under the fallen leaves on the soil, usually at the edge of the field. In some cases, pupation also takes place within the folded leaves on the plant itself. The pupal stage lasts 10-15 days and the moths, on emergence, feed on the soft fruits of citrus, mango, etc. There are 5-6 generations in a year. Damage.The caterpillars feed voraciously on castor leaves, starting from the edges inwards and leaving behind only the midribs and the stalks. With the excessive loss of foliage, the Seed yield is reduced considerably. Management.Apply 1.5 litres of monocrotophos or 1000 ml of quinalphos 25EC In 625 litres of water per ha.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_28"><head>( 2 )</head><label>2</label><figDesc>Apply 1.5 litres of monocrotophos or 1000 ml of quinalphos 25EC In 625 litres of water per ha. SESAME (Sesamum indicum L.; Family : Pedialiaceae) 8.Til leaf and pod caterpillar: Antigastra catalaunalis (Duponchel) (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_29"><head>7 . 1 .</head><label>71</label><figDesc>MEALYBUG,Phenacocus solenopsis Tinsley (Cotton mealy bug, Hemiptera: Pseudococcidae 8. Red cotton bug, Dysdercus koennigii ( Hemiptera: Pyrrhocoridae) 9.Dusky cotton bug, Oxycarenus laetus Hemiptera : Lygaedae 10.Cotton leaf roller, Sylepta derogate, Lepidoptera : Pyrallidae 11.Bud moth,Phycitia infusella, Lepidoptera : Pyrallidae 12.Cotton semi looper, Tarache notabilis, Lepidoptera : Noctuidae 13.Green semi-looper, Anomis flava, Lepidoptera : Noctuidae 14.Cotton grey weevil, Myllocerus undecimpustulatus, Coleoptera : Curculionidae 15.Cotton stem weevil, Pempherulus affinis, Coleoptera : Curculionidae Cotton leafhopper(Jassid),Amrasca biguttula biguttula (lshida) (Hemiptera Cicadellidae)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_30"><head></head><label></label><figDesc> Damage. There is excessive shedding of the fruiting bodies. The attacked squares, buds, flowers (called rosetted flowers) and young bolls fall off prematurely and those which do mature do not open properly. The damaged seed-cotton is difficult to pick, discoloured and gives a lower ginning percentage, lower oil extraction and inferior spinning quality. The infestation ranges from 40 to 85 per cent. Management.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_31"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2. 5 litres of endosulfan 35EC. (b) Organophosphates. 2. 0 litres of fenitrothion 50EC, 2.0 litres of quinalphos 25EC, 1. 25 litres of monocrotophos 36SL, 1.0 liters of phenthoate 50EC, 5.0 litres of chlorpyriphos 20EC, 2. 0 litres of quinalphos 25EC,1.25liters of quinalphos 20EC 1.25 litres of fenitrothion 82.5EC, 1.5 litres of triazophos 40EC, 2.0 litres of ethion 50EC, 2.0 kg of acephate 75SP, 1.25 litres of profenophos 50EC. (c) Carbamctes 2.5 kg of carbaryl 50WP, 3.125 kg of carbaryl 40LV, 1. 5 kg of carbaryl 58, 3.0 litres of carbaryl 42F (d) Synthetic pyrethroids. 500 ml of cypermethrin 10EC, 200 ml of cypermethrin 25EC 400 ml of deltamethrin 2.8EC, 275 ml of deltamethrin 4EC, 250 ml of fenvalerate 20EC 300 ml of Fluvalinate 25EC, 250 ml of alphamethrin I0EC or asymethrin 5EC. (e) 150 ml of spinosad 48 SC. • (iv) At least 5-6 sprays are required for effective control of bollworms.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_32"><head>6 .•</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Spotted bollworms, Earias insulana (Boisduval) and E. Vittella (Fabricius) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) These two species of bollworms are widely distributed in North Africa, India, Pakistan and other countries and are serious pests of cotton. The full-grown dull-green caterpillars are 20 mm long having tiny stout bristles and a series of longitudinal black spots on the body. The moths are yellow green and measure about 25 mm across the wings. E. vittella moths are of the same size and have a narrow light longitudinal green band in the middle of the forewing. • Life cycle. The female moths lay 200-400 eggs at night, singly on flower buds, brackets and tender leaves of okra or cotton plants. The eggs hatch in 3-4 days and the caterpillars passthrough 6 stages, becoming fullgrown in 10-16 days. They pupate either on the plants or on the ground (during November December) among fallen leaves and the moths emerge in 8-14 daysin summer and 18-23 days in winter. The life cycle is completed (usually August to October) in 17-29days. Several overlapping generations are completed in a year. • Damage. When cotton plants are young, the larvae bore into the terminal portions of the shoots, which wither away and dry up. Later on, they cause shedding of the fruiting bodies. The green bolls attacked by spotted bollworm are often infected by fungi which causes bolls to rot and dry up without opening. The infested bolls called aborted bolls open prematurely and produce poor lint, resulting in lower market value. • Management. • (i) The pest can be suppressed with clean cultivation and the destruction of alternative food plants (Abutilon indicum Sweet, Malvastrum tricuspidatum A.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_33"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>5 ml/ lit, Chlozopyriphos 20EC -5 ml/lit Helicoverpa armigera (Hubner) (Lepldoptera: Noctuidae)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_34"><head>1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Brinjal fruit and shootBorer :Leucinodes orbonalis (lepdoptera : Pyralidae) Appearance: Moth , white but has pale brown or black spot on the dorsum of the thorax and abdomen (20-22mm).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_35"><head>Damage: 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The maggots bore into the stem thereby causing withering and ultimate drying of the affected shoots, thus reducing the bearing capacity of the host plants.The adults also cause damage by puncturing the leaves, and the injured parts turn yellow. The damage is more severe on seedlings than on the grown up plants. Management: Avoid sowing of the crop earlier than mid-October to check the attack of the pest.Sow the crop in the second fortnight of October to escape the damage of the pest.Remove and destroy all the affected branches during the initial stages of attack.Apply 7.5 kg of phorate 10G or 25 kg of carbofuran 3 G per ha in furrows at the time of sowing.On the crop, spray three times 750 ml of oxydemeton methyl 25EC in 250 litres of water per ha. The first application should be just after germination and the other two at an interval of 2 weeks each. Onion Thrips, Thrips tabaci Lindeman (Thysanoptera: Thripidae) Onion thrips is world-wide and is found throughout India as a major pest of onion and garlic. Other Hosts: Cotton, cabbage, cauliflower, potato, tobacco, tomato, cucumber etc.Onion Thripsbrown and measure about 1 mm in length. The males are wingless whereas the females have long, narrow strap-like wings, which are furnished with long hair along the hind margins. Nymph: The nymphs resemble the adults but are wingless and slightly smaller. They move briskly on the flowers and leaves of onion and garlic plants. Life-cycle: This pest is active throughout the year and breeds on onion and garlic from November to May when it migrates to cotton and other summer host plants and breeds there till September. In October, it is found on cabbage and cauliflower. The adult female lives for 2-4 weeks and lays 50-60 kidney-shaped eggs singly in slits which are made in leaf tissue with its sharp ovipositors. It reproduces parthenogenetically. The eggs hatch in 4-9 days and the nymphs start feeding on plant juices by lacerating the leaf tissues. On onion and garlic, they are usually congregated at the base of a leaf or in the flower. On cotton, cabbage and cauliflower, they generally feed on the lower surface of leaves. The nymphs pass through four stages and are full-fed in 4-6 days, after which they descend to the ground and pupate at a depth of about 25 mm. The 8-9 G  Damage: Damage is done by adults as well as by nymph by congregate at the base of leaf or in the flower. The nymph and adult lacerate and suck the sap from the leaves. The puncture produces silvery white blotches leading to distortion, wilting, curling, wrinkling and drying of leaves from tip downward. The seedling show retard growth. The bulb remain undersized and appear distorted in shape. In Hawaii, T. tabaci is known to act as a vector of streak -virus disease of peas and yellow-spot of pineapple.  Management:  Grow resistant varieties sweet Spanish, white Persian and Grano.  Use neem coated urea which reduces the infestation of pest. Set up sky blue sticky traps which attracts more adult than yellow colour traps Spray 625 ml of Malathion 50 EC in 250 litres of water per ha as soon as the pest appears. A waiting period of 7 days should be observed before harvest. Chilli thrips: Scirtothrip dorsalis Thripidae: Thysanoptera • Host Plant: Chilli, Citrus, corn, cotton, eggplant, melon, rose, tobacco, tomato. • Mark of Identification: Small size, yellow coloration, dark antennae and dark striping on the lower abdomen. • Biology: The insect reproduce sexually as well as parthenogenetically. The female thrips insert eggs into the veins of leave and a female may lay 40-80 eggs. The female lay kidney shaped egg. Egg will hatch in 2-7 days. There will be two nymphal stage. The nymph feed for 8-10 days before entering into pupal stage that lasts for 2-3 days. The life cycle is completed in 10-20days. • Damage: The nymph and adult infest tender leaves and feed on the sap causing curling of leaves which may leads to stunting of the crop. Buds and flower are damaged. The yield loss may range to 25-50%. Chilli thrip is a vector of chilli leaf curl virus,tobacco streak virus.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_36"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Adult: The butterflies are pale white and have a smoky shade on the dorsal side of the body. The wings are pale white, with a black patch on the apical angle of each fore wing and a black spot on the costal margin of each hind wing. The females measure 6.5 cm across the spread wings and have two conspicuous black circular dots on the dorsal side of each fore wing. Males are smaller than the females and have black spots on the underside of each fore wing. Life-cycle: This pest apper in October and remains active up to the end of April. The female lay, on an average, 164 yellowish conical eggs in clusters of 50-90 on the upper or the lower side of a leaf. The eggs hatch in 11-17 days in November-February and 3-7 days in March-May. The caterpillars feed gregariously during the early instars and disperse as they approach maturity. They pass through five stages and are full-fed in (larval period) 15-22 days during March-April and 30-40 days during November-February. The larvae pupate in barns or on trees. The pupal stage lasts 7.7-l4.4 days in March-April and 20-28 days in November-February. The butterflies live for 25-125 days and the pest breeds four times during October-April. The larvae of this insect are parasitized by Apanteles glomeratus (Braconidae) in the natural populations.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_37"><head>••</head><label></label><figDesc>The caterpillars alone cause damage. The first instar caterpillars just scrape the leaf surface, whereas the subsequent instars eat up leaves from the margins inwards, leaving intact the main veins. Often, entire plants are eaten up. Management:-Hand picking and mechanical destruction of caterpillars during early stage of attack can reduce infestation. Spray one litre of Malathion 5OEC or 925 ml of quinalphos 25EC in 250 litres of water per ha. Repeat spraying at 10 day interval s if necessary. Do not spray the crop at least one week before the harvest. Yellowish eggs of the size of pin heads are laid singly or in batches of 2-40 on the underside of leaves. A female may lay 18-356 eggs in her life-time. The eggs hatch in 3-6 days. The newly hatched caterpillars bore into the tissue from the underside of leaves and feed in these tunnels. At first, their presence is detected only from the blackish excreta The larvae are very sensitive to touch, wind or other physical disturbances and readily feign death. They become full-grown in 14-21days. Before pupating, the larva constructs a barrel-shaped silken cocoon which is open at both ends and is attached to the leaf surface. The pupa stage lasts 4-5 days and the moths may live for as long as 20 days. The life-cycle is completed in 15-18 days during September-October and there are several generations in a year.Apanteles plutellae (Kurdyumov) effectively checks the population of diamondback moth on cabbage in Gujarat and Karnataka under favourable environmental conditions.Damage:-Damage is caused by the caterpillars which, in the earlier stages, feed in mines on are lower side of cabbage leaves and, in the later stages, feed exposed on the leaves. Caterpillars damage the leaves of cauliflower, cabbage and rape-seed particularly in the heart of the first two.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_38"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Spray 625 ml of diazinon 20EC or 1.0 litre or quinalphos 35EC or trichlorphon 50EC or 250 ml of fenvalerate 20EC in 250 litres of water per ha. Repeat sprays at one week intervals. Hosts : This is polyphagous pest.: Cabbage, cauliflower and other winter vegetables, groundnut and sunflower are the host plant. • Marks of identification: • Larva:The caterpillars are plump and palish green. They cause damage by biting round holes into cabbage leaves. On walking, they form characteristic half-loops and are often seen mixed with cabbage caterpillars. • Adult:The adults of T. orichalcea are light palish brown with a large golden patch on fore wing. They measure about 42 mm across the spread wings. The adults of A. nigrisigna arc darker and have dark brown and dirty-white patches on the fore wings.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_39"><head>2 .</head><label>2</label><figDesc>to plants is caused both by the nymphs and the adults which suck sap from the foliage and probably also due to the injection of toxins into the plant tissues. The attacked leaves turn pale and then rust-red. With change in appearance, the leaves also turn downwards, dry up and fall to the ground. Owing to the loss of plant vitality, the cotton bolls also drop off, causing upto 35 per cent reduction in yield. Management. Grow American cotton varieties which are resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack. In Punjab, recommended varieties are F1861, F1378, F846, LH1556 and hybrid LH144, all of which are moderately resistant or tolerant to leafhopper attack. Spray against leafhopper should be done only at economic threshold level of 1-2 nymphs per leaf or when second grade injury symptoms (yellowing and curling at margins of leaves) appear in 50 per cent of the plants. Any one of the following insecticides can be used in 250 litres of water per ha: 750 ml of formothion 25EC or oxydemeton methyl 25EC, 625 ml of dimethoate 30EC, 100 m1 of imidacloprid 200 SL, 50g of acatamiprid 20SP, 100g of thiamethoxam 25WG. At the time of sowing, smear the cotton seed with imidacloprid 75WS@ 5g/kg seed. Cotton whitefly, Bemisia tabaci (Gennadius) (Hemiptera : Aleyrodidae)  Host Plant: Apart from cotton, this insect also feeds on various other plants such as cabbage, cauliflower, sarson, toria, melon, potato, brinjal, okra and some weeds.  In the winged stage, they are 1.0-1.5 mmlong and their yellowish bodies are slightly dusted with a white waxy powder.They have two pairs of pure white wings and have prominent long hind wings.  Life-cycle : Females lay stalked eggs singly on the underside of the leaves, averaging 119 eggs per female. The eggs hatch in 3-5 days during summer, 5-33 days in winter. The nymphs feed on cell-sap and grow into three stages to form the pupae within 9-14 days in summer and in 17-81 days in winter. In 2-8 days, the pupae change into whiteflies. The total life-cycle is completed in 14-Damage.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_40"><head> 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Damage. There is excessive shedding of the fruiting bodies. The attacked squares, buds, flowers (called rosetted flowers) and young bolls fall off prematurely and those which do mature do not open properly. The damaged seed-cotton is difficult to pick, discoloured and gives a lower ginning percentage, lower oil extraction and inferior spinning quality. The infestation ranges from 40 to 85 per cent. Management. (i) Cultural and mechanical control. The carryover and multiplication of this pest can be appreciably reduced by the following cultural and mechanical control measures: Pick the seed cotton completely. Partially unpicked locule (burs) should not be left on the plants. 2. After the last picking, sheep, goats and other animals should be let into the cotton fields to feed on the plant debris and unopened bolls. Goats are most effective as they can browse even on the standing plants.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_41"><head>6 .•</head><label>6</label><figDesc>Spotted bollworms, Earias insulana (Boisduval) and E. Vittella (Fabricius) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) Mark of identification. The full-grown dull-green caterpillars are 20 mm long having tiny stout bristles and a series of longitudinal black spots on the body. The moths are yellow green and measure about 25 mm across the wings. E. vittella moths are of the same size and have a narrow light longitudinal green band in the middle of the forewing. • Life cycle. The female moths lay 200-400 eggs at night, singly on flower buds, brackets and tender leaves of okra or cotton plants. The eggs hatch in 3-4 days and the caterpillars passthrough 6 stages, becoming full-grown in 10-16 days. They pupate either on the plants or on the ground (during November December) among fallen leaves and the moths emerge in 8-14 daysin summer and 18-23 days in winter. The life cycle is completed (usually August to October) in 17-29days. Several overlapping generations are completed in a year. • Damage. When cotton plants are young, the larvae bore into the terminal portions of the shoots, which wither away and dry up. Later on, they cause shedding of the fruiting bodies. The green bolls attacked by spotted bollworm are often infected by fungi which causes bolls to rot and dry up without opening. The infested bolls called aborted bolls open prematurely and produce poor lint, resulting in lower market value.• Management.• (i) The pest can be suppressed with clean cultivation and the destruction of alternative food plants (Abutilon indicum Sweet, Malvastrum tricuspidatum A. Gray, Sida spp) particularly when cotton or okra is not growing in that locality. • (ii) The withering tops of the plants damaged by the spotted bollworm during June-July should be removed and destroyed to check the multiplication of the pest in the initial stage.• (iii) Chemical control measures are same as in case of pink bollworm. The economic threshold level is 10 percent incidence in shoots or reproductive parts. • (iv)Trichogramma chilonis and Trichogramma brasilience are the egg parasitoid against spotted boll worm.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_42"><head>7 .</head><label>7</label><figDesc>American bollworm, Helicoverpa armigera (Hubner) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) Host plant: Poly phagous pest and feeds on Cotton, Chickpea, Pigeon pea, Mungbean, Urdbean, Lentil, Soyabean and Cowpea. Mark of Identification:-The moth is stoutly built and is yellowish brown with a V shaped speck on fore wing. Hind wings are whitish and lighter in color with broad blackish band along outer margin. Caterpillar :-Greenish with dark broken grey lines along the side of the body (35 cm long). Damage:-Small puncture may be seen on bolls .Larva seen feeding on the bolls by thrusting the head in boll and half body hanging outside. The larvae first feed on the leaves than on the bolls. Life cycle:-Moth lays eggs on tender parts of plant. Hatching period. 2-4 days in April-October and 6 days in February. caterpillar period. 13-19 days Pupal period. 8-15 days. They pupate in soil Generation: 8 over lapping. ETL 5 % damage in fruiting bodies or 3-4 male moth / pheromone trap/ week 2mono cropping by growing 0f less preferred crops like greengram, blackgram, castor, soyabeanalong with cotton as inter crops, border crop or alternate crop. iv. Remove and destroy crop residue to avoid the carryover of the pest v. Avoid the excessive use of nitrogen fertilizers vi. Water management to prevent excessive vegetative growth and larval harborage vii. Monitoring the pest through light and pheromone traps Inundative release of egg parasites Trichogrammaspp @1.5 lac/ha, Campoletis chlorideae is a larval parasite of H. armigera viii. Destroy the larvae by hand collection ix. 10-12 thousand chrysoperla/ Bigha, Apply NPV @ 0.75ml/l of water x. Neem insecticide 300 ppm/5.0ml/lit water xi.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_43"><head>Entomology:</head><label></label><figDesc>The term entomology has been derived from the Greek words, entomon= insect and logos = knowledge.Itis the branch of zoology that deals with insects only under class insecta of the phylum arthropoda. Agricultural entomology : This mainly concerns with the study of insects which are directly related with the crops and stored commodities. Applied entomology : The application of pure entomology to the control of insect pests. Insect: Insect are those tracheae arthropod in which the body is devided in to three region head , thorax and abdomen with three pair of legs and development through metamorphosis is known as insect. The world insect is derived fromLatin world ( Insectum=having cut into).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="29,533.99,101.65,277.46,183.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="39,137.99,239.98,665.52,215.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="44,39.18,83.96,278.82,197.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="44,36.00,317.96,281.96,209.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="44,348.01,82.09,292.90,215.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="44,348.04,316.21,292.90,211.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="45,22.42,219.52,365.98,273.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="45,389.99,17.97,323.97,227.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="45,389.99,257.98,323.97,275.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="50,11.99,228.39,371.96,281.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="50,407.99,228.39,263.96,281.57" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="50,407.99,17.97,263.96,191.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="60,18.00,78.35,291.60,233.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="60,348.01,78.35,341.97,233.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="60,338.46,325.16,353.96,208.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="68,360.00,292.08,293.33,176.60" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="72,18.00,95.98,665.58,401.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="76,36.00,293.98,301.64,200.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="76,353.99,293.98,351.07,200.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="76,357.93,53.97,323.97,206.14" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="81,371.99,131.98,440.99,371.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="86,162.00,197.97,632.98,257.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="86,479.99,5.98,311.24,179.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="94,117.01,103.47,470.13,312.15" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="145,102.39,83.96,515.23,371.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="146,99.64,71.97,520.72,395.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="147,119.99,65.96,462.59,419.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="148,137.99,37.22,443.96,465.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="150,21.63,89.97,676.72,359.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="156,288.00,215.97,343.47,231.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="157,155.99,311.98,283.47,202.59" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="157,510.01,65.96,307.47,190.46" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="157,497.99,317.96,307.47,203.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="159,270.00,161.97,355.61,290.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="160,263.99,137.96,397.59,264.73" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="161,258.01,227.96,416.61,269.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="163,162.00,197.97,275.98,269.35" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="163,510.01,101.96,269.97,199.11" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="163,492.01,317.96,311.98,200.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="175,330.01,275.98,347.98,247.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="176,486.26,282.76,353.74,257.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="176,128.47,133.88,347.24,252.68" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="177,222.01,65.96,241.48,437.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="177,492.01,65.96,292.59,437.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="178,155.99,107.97,431.35,287.24" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="178,612.00,111.29,197.24,294.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="179,132.01,113.98,302.97,302.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="179,492.01,89.97,280.60,186.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="179,486.00,311.98,307.47,173.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="180,162.48,111.20,317.23,335.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="180,494.45,167.93,307.47,204.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="207,18.00,180.71,665.97,335.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="215,72.00,-0.03,563.98,245.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="218,150.01,11.96,473.98,245.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="220,35.01,35.97,649.98,467.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="224,44.22,107.97,566.53,365.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="279,162.00,180.68,618.89,299.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="284,150.01,263.96,626.97,221.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="284,522.00,35.97,275.98,206.99" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="295,450.00,2.92,269.97,197.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="295,450.00,341.97,269.97,197.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="295,180.00,92.41,257.98,227.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="301,229.47,131.98,241.40,215.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="304,42.01,293.98,306.45,205.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="304,384.01,299.96,287.97,191.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="304,371.99,71.97,326.98,187.48" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="327,8.48,143.18,347.24,222.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="327,357.85,287.97,362.13,239.19" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="330,54.00,125.97,389.96,356.34" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="330,468.00,125.97,233.97,356.34" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="334,42.49,107.97,317.23,335.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="334,374.46,107.97,307.47,335.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="337,18.00,125.97,365.98,389.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="337,414.00,125.97,281.96,389.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="340,13.15,142.16,268.81,271.98" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="340,330.01,143.04,279.98,180.91" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="340,330.01,352.97,306.06,168.97" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>• 1.Mango-hopers, Idioscopus clypealis, Amritodus atkinsoni and Idioscopus niveosparus : Hemiptera : cicadellidae. • 2.Mango mealybug, Drosicha mangiferae (Hemiptera) : Margarodidae • 3. Mango stem borer, Batocera rufomaculata (Coleoptera : Cerambycidae) , Batocera rubus (Coleoptera : Cerambycidae)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>4.Mangofruit fly, Bactrocera dorsalis (Diptera : Tephritidae) 5.Mango stone weevil, Sternochetus mangiferae (coleopteran : curculionidae) 6. Mango shoot borer, Chlumetia transversa (Lepidoptera : Noctuidae) 7.Mango gall psyllid Apsylla cistella (hemiptera : psyllidae) 8.Mango bud mite, Acerya mangiferae ( Acarina : Eriophidae) 9.Bark eating caterpillar, Inderbella quadrinotata (Lepidoptera : Meterbelidae) 10.Red tree ant, Oecophylla smaragdina, ( Hymenoptera : formicidae ) 11.Mango scale, Chloropulvinaria psidi, (Hemiptera : Coccidae) 12.Mango leaf mining weevil, Rhynchaenus mangiferae, (coleopteran : Curculionidae) Mango hoppers 1.Mango-hopers, Idioscopus clypealis, Amritodus atkinsoni and Idioscopus niveosparus : Hemiptera : cicadellidae.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>1.25 litres of malathion 50 EC + 12.5 kg gur or sugar in 1250 litres of water</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>per ha and repeat spray at 7-10 days intervals if infestation continues.(6)  After harvest dip the fruit in 5 per cent sodium chloride solution for 60 minutes to kill the eggs, if any and also to decontaminate them of insecticide residue if at all present.Pest of Guava ( Psidium guajava) (Family : Myrtaceae) Guava fruit fly, Bactrocera dorsalis (Diptera : Tephritidae )</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>or hyaline wings and yellow legs. The legless maggots are</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>• Mark of identification : The adult is stout, a little larger than the housefly, is brown or dark brown fly and has transparent yellow and opaque.The other fruit flies damaging mango fruits are Dacus zonatus, D. correctus, D. diversus and D. hageni.Which, though less common than D. dorsalis, cause similar damage. Life cycle : The adult flies emerge in April and start laying eggs under the rind of the ripening fruits and vegetables of the season such as guava,</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>laquat, apricot, plum, brinjal, and later shift to mango. They lays 2-15 eggs at</head><label></label><figDesc>a time in clusters. A female lays on an average, 50 eggs but under favourable conditions, 150 eggs are laid in one monththe eggs</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>hatch in 2-3 days in march april and 1-1.5 days in the summer and 10 days in winter.</head><label></label><figDesc>As the maggot develop they they pass through 3 stages in the ripening pulp and are full grown in 6-</figDesc><table><row><cell>Many G 2-13 w</cell></row></table><note>29 days. They leave the fruit and move away by jumping in little hope. On reacing a suitable place, they burry themselves into the soil and pupate 8-13 cm below the soil surface. In (Pupa)6-44 days, they emerge as flies and reach the ripe fruit for further multiplication. The life cycle is completed in 2-13 weeks and many generations are complicated in a year.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>by maggot and adults. The adults feed on exudation of ripe fruits and honeydew of various insects.</head><label></label><figDesc>The punctures for egg laying made by the females attract</figDesc><table /><note>• Damage. The damage is caused both</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>fermenting microorganisms. The maggot destroy the pulp making it foul smelling</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>and discoloured. The fruit develop brown rotten patches on them and fall to the ground ultimately. The infested fruits become unmarketable and at times almost all of them contain maggots.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Black-headed caterpillar, Opisina arenosella, Lepidoptera : xyloryctidae.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>This is one of the most important pests of coconut palm. The moth is ash</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>grey coloured. It is medium sized, measuring 10-15 mm, with wing expance of 20-25 mm.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>125</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Egg</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>3-5 D</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult</cell><cell>G</cell><cell>Larva 40 D</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pupa</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>12 D</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Life cycle.A female moth lays 125 scale like eggs in small batches on the underside of tip of old leaves. Freshly lays eggs are creamy white and turn pink on completion of embryonic development. The incubation period lasts about 3-5 days in summer and 10 days in winter. The</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>larvaa feedson green matter and simultaneously construct silken galleries in which it feeds and voids frass. When full grown in about 40 days, the larva transformed itself into a brownish pupa inside the gallery. Within about 12 days, a whitish moth emerges and starts the life cycle all over again. The caterpillar is paracitized by</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Apanteles taragammae, Bracon brevicornis,and Elasmus nephantidis. Inundative release of native parasitoids, Goniozus nephantidis and Bracon brevicornis at</head><label></label><figDesc>3000 and 4500 per ha respectively have given encouraging results for management of black head caterpillar.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>• Active period: March to December.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Life cycle: The aphids reproduce parthenogenetically and the progeny thus produced, consists of females only. Each female may produced up to 116 young ones in her life time . There are four nymphal instar and the duration of each varies according to the season. The total duration of nymphal period is 35-42 days in February, 29.5days in August-November, and 10.5-19.5 days in April-july. There may be 13 generations in a year. There is a partial migration from aerial parts to the roots of infested plants ( December)and the reverse migration from the roots to the aerial parts takes place in( May). FEMALE NYMPH 116 NYMPHS NYMPHS 10.5-19.5 D Apr-jul 29.5 D Aug-Nov 35-42 D Feb 13 OVERLAPPING G</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Life cycle:The pest is active from November to April in North India. Nymphal development of non winged is complted in 11- 14 days and of winged forms in14-19 days. The</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>growth is quickest in March. Population starts increasing from November and is highest during March. There is an</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>increase in winged forms from December on wards with peak in March (90% winged).The pest multiplies most rapidly in late spring but can not withstsnd the summer heat and with the increasing in temperature its population declines. • Management: The pest can be controlled by spraying the crop with oxy-demeton methyl (0.025%) or phosphamidon (0.03%) or malathion (0.05%) as soon as the attack is noticed.Natural enemies like coccinellids, syrphids, chrysopids, etc</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>. also take care of these aphids.Avoid application of insecticides when these natural enemies are active.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_21"><head>2.Hollyhock tingid bug, Urentius euonymus (Hemiptera :Tingidae)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>• Hosts: Garden hollyhock, Althcea rosea, Abutilon indicum, Sida cordifolia and Chrozophora rottleri.</cell></row><row><cell>• Mark of Identification: The bugs are about 5-6 mm in length having densely reticulate body and wings . The nymphs are spiny in appearance.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_24"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>In this types of storage structures the grain is generally stored in bulk. This types of storage structures having generally capacities between 1 to 50 tonnes. The storage of grain is generally done in one of the following storage structures in the different rural and urban regions of India in bulk as well as in bag storage.</figDesc><table><row><cell>1.Traditional Storage Structures</cell></row><row><cell>i. Morai type storage structures</cell></row><row><cell>ii. Bukhari type storage structures</cell></row><row><cell>iii. Kothar type storage structure</cell></row><row><cell>iv. Mud Kothi type storage structure</cell></row><row><cell>v. Muda type storage structure</cell></row><row><cell>vi. Kanaj type storage structure • Traditional storage structures vii. Kuthla type storage structure • Improved storage structures viii. Metal/ Steel bin type storage structure • Modern storage structures • Farm Silos ix. Bag type storage structure</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_25"><head>1.1 Shallow bins</head><label></label><figDesc>Squat silos are comes under shallow bins. A squat silo has a wall height to diameter ratio 0.5 or even less. Squat silo can compete with sheds for low-cost quality storage. 1.2 Deep bins Vertical Silos are comes under this type of storage structures. There are two types of vertical silos a) Flat bottom vertical silo and b) Hopper bottom vertical silo. 2 Shed Generally, a horizontal sheds have been used to provide lowcost, large volume storage. For storing grains and other products a very large volume sheds have also been constructed by Central Warehousing Corporation.</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_26"><head>• Symptoms: The only nymphs of whiteflies suck the sap from the under surface of leaves which turn yellow and pinkish in severe cases and gradually dry up. Honey dew=black mould= photosynthesis= poor yield and fodder. Poor quality of gur causes reduced sugar recovery by 25 %. Waterlogging and nitrogen starvation</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>cause severe outbreak of whiteflies.Varieties with broad and long leaves are more susceptible to this pest..Heavy  </note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_27"><head>infested leaves are covered by the sooty mould caused by the fungus, which adversely affects photosynthesis. The whitefly infestation retards cane growth and reduces sugar content. Management:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>July-November:-Use 800ml</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_28"><head>of malathion 50 EC or methyl demeton 25 EC(Metasystox) or 600 ml dimethoate 30 EC for spray in 400 ml water per</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>acre. In this solution use 10 Kg urea for spray due to this leaves become green frequently SUGARCANE Pyrilla (</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_29"><head>Pyrilla purpusilla Walker Hemiptera: Lophopidae) • Host plant: wheat, barlrey, oats, maize, sorghum, baru, guinea grass, swank and sudan grass.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>• Identification:</cell></row><row><cell>• The leaf hopper is very agile,20 mm long and jumps around in large numbers, making a faint noise when a person walks through a heavily infested field. The adult equally active, has a straw</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_30"><head>colored body with dark patches or spots on the wings. At the front end it has a snoutlike prolongation and prominent red eyes. Nymphs are pale yellow, 10-15 mm long and has two white prominent feather like filaments at the tail end of the body.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>• Damage • Pyrilla adults and nymphs both suck the cell sap from the lower side of sugarcane leaves. Due to continuous de-sapping by large number of hoppers top leaves in the affected canes dry up and lateral buds germinate. The hoppers exude a sweet sticky fluid known as honeydew, which promotes quick and luxuriant growth of the fungus and as a result the leaves are completely covered by the sooty mould. This affects photosynthesis activity of the plant and growth of the plant is affected adversely. Affected canes when planted give poor germination and low yield.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_31"><head>Heavy rainfall followed by 75-80% humidity,intermittent drought periods, high temperature (26-30°C) and wind movement favors rapidbuildup of pyrilla</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Life cycle:Eggs:300-536 cluster on the under surface of leaf. Egg cluster are covered with fluffy material. Hatching Period: 8-10 days in summer 3-4 week during winter, Nymph: 8 weeks in summerand 18-20 weeks in winter. Adult: 27-52 days in summer and 18-20 weeks in winter. 3-4 generation in a year.</cell></row></table><note>. Other factors favoring pyrilla buildup are dense and luxuriant crop, excess nitrogen application, water logging, lodging of cane and varieties with broad and succulentleaves.Management:1.Collect and destroy all trashes after harvest.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_33"><head>Painted bug, Bagrada hilaris (Burmeister) (Hemiptera : Pentatomidae) 4.Groundnut aphid, Aphis craccivora Koch (Hemiptera: Aphididae) 5. Soyabeen,Girdle beetle Obereopsis brevis , Coleoptera : Cerambycidae 6.Castor semilooper, Achaea janata (Linnaeus) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae) 7. Castor capsule borer, Conogethes puntiferalis ( Lepidoptera : pyralidae ) 8. Til leaf and pod caterpillar, Antigastra catalaunalis (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae) BRASSICA CROPS (Brassica spp.; Family : Cruciferae) 1. Mustard aphid, Lipaphis erysimi (Kaltenbach) (Hemiptera : Aphididae)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.Mustard aphid, Lipaphis erysimi (Kaltenbach) (Hemiptera : Aphididae) 2.Mustard sawfly, Athalia Iugens (Klug) (Hymenoptera: Tenthredinidae) 3.• The mustard aphid is worldwide and is a serious pest of cruciferous oilseeds like toria,sarson, raya, taramira and Brassica vegetables like cabbage, cauliflower,knol-khol,etc.</cell></row></table><note>• Mark of Identification • The aphids are minute, soft-bodied and light green insects having a pair of short tubes called cornicles on the posterodorsal region of the abdomen. • Life cycle.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_34"><head>pale-yellow eggs singly or in groups of 3-8 on leaves stalks, pods and sometimes on the soil</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note> The full-grown nymphs are about 4 mm long and 2.66 mm broad. Nymph are black with a number of brown markings. The adult bugs are 3.71 mm long and 3.33 mm broad. Adult Bug are sub-ovate, black and have a number of orange or brownish spots. Life-cycle: These bugs lay oval, . A female bug may lay 37-102 eggs in its life-span of 3-4 weeks. The eggs hatch</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_35"><head>in 3-5 days during summer and 20 days during December.</head><label></label><figDesc>The nymphs develop fully in live stages and transform themselves into adults in 16</figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_36"><head>-22 days during the summer and 25- 34 days during the winter</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>. The entire lifecycle is completed in 19-54 day, and it passes through 9 generations in a year.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_37"><head>Female Male adult Caterpillar Pupa DamageSymptoms Cabbage Butterfly: Pieris brassicae, Lepidoptera:Pieridae Cabbage Caterpillar, Pieris brassicae (Linnaeus) (Lepidoptera: Pieridae)</head><label></label><figDesc>The full-grown larva measure 40-50 mm in length. The young larvae</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="6">Pest of Cruciferous vegetable Cabbage (Brassica oleracea var.capitata L.); Cauliflower (Brassica oleracea var. botrytis L.); Knol-khol (Brassica oleracea var. gongylodes); and Radish (Raphanus sativus L.) Family : Brassicae</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">S.No Pest Cabbage Caterpillar Pieris brassicae Scientific name Diamond-back Moth Plutella xylostella • Hosts: It is a serious pest of cabbage, cauliflower, knol-khol and it may also Order Family Lepidoptera Pieridae Lepidoptera Yponomeutidae attack turnip, radish, sarson, toriaand other cruciferous plants. Eggs • Marks of identification:</cell></row><row><cell>Cabbage • Larva:</cell><cell>Semi-</cell><cell>Thysanopulsia</cell><cell></cell><cell>Lepidoptera</cell><cell>Noctuidae</cell></row><row><cell>looper</cell><cell></cell><cell>orichalcea</cell><cell>and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Autographa nigrisigna</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">Tobacco Caterpillar Spodoptera litura</cell><cell></cell><cell>Lepidoptera</cell><cell>Noctuidae</cell></row><row><cell>Crucifer</cell><cell>Leaf-</cell><cell cols="3">Crocidolomia binotalis Lepidoptera</cell><cell>Pyralidae</cell></row><row><cell>webber</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Cabbage Borer</cell><cell></cell><cell>Hellula undalis</cell><cell></cell><cell>Lepidoptera</cell><cell>Pyralidae</cell></row><row><cell>Cabbage</cell><cell>Flea</cell><cell cols="2">Phyllotreta cruciferae,</cell><cell>Coleoptera</cell><cell>Chrysomelidae</cell></row><row><cell cols="6">Beetles • Management: Dusting Quinalphos 1.5 % or spray application of Dimethoate .03% malathion P. chotanica, P. 0.1% quinalphos 0.05% or cypermethrin0.025%. Spray these insecticide four times at monthly birmanica, P.oncera, P. intervals. downesi</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_38"><head>are pale yellow, and become greenish yellow later on. The head is black and the dorsum is marked with black spots. The body is decorated with short hair.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_39"><head>Spodoptera litura (Fabricius) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Hosts: Besides tobacco, feeds on castor, groundnut, tomato, sunflower, cabbage and various other cruciferous crops.</cell></row><row><cell>Marks of identification:-Larva : Larva measure 35-40 mm in length, at maturity. They are velvety</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_40"><head>black with yellowish-green dorsal stripes and lateral white bands. Adult :The moth are about 22 mm long and measure 40 mm across the spread wings</head><label></label><figDesc>The larvae feed gregariously for the first few days and then disperse to feed individually. They pass through 6 stages and are full-fed in 15-30 days. The full-grown larvae enter the soil where they pupate.</figDesc><table /><note>. The fore wings have beautiful golden and greyish brown patterns.Life-cycle:This pest breeds throughout the year, although its development is considerably retarded during winter. The moths are active at night when they mate and the female lays about 300 eggs in clusters. These clusters are covered over by brown hair and they hatch in about 3-5 days.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_41"><head>The pupal stage lasts 7-15 days and</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>The natural enemies,</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>300 Egg</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>3-5 D</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Adult 7-10 D</cell><cell>8 G</cell><cell>Larva 15-30 D</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Pupa</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>7-15 D</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>the moths, on emergence, live for 7-10 days. The life cycle is completed in 32-60 days and the pest completes eight generations in a year.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_42"><head>Compoletis sp., Eriborus sp., Rogas sp. (Braconidae) and</head><label></label><figDesc>Strobliomiyia orbata W. (Anthomyiidae) are associated with larvae of this pest.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Damage:</cell></row><row><cell>The damage is done only by the caterpillars.</cell></row><row><cell>The larvae feed on leaves and fresh growth. They are mostly active at night and cause extensive damage, particularly in tobacco nurseries.</cell></row><row><cell>Management:</cell></row><row><cell>Remove the egg masses and clusters of larvae and destroy them.</cell></row><row><cell>(</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_43"><head>ii)Spray 625 ml of diazinon 20EC or 1.0 litre or endosulfan 35EC or quinalphos 35EC or trichlorphon 50EC or 250 ml of fenvalerate 20EC in 250 litres of water per ha. Repeat sprays at one week intervals.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>7. MEALYBUG, Phenacocus solenopsis Tinsley (Cotton mealy bug, Hemiptera:Pseudococcidae Curculionidae 15.Cotton stem weevil, Pempherulus affinis, Coleoptera : Coleoptera : Curculionidae 14.Cotton grey weevil, Myllocerus undecimpustulatus, 13.Green semi-looper, Anomis flava, Lepidoptera : Noctuidae Noctuidae 12.Cotton semi looper, Tarache notabilis, Lepidoptera : 11.Bud moth,Phycitia infusella, Lepidoptera : Pyrallidae Pyrallidae 10.Cotton leaf roller, Sylepta derogate, Lepidoptera : 9.Dusky cotton bug, Oxycarenus laetus Hemiptera : Lygaedae Pyrrhocoridae) 8. Red cotton bug, Dysdercus koennigii ( Hemiptera: 1. Cotton leafhopper (Jassid), Amrasca biguttula biguttula (lshida) (Hemiptera Cicadellidae)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_44"><head>0 litres of fenitrothion 50EC, 2.0 litres of quinalphos 25EC, 1. 25 litres of monocrotophos 36SL, 5.0 litres of chlorpyriphos 20EC, 2.0 litres of ethion 50EC, 1.25 litres of profenophos 50EC. (c) Carbamctes 2.5 kg of carbaryl 50WP, (d) Synthetic pyrethroids. 500 ml of cypermethrin 10EC, 200 ml of cypermethrin 25EC, 400 ml of deltamethrin 2.8EC, 275 ml of deltamethrin 4EC, 250 ml of fenvalerate 20EC 300 ml of Fluvalinate 25EC, 250 ml of alphamethrin I0EC or asymethrin 5EC. (e) 150 ml of spinosad 48 SC.</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>• Organophosphates. 2.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_45"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>• Chemical control : Poison baits : (A) acute poisons : which are uded in a single dose Ex. 1. strychnine hydrochloride.2. Zinc phosphide.3. Norbormide (Raticate).4. Sodium fluoro-acetate.5. Thallium sulphate. 6.( ANTU) Alfanaphthyl thiourea. • (B) Chronic poison: Which are used in multiple doses . Which acts as blood anticoagulants. 1. Hydroxy coumarins (warfarin, fumarin, tomarin and recumin). • Indan dions (Pival, Radione and Valone).These chemicals case external and internal haemorrhage. • Bromadiolane, and Brodicacoum are lethal in a single dose but rate die after several days of poisoning. Bromadiolane bait (0.005% Bromadiolane) can be prepared by mixing 20 gm of 0.25 per cent Bromadiolane powder ,20 gm of oil and 20 gm of powdered sugar in 1 kg of any cereal flour.32 • Zinc phosphide 2% bait : • 2 gm zinc phosphide, 98 gm bait (whole or cracked grains of wheat, gram maize, bajra or sorghum smeared with vegetable oils. • Fumigation with aluminium phosphide : aluminium phosphide one tablet of 3 gm/per burrow should be introduced after that burrow should be closed tightly.</figDesc><table /></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0">ii. In case seed treatment has not been done; apply12.5 kg of carbofuran 3G, 10 kg of phorate 10G/ha, in furrow before sowing( iii) spray 1.25 litres of malathion 50 EC or 2.0 kg cararyl 50 WP in 500 liters of water/ha.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SORGHUM (Sorghum bicolor,Famly:Gramineae)</head><p>More than 150 species of insects have been reported to damage sorghum. However, over a dozen species are very serious and constitute a major constraint in sorghum production.</p><p>House sparrow,Passer domestics (Passeriformes. Ploceidae)</p><p>15</p><p>Indian Myna: Acridotheres tristis (Passeriformes: Saturnidae)</p></div>
			</div>


			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Common Indian field mouse: Mus booduga Gray.</head><p>• It dwells in shallow burrows.</p><p>6. Indian mole rat: Bandicota bengalensis Gray.</p><p>• It is found all-over India.</p><p>• It measures 6-9 inches and weighs 300 g.</p><p>• Live in extensive burrow.</p><p>• It destroys many crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B) Bandicoot: Bandicota indica L.</head><p>• Largest in size.</p><p>C) Gerbils: Tatera indica Hardw.</p><p>• They differ from rats in having their tails clothed in fur and ending in tassel.</p><p>• Live in unplanned burrows.</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pest of POTATO (Solanum tuberosum)</head><note type="other">Family: Solanaceae</note><p>This pest occurs especially in hot and dry climates. It is destructive to potato and also attacks tobacco, tomato, brinjal and solanaceous weeds. It is particularly serious on potato in Himachal Pradesh. The adult is very small narrow-winged nocturnal moth, about 13 mm across the wings when spread, It is greyish brown with mottling of dark brown.</p><p>The larvae cause the damage and are recognized as pinkish-white or greenish caterpillars, with dark-brown heads. They are about 20 mm in length. Another species of tuber moth attacking potato is P. heliopa <ref type="bibr">(Lower)</ref> Life-cycle: This pest may breed throughout the year. In cold weather, the life-cycle is much prolonged.</p><p>Early in the spring, the moths escape from store-houses and start breeding in fields. A female, on an average, lays 150-200 eggs singly on the underside of leaves or on exposed tubers. H. P. is 2-6 days.</p><p>The larvae first produce blotch mines on leaves but subsequently, they work their way into the stems.</p><p>The larval stage in summer lasts 2-3 weeks and the mature larva pupates in a grayish silken dirt-covered cocoon, which is about 13 mm in length. The moths emerge in 7-10 (Pupa) days.</p><p>They complete their life-cycle about one month and there are usually 5-6 generations in a year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p>In warm dry climates extensive damage may be done to the crop; but the potato tubers kept in cold stores escape damage. Later generations in the field infest the tubers also. The grubs bore into the tender vines and tubers making the later unfit for marketing and consumption. At the time of digging, the moths may lay eggs on tubers. The larvae, on hatching, may work their way just under the skin and, later, may make tunnels through the flesh, causing damage to the tubers. 30 to 70 % damage in storage. The eggs hatch in 2-4 days and the maggots on emergence feed on leaf tissue at first but later on move to the terminal stems.</p><p>They pass through three instars and the larval development is completed in 6-7 days in March-April and 9-12 days in November and December.</p><p>The larva pupates within its gallery and the pupal period lasts 5-9 days in March and April, and 18-19 days in November and December.</p><p>The female flies live for 8-22 days and the males for 11 days. The pest completes 8-9 generations from July to April and shifts from one host plant to the other in various seasons.</p><p>It passes winter as larva or as pupa. Marks of identification: Larva: When full-grown, the larvae measure about 8 mm in length and are pale yellowish green with fine black hair scattered all over the body.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Adult:</head><p>The moths measure about 8-12 mm in length and are brown or grey, with conspicuous white spots on the fore wings, which appear like diamond patterns when the wings lie flat over the body.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Life-cycle:</head><p>This insect is active throughout the year. Yellowish eggs of the size of pin heads are laid singly or in batches of 2-40 on the underside of leaves. A female may lay 18-</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PESTS OF COTTON</head><p> COTTON (Gossypium spp.: Family :Malvaceae) Although India occupies the largest area in the world under cotton, it ranks third in production. More than 1326 species of insects have been reported attacking cotton in the World However, in India, only 162 species have been recorded, among which only 15 species may be called as major pests due to their occurrence in serious proportions almost every year.</p><p>Ornithology: Study of Birds. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Habits</head><p>• It breeds practically throughout the year and makes nest by collecting a few sticks and lines them with rags and feathers. • The nest are located in the holes on cliffs,rafters and ceiling of the house, particularly those uninhabitated. • There are generally two white elliptical eggs in the clutch and both sexes share domestic duties. • Individually or in small groups, they are always around to pick up grains from here and there. • In large buildings , they are a nuisance as they cause noise and makes the floor and walls dirty with their droppings</p><p>Management of Birds:</p><p>• The periodic collection and destruction of nests would lead to reduction in their population. • Scaring: Many visual and sound devices have been used by man in an attempt to scare birds.Ex. LPG gas gun, rotating lights, scarecrows, reflective mirror or tape. • Netting: Parmanant net can be used to make birds away.</p><p>• Use of gulel : This mechanical device can be used to disperse the birds groups. • Use of chemical: (1) use of non toxic and sticky materials like lassa. • (2): Use of repellents like cupric oxide and methiocarb.</p><p>• ( 3) Use of toxic chemicals: These chemicals like insecticide are prohibited in our country.</p><p>Rodents and their management in field and godowns.</p><p>• Rodents are omnivorous and feed on grains, vegetables, fruit, meet, and other products in the house or in the field. • Rodents are responsible for causing enormous losses to crops and stored grains.</p><p>• They damage about 20 times the amount they actually consuming by their gnawing activity and by polluting the food grains ( droppings, urine, body hair etc). • It has been estimated that there are about 2500 millions rates are found in India. • They inflict, on an everage about 5-10 per cent loss in food products alone.</p><p>• 84 species of rodents are found in India, out of which 10 are of major significance. • Only few important species are discussed here.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Habit andHabitat</head><p>• Very cunning and claver animal.</p><p>• Colour blind.</p><p>• Well developed sense organ, smell, taste, hearing.</p><p>• Bearchesel like teeth.</p><p>• Generally search food in night.</p><p>• Good swimmer.</p><p>• Good climber • New afraid of new objects.</p><p>• Burrow in field and houses, close to the food materials in houses.</p><p>Difference between Mouse and rat</p><p>• Mouse.</p><p>• Size small to medium size, 12 to 20 cm in length. • Mice have thin, slightly hairy tail. • Nose triangular in shape.</p><p>• Brown and grey in colour.</p><p>• Rat.</p><p>• Medium sized to large size,measuring 40 cm in length. • Thicker, hairless,scaly tail • Nose blunt and rounded.</p><p>• Apart from Brown and grey in colour their colour may black also.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Common Indian field mouse (Mus musculus booduga)</head><p>The body of Indian field mouse is about 5 to 8 cm long with 5 cm long tail. It is brown in color with a white belly. It burrows in field bunds causing extensive damage to bunds and wastage of water. It produces 3 to 9 young ones per litter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Brown rat or Norway rat (Rattus norvegicus)</head><p>Closely associated with the activity of man. Good climber and swimmer. Prefers wet or damp locations. Do not close the burrow openings. Length from nose to tail 35-41 cm with blunt snout. Brownish above, white on belly.</p><p>Indian mole rat, Bandicota bengalensis,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rodentia : Murinae</head><p>• This rat has greyish-brownor black on top and greyish -white colour on the belly. • It is heavily built and a pig like face and a short stumpy head.</p><p>• It breed through out the year and the number of young ones per litter vary from 6-15. • The mole rat hoards large amount of food in its burrows.</p><p>• There are 2-12 burrow ,tunnels has 2-5 linesof which some are blind and have food chamber at the end. • The burrows are generally found in the field of groundnut, wheat, gram, sugarcane, maize, sorghum, cotton, paddy, and in fruit orchards. • The mole rat cut the entire paddy ears but rat only part of it.</p><p>• Like other species, it migrate from the harvested fields to the newly sown crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nature and Symptoms of damage</head><p>Rodents attack rice at all stages of growth from planting to harvest and if there is opportunity, even they will continue to attack the grain in store.</p><p>Freshly sown seed may be dug up and the seed eaten. On young rice plants, rodents attack the heart of the stem discarding the leaves. The rodents make the rice stems fall by gnawing 5-15 cm above ground level. Some rodent species may store grain in their burrows. Large rodents, besides feeding on the crop may cause serious damage to the bunds.</p><p>Occasional pest: Many insects occur rather infrequently and close association with a particular crop is absent e.g mango stem borer. Occasional pest: a pest with general equilibarium position substantially below the economic injury level; highest pest population fluctuations occasionally and sporadically exceed the economic injury level.</p><p>Persistent pest: Insect which occur on a crop almost throughout the year are called as persistent pest.</p><p>Potential pest: These insects normally do not cause any economic damage, but may become serious pests resulting from some changes in the ecosystem, e.g. armyworm on wheat.</p><p>Sporadic pest: Insect which occur in a few isolated localities are known as sporadic pest Epidemic pest: When pest occur in a severe form in a particular area or locality is known as epidemic pest Endemic pest: When infestation occurs at a regular feature and confined mostly to a particular area or locality Plant protection: refers to the measure which is used to protect the crop from pest and disease.</p><p>Pest control: Any method employed to reduce the pest population and to prevent damage caused by them are known as pest control.</p><p>Integrated pest control: A multidisciplinary ecological approach to the management of pest population which utilizes a variety of control tactics compatibility in a single coordinated pest management system is termed as integrated pest control.</p><p>IPM: According to FOA.(1967) it is the system that in context of the associated environment and population dynamics of pest species , utilizes all the suitable technique and methods in as compatible manner as possible and maintains the pest population at a level below those causing economic injury.</p><p>Biological control: Metcalf and flint (1962) defined biological control as the destruction and suppression of undesirable insects other enemies or weeds by the introduction, encouragement or artificial increase of their natural enemies.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Biological control:</head><p>The employment of any biological agent for pest suppression.</p><p>Parasite: parasite is an organism which at one time or other lives on the body of the host which may or may not be killed after it has completed development.</p><p>Parasitoid: A parasitoid is an organism which completes its life on one host only and kills it.</p><p>Predator: Predator is a free living organism and kills the host immediately normally larger than prey (host) requires more than one host to develop and is very specific unlike parasitoids, e.g. lady bird beetle (Coccinell septempunctata, Coccinella sexmaculata) and green lace wing (Chrysoperla carnea)</p><p>Pesticide: Pesticide is a chemical which kills the pests by its chemical action. Insecticide is a pesticide and the term is used for those chemicals which kill the insects. The term pesticide is a broad group which contains chemicals used to kill a wide range of</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Macrosiphum rosaeformis (Aphididae: Hemiptera)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Insect Pest of Rice(Oryza sativa, Family: Gramineae)</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Yellow stem borer (Scirpophaga incertulas) (Lepidoptera; Family -Pyralidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Dicladispa armigera)</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Coleoptera</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Chrysomelidae</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pink borer(Sesamia inferens</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Lepidoptera : Noctuidae)</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Rice leaf-folder</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lepidoptera: Pyralidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Cnaphalocrocis medinalis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Diptera: Cecidomyiidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Orceolia oryzae</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Whitebacked</forename><surname>Planthopper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Hemiptera : Delphacidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sogatella furcifera</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Green Leafhoppers</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Nephotettix nigropictus) and (N. virescens)</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Hemiptera</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Cicadellidae</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Coleoptera : Curculionidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Paddy root weevil (Echinocnemus oryzae</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Hemiptera : Coreidae) 1. Common house crow, Corvus splendens L</title>
				<imprint/>
		<respStmt>
			<orgName>Rice bug (Leptocorisa acuta</orgName>
		</respStmt>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Rose ringed parakeet, Psittacula krameri Scopoli 3. House sparrow, Passer domesticus L 4. Common myna, Acridotheres tristis L 5. Pigeon</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Columba livia Gmelin</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Peacock</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Pavo cristatus L</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b13">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sorghum shoot fly (Atherigona soccata) (Diptera : Muscidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b14">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Sorghum earhead bug</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Hemiptera</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Miridae</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Calocoris angustatus</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b15">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Hemiptera : Delphacidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Sorghum shoot bug</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b16">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Contarina sorghicola (Diptera : cecidomyidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b17">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Stem borer, Chilo partellus ( Lepidoptera : pyralidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b18">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Lepidoptera : Noctuidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Pink borer</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b19">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Hemiptera : Aphididae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rhopalosiphum maidis</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b20">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Leaf hopper, Pyrilla perpusilla ( Hemiptera : Lophopidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b21">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Hairy caterpillar</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Amsacta moorei (Lepidoptera : Arctiidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b22">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Holotrichae consanguinea ( Coleoptera : scarabaeidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b23">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Neomaskelliia bergii (Hemiptera : Aleyrodidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b24">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Hatching period 3-6days. Larval period 9-28 days. Pupal stage in the fallen leaves 6-17 days. 5 over laping generation</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Life cycle: Egg,creamy white egg on under surface of leaves, stem,flower buds and calyces of fruit</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b25">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">G Egg 3-6 Days Caterpillar 9-28 Days Pupa 6-17 Days Adult Damage:The young caterpillar bore into the tender shoot near the growing point into flower buds and into the fruits. The growing point of the plant killed. Later on it bore into the fruit. One caterpillar may destroy as many as 4-6 fruits. The damage to fruit particularly in autumn</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>is very severe. Management: (1) Remove and destroy the infested fruit</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b26">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Avoid continuous cropping of brinjal crop</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b27">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">spray carbaryl 50 wp @ 4 gm or formathion 50 EC @ 1 ml or Acephate 50 EC @ 0.5 gm quinalphos 25 EC, trizophos 40 EC and monocrotophos 36 SL @ 2 ml per litres of water</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b28">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Pink bollworm, Pectinophora gossypiella (Saunders) (Lepidoptera -Gelechiidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b29">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Spotted bollworms, Earias insulana (Boisduval) and E. Vittella (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b30">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">American</forename><surname>Bollworm</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Helicoverpa armigera (Hubner) (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b31">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cotton Leafhopper</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Amrasca biguttula biguttula (lshida)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
	<note>Hemiptera Cicadellidae</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b32">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Bemisia</forename><surname>Cotton Whitefly</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Tabaci</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Aleyrodidae</publisher>
			<pubPlace>Gennadius) (Hemiptera</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b33">
	<monogr>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Cotton Aphid</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<title level="m">Aphis gossypii Glover (Hemiptera: Aphididae)</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b34">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">The seed should be acid-delinted or fumigated before sowing</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b35">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Replace the cotton seed by seed-cake for feeding the animals</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b36">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">The damage of the pest can be reduced by sowing short-duration varieties and by early termination of last irrigation to the crop. Rose-ringed parakeet</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Psittacula krameri</title>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>Psittacidae</publisher>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
