<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">BANANA BOXES ON RACK IN PRE-COOLING CHAMBER TEMPERATURE MEASUREMENT ON TRANSFER OF BOXES TO COLD STORAGE TEMPERATURE MEASUREMENT OF BANANA PULP AFTER UNLOADING OF BOXES FROM</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Karnataka</forename><surname>Maharashtra</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Andhra</forename><surname>Pradesh</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Tamil</forename><surname>Nadu</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">June</forename><surname>Mid</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">BANANA BOXES ON RACK IN PRE-COOLING CHAMBER TEMPERATURE MEASUREMENT ON TRANSFER OF BOXES TO COLD STORAGE TEMPERATURE MEASUREMENT OF BANANA PULP AFTER UNLOADING OF BOXES FROM</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">9F3DAF57868BE5F409F54F4B8A913F26</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:41+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Major Insect Pests of Banana</head><p> Alternately, application of imidachlorprid (0.04%) also controls the pest population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pseudostem Borer (Odoiporus longicollis)</head><p>Damage:  The larvae or grub of the weevil feeds by tunnelling in the banana plant.  The corm decays and becomes a mass of rotten tissue. Injury to corm prevents nourishment going to the plant.  Leaves turn yellow, wither and die maturely.  Adults feed on dead or dying banana plants and live under newly cut or rotting pseudostems.  The female weevil either lays its eggs in the rotting pseudostem or moves to a living plant where eggs are inserted singly into a hole.  Spreads from plantation to plantation through planting material. Control:  Plantations should be clear of debris in which borers can survive.  Use clean planting material from fields, known to be free of weevils.  Pieces of old rhizomes or pseudostems 1-2 feet long are cut down split and placed on the plantation floor between plants.  Adult beetles migrate into these stems and can be collected by hand and poisoned.  Before planting dipping of suckers in imidachloprid (0.5%) for 30 minutes to protect rhizome from weevil attack.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rhizome Weevil (Cosmopolites sordidus)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contd…</head><p>Damage:  The insect, is the vector of the virus causing bunchy top disease.  Yellowish green nymphs and adults suck cell sap and devitalise plants.  Affected parts become discoloured and malformed.  High humidity favours rapid multiplication of this pest.  The aphids are mostly observed on the lower surface of the leaves.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control:</head><p> Spraying of Monocrotophos (0.05%) or Malathion (0.1%) at 10-15 days interval contains aphid population effectively.  To prevent recurrence of the pest granular insecticides like Phorate @ 1.0 kg a.i./ha should be applied to soil. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Banana Aphid (Pentalonia nigronervosa)</head><note type="other">Cont…</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scarring Beetle</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post Harvest Technology of Banana</head><p>Grading:  The hands are graded based on the number and size of fingers in each hand.  Overripe and injured fruits are discarded at this stage.</p><p>Banana is sent to the local market as bunches Packaging:  For packing and transportation the bunch is padded with banana leaves.  A fungicidal paste prepared by the Central Food Technological Research Institute, Mysore is applied to cut ends to prevent stem end rot. After the paste dries, the bunches are put into polythene tubes (175 gauge, 55 cm wide with 1.8 cm with holes 10 cm apart).  The bunches should then be stacked vertically or horizontally on the ground added with wilted or dry banana leaves in case there is delay in transportation.  For exports, bananas are removed from the stem and hands and clusters of the bananas are packed in corrugated boxes with perforated polyethylene liners. The curved side of the hands is kept facing upwards making sure that the crown of the upper hands do not damage the banana underneath.  Mature-green bananas can be stored for up to 3 weeks in ethylene-free air or up to 6 weeks in a controlled atmosphere at 14 o C.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Contd…</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cool Chain:</head><p>The various stages of the cool chain are: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Some Problems Observed</head><p> Some Banana were at advanced stage of maturity.  Some degree of bruising seen  Crown was not cut deep enough to prevent rotting in some hands  Wrong packing -some boxes packed with crown down instead of crown up.</p><p>Overall Bananas not comparable to Chiquita or Del Monte in quality or appearance. But with improvements Jalgaon Banana can compete with the best.</p><p>• Cost competitiveness needs to be improved -India loses 3 to 4 million tons of Banana annually due to reported post harvest losses at 30-40%. This adds to the cost of Banana.</p><p>• Bruise, Injury and Mechanized shocks due to poor harvesting technique, -improper loading and unloading operations and lack of proper post harvest practices.</p><p>• Lack of pack house facilities for washing and grading, on-farm cooling, cold storage or cold chain, lack of knowledge on harvest standards, handling and packaging techniques.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Industry Problems</head><p>Major Insect Pests of Grape Damage:  The adult beetles scrap the sprouting buds after each pruning.  Damaged buds fail to sprout.</p><p> The beetles also feed on tender shoots and leaves, and tendrils causing substantial damage.  The tender shoots may wither and drop down.  The losses are heavy when the sprouting buds are damaged after forward pruning. Control:  Removal of loose bark of the stem and applying paste of Copper Oxychloride and Carbaryl 50% WP after forward pruning to exposes and kills the beetles.  Spraying of insecticides like Carbaryl (0.15%) or Quinalphos (0.05%) from the fourth day after pruning at an interval of 3-5 days until the emergence of the leaves is effective in protecting the sprouting bud from the attack.  The spraying should preferably be carried out in the evening.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flea Beetles (Scelodonta strigicollis)</head><p>Damage:  Both the nymphs and adults suck cell sap from the lower surface of the leaf.  The injured surface is marked by a number of minute spots thereby producing a speckled silvery effect, which can be detected from a distance.  In case of heavy incidence, the leaves may dry up and drop off the vine.  Thrips also attack blossoms and newly set berries.  The affected berries develop a corky layer and become brown on maturity.  Fruit setting is poor and yield is considerably reduced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control:</head><p> Alternate spraying of insecticides like Phosphamidon (0.05%) or Monocrotophos (0.1%) or Malathion (0.05%) offer a good control over the pest.  Prophylactic sprays immediately after flowering and during fruit set is essential.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Thrips (Rhipiphorothrips cruentauis)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cont…</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p> Most common pest found in the vineyards of Punjab.  The adult female lays eggs in the crevices or loose bark of the vine, trunk and its arms.  These insects suck the cell sap from the leaves, petioles, main veins and tender shoots of the grapevine.  Weak shoot growth with appearance of golden-yellow leaves indicates the advanced stage of pest attack.  As the arms become dry, wood-boring insects may cause further damage.  Frequent attack in subsequent years leads to the death of the vine.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control:</head><p> The loose bark should be removed at the time of pruning.  The encrustations should be scraped and the vine should be sprayed with Trithion (0.05%).  Cuttings free from the infestation of the pest should be used for planting.  Ants which act as carrier of the scales should be controlled to check the spread of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Scale Insects (Aspidiotus lataniae; A. cydoniae)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cont…</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p> The nematodes mostly damage the secondary and the feeder roots.  The affected roots show brownish discoloration.  The affected portions rot and get sloughed off. As a result the nutrient uptake is affected and the vine appears sick. Control:  Soil application of Carbofuran (2.5 kg a.i. /ha) or neem cake (1 t/ha) helps to control the reniform nematode.  Application of organic manures reduces the nematode population when applied to grapevines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reniform Nematode (Rotylenchulus reniformis)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cont…</head><p>Damage:  The affected roots exhibit severe galling.  Galling is the result of the proliferation of cells of the affected roots.  The vines show stunting and poor growth. Young shoots remain short and chlorotic.  In severe attack, the vines get defoliated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control:</head><p> Soil application of Carbofuran (2.5 kg a.i. /ha) or neem cake (1 t/ha) helps to control the root knot nematode.  Application of organic manures reduces the nematode population when applied to grapevines.</p><p>Root-knot Nematode (Meloidogyne sp.)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cont…</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Post Harvest Technology of Grapes</head><p>Grading:  The harvested bunches are graded as per their size of the berries and their colour.  Before packing, the broken, decayed, deformed, undersized, and discoloured berries are removed by their pedicels from the selected bunches, using a long nosed scissors.  While cleaning, harvesting or trimming bunches should be held by their stalk, preferably by wearing rubber gloves.  This care is taken not to erase the fine waxy coating called 'bloom' from the berry surface.  Otherwise it leads to rapid loss of water through the skin of berries and they shrivel during storage. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Storage:</head><p> They are normally pre-cooled at 1-2 o C within 6 hours of harvest.  After pre-cooling, the dual releasing Sulphur dioxide pads (Grape guard) are placed with their coated surfaces downwards on the filled plastic pouches and covered with the polythene liner.  The boxes are closed and shifted to cold storage rooms where the temperature and humidity are maintained at 0-2 o C and 95% respectively.  The arrangement of boxes in the cold storage to ensure uniform cooling of all berries in a box and all boxes is very important.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cool Chain:</head><p>The various stages of the cool chain are:</p><p>1. Cold store at the farm. 2. Refrigerated truck from farm to the airport 3. Cold store at the airport. 4. Building up of the pallet in a cold store at the airport. 5. Loading the aircrafts directly from the cold store in a short time. 6. Cargo aircraft maintains cold store temperature in hold. 7. Off loading direct into a cold store in the receiving country. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hopper (Idioscopus clypealis, I. nitidulus and Amritodus atkinson)</head><p>Damage:  Nymphs and adults suck the plant sap and reduce the vigour of the plant.  Secretes honey dew, facilitating sooty mould development.  The female adult crawls down the tree in the month of April-May and enter in the cracks in the soil for laying eggs.  Just after hatching, the minute newly hatched pink to brown coloured nymphs crawl up the tree.  After climbing up the tree, they start sucking the sap of tender plant parts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control:</head><p> Flooding of orchards with water in the month of October kills the eggs.  Ploughing the orchards in the month of November exposes the eggs to suns heat.  Polythene bands of 400 gauge and 25 cm width fastened around the tree trunk have been found effective barrier to stop the ascent of nymphs to the trees.  The band should be fastened well in advance before the hatching of eggs, i.e., during November-December.  Application of 250 g per tree of Methyl Parathion 2% dust in soil around the trunk kills the newly hatched nymphs.  Spraying of 0.05% Monocrotophos or 0.2% Carbaryl or 0.05% Methyl Parathion is useful in controlling young nymphs of the mealy bug.  The entomogenous fungus Beauveria bassiana is found to be an effective bioagent in controlling the nymphs of this pest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mealy Bugs (Drosicha mangiferae)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cont…</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage:</head><p> Most serious pest in export of fresh fruits.  The female punctures the outer wall of the mature fruits with the help of its pointed ovipositor and insert eggs in small clusters inside the mesocarp of mature fruits.  After hatching, the larva feeds on the pulp of fruit which appears normal from outside, but drops down finally.  The mature maggots fall down into the soil for pupation.</p><p>The  5. Method of packing:-(i) Fruits and Vegetables shall be packed in such a way as to protect the produce properly.</p><p>(ii) The materials used inside the package must be new, clean and of such a quality as to avoid causing any external or internal damage to the produce.</p><p>(iii) The use of materials particularly of paper or stamps bearing trade specifications is permitted provided the printing or labelling has been done with non toxic ink or glue.</p><p>(iv) Fruits and Vegetables shall be packed in each container in compliance with the recommended international code of practice for Packaging and Transport of Tropical Fresh Fruit and Vegetables (CAC/RCP 44-1995) of practice for export and as per the Instructions issued by the Agricultural Marketing adviser from time to time for domestic market.</p><p>(v) The containers shall meet the quality, hygiene, ventilation and resistance characteristics to ensure suitable handling, shipping and preserving of the Fruits and Vegetables. Packages must be free of harmful foreign matter and obnoxious smell.</p><p>(vi) Contents of each package or lot must be uniform and contain only Fruits and Vegetables of same origin, variety and grade designation.</p><p>(vii) The visible part of the contents of the package (if present) must be representative of the entire content. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cont…</head><p>7. Frui ts and Vegetables may be graded and marked as per buyer's requirements for exports provided the mini mum requi rements specified in the relevant schedule are met.</p><p>8. For domesti c trade, Fruits and Vegetables shall comply with the residue level s of heavy metals, pesti cides, aflatoxin and other food safety parameters as specified in Prevention of Food Adul teration Rul es, 1955. 9. Special conditions of certificate of authorisation:-In addi tion to the condi tions specified under sub-rule (8)of the rule 3 of the General Grading and Marking Rul es, 1988, every authorised packer shall follow al l i nstructions prescribed by Agricultural Marketi ng Adviser from ti me to time. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Method of Marking and Labeling</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GRADE DESIGNATION AND QUALITY OF TABLE GRAPES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Criteria for Grade Designation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grade designation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grade Requirements Provision concerning sizing</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Grade tolerances</head><p>Extra class Grapes must be of superior quality. The bunches must be typical of variety in shape, development and colouring and have no defects. Berries must be firm, firmly attached to the stalk, evenly spaced along the stalk and have their bloom virtually intact.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>As per table`A'</head><p>5% by weight of bunches not satisfying the requirements for the grade, but meeting those of Class I grade or exceptionally coming within the tolerances of that grade.</p><p>Class I Grapes must be of good quality. The bunches must be typical of variety in shape, development and colouring. Berries must be firm, firmly attached to the stalk and, as far as possible, have their gloom intact. The may, however, be less evenly spaced along the stalk than in the extra class. Following slight defects may be there, provided these do not affect the general appearance of the produce and keeping quality of the package.</p><p>-a slight defect in shape, -a slight defect in colouring do 10% by weight of bunches not satisfying the requirements for the grade, but meeting those of Class II grade or exceptionally coming within the tolerances of that grade.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Class II</head><p>The bunches may show defects in shape, development and colouring provided these do not impair the essential characteristics of the variety. The berries must be sufficiently firm and sufficiently attached. They may be less evenly spaced along the stalk than Class I grade. Following defects may be there, provided these do not affect the general appearance of the produce and keeping quality of the package.    </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Other Requirements</head><note type="other">Export Specifications for Grapes Grape Export Suffered</note></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Other Requirements</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.Provisions Concerning Sizing</head><p>For all grades, 10% by number or weight of mangoes in each package are permitted to be outside (above or below) the group size range by 50% of the maximum permissible difference for the group. In the smallest size range, mangoes must not be less than 90 gms. and for those in the largest size range a maximum of 925 grams applies, as follows: </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Adults are either reddish-brown or black.  The pest is active during summer and monsoon months.  The grubs bore into the stem and feed within the stem.  An initial symptom is in the form of exudation of plant sap and blackened mass that comes out from the hole by the grub. Control:  Uprooting and burning of infected plants.  Celphos (3 tablets/plant) is recommended for control of egg, larva, pupa and adult population of the insect, application of.  After placing the tablet inside the pseudostem, the slit should be plastered with mud.  Clean cultivation.  Application of Carbofuran (3 g of granules/stool).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The first symptom of the disease is a small dark spot on the root.  The nematode deposit eggs in the root tissue.  Larvae after hatching form the eggs feed on the root tissue.  Fungi rapidly invade such damaged root tissue.  The number of fruits in the bunch is reduced and individual fruits are small.  Affected plants do not respond to fertilizers, irrigation or cultural practices. Nematode population is built up rapidly in ratoon crops. Control:  Application of Carbofuran 3G or Phorate 10G @10 g/pit at the time of planting or application of neem cake (250-400 g/pit) at the time of planting reduces the pest population.  Control measures such as application of nematicides to the growing infected plants and planting of nematode-free corms in fallow soil are recommended. Burrowing Nematode (Radopholus similis) Cont… Damage:  The adult beetles feed on various weeds, as well as the young unfurled leaves, stems, and roots of banana trees. They also eat on the young fruit, making scars and spots on the skin that deforms it and makes it unmarketable. Control:  Clean cultivation.  Application of Rogor 1ml/l or imidachlorprid (0.04%).</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>*</head><label></label><figDesc>Outer ply of white duplex board or bleached kraft **Or any other suitable style which provides equal strength and performance ***Outer ply to be laminated or coated for water proofing Specifications developed by IIP for APEDA Packing and Packaging in CFB Boxes Post Harvest Technology of Banana Storage:  Cold storage: 13-14°C with 90-95% RH.  Controlled atmospheric conditions: 2-5% oxygen and 2-5% carbon dioxide should be used to supplement temperature and humidity management during transport and storage.  Maintaining ethylene concentration below 1 ppm can extend postharvest life.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The grapes sent to the local market are packed in ventilated corrugated boxes accommodating 2-4 kg of grapes.  These boxes are lined with newsprint paper. Fine paper shred or fine hay is spread at the bottom and top of the box for cushioning.  The open flaps of the box are secured firmly by an adhesive tape. Table grapes for overseas market are packed in 5 ply corrugated boxes of size 500x300mm accommodating 5 kg of grapes.  The graded bunches are weighed into 5 kg lots in plastic trays.  One or two bunches weighing between 350-650 g are placed in small and thin polythene pouches.  Before placing the pouches in the carton, bubble sheet is spread with its rough surface facing towards the base of the box.  A white and soft polythene liner is spread over the top of the bubble sheet.  These pouches are arranged in a single layer in a slanting fashion in the carton.  The flaps at the open end of the carton are folded before precooling.  After precooling, dual purpose SO 2 releasing pads are placed over the pouches and the polythene liner is folded in.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>8 .</head><label>8</label><figDesc>Refrigerated truck to the customer Cont… Major Insect Pests of Mango Damage:  Most serious and widespread pest of mango.  Nymphs and adult insects puncture and suck the sap of tender parts.  Heavy puncturing and continuous draining of the sap causes curling and drying of the infested tissue.  Secrets sweet sticky substance which facilitate the development of the fungus Maliola managiferae (sooty mould).  Hopper population shoots up in Feb-April and June-Aug. Control:  Three sprays of 0.15% Carbaryl or 0.04% Monocrotophos or 0.05% Phosphamidon or 0.05% Methyl Parathion are effective .  First spray: at the early stage of panicle formation.  Second spray: at full-length stage of panicles but before full bloom  Third spray: after the fruits set at pea size stage  Biological control agents: Mallada boninensis, Chrysopa lacciperda, Beauveria bassiana.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>* 1 .</head><label>1</label><figDesc>The grub of this beetle causes damage as it feeds inside the stems, boring upward resulting in drying of branches and in severe cases attacked stem is killed.  Eggs are laid either in the slits of tree trunk or in the cavities in main branches and stems covered with a viscous fluid.  Pupation takes place within the stem.  Beetle emerges in July-August Control:  Cleaning the tunnel with a hard wire, pouring kerosene oil, creosote, petrol, crude oil or formalin and subsequently closing entrance of the tunnel with mud or plugging it with cotton wool soaked in any of the above substances kills the grub. Outer ply of white duplex board or bleached kraft **Or any other suitable style which provides equal strength and performance ***Outer ply to be laminated or coated for water Short title, application and commencement:-(i) These rules may be called the Fruits and Vegetables Grading and Marking Rules, 2004. (ii) They shall apply to commercial varieties of Fruits and Vegetables. (iii) They shall come into force on the date of their publication in the Official Gazette. 2. Definitions:-In these rules, unless the context otherwise requires,-(i) "Agricultural Marketing Adviser" means the Agricultural Marketing Adviser to the Government of India; (ii) "Authorised packer" means a person or a body of persons who has been granted a certificate of authorisation to grade and mark Fruits and Vegetables in accordance with the grade standards and procedure prescribed under these rules; (iii) "Certificate of Authorisation" means a certificate issued under the provisions of the General Grading and Marking Rules, 1988 authorising a person or a body of persons to grade and mark Fruits and Vegetables with the grade designation mark; (iv) "General Grading and Marking Rules" means the General Grading and Marking Rules, 1988 made under section 3 of the Agricultural Produce (Grading and Marking) Act, 1937 (1 of 1937); (v) "Grade designation" means a designation prescribed as indicative of the quality of Fruits and Vegetables; (vi) "Grade designation mark" means the "Agmark Insignia" referred to in rule 3; (vii) "Schedule" means a Schedule appended to these rules. 3. Grade designation mark.-The grade designation mark shall consist of "AGMARK insignia" consisting of a design incor-porating the certificate of authorisation number, the word "AGMARK", name of commodity and grade designation resembling the design as set out in Schedule-I. 4. Grade designation and Quality:-The grade designation and quality of Fruits and vegetables shall be as set out in Schedules II to XIX.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>(</head><label></label><figDesc>viii) Contents of package may have different fruits and vegetables of different grades as per buyer's requirements with proper labelling Cont… Method of Packing Method of Marking and Labeling (i) The grade designation mark shall be securely affixed to or printed on each package in a manner approved by the Agricultural Marketing Adviser or an officerauthorised by him in this behalf. (ii) The following particulars shall be clearly and indelibly marked on each package, namely:other particulars as may be specified by the Agricultural Marketing Adviser. (iii) The ink used for marking on packages shall be of such quality which may not contaminate the product. (iv) The authorised packer may, after obtaining the prior approval of the Agricultural Marketing Adviser, mark his private trade mark or trade brand on the graded packages provided that the same do not indicate quality other than that indicated by the grade designation mark affixed to the graded packages in accordance with these rules.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>been carefully picked and have reached an appropriate degree of development and ripeness in accordance with criteria proper to the variety and/or commercial type and to the area in which they are grown. The Development and condition of the Grapes must be such as to enable them; to withstand transport and handling, and to arrive in satisfactory condition at the place of destination.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>a loss of Rs 250 crores after the EU Countries refused to accept the consignments due to chemical residue.  The rejected grapes were alleged to have residue of chlormequat chloride (CCC), a growth hormone being used for many years by the grape growers in India. As per the new norms, 0.05 milligram per kilogram is the new permissible residue level for farmers exporting to EU countries as against the earlier limit of 1.6 mg per kg. of superior quality. They must be characteristic of the variety. They must be free of defects, with the exception of very slight superficial defects, provided these do not affect the general appearances of the produce, the quality, the keeping quality and presentation in the package. 5% by number or weight of mangoes not satisfying the requirements for the grade, but meeting those of Class I or exceptionally, coming within the tolerances of that grade. Class I Mangoes must be of good quality. They must be characteristic of the variety. Mangoes may have following slight defects, provided these do not affect the general appearance of the produce, the quality, the keeping quality and presentation in the package. -slight defects in shape; -slight skin defects due to rubbing or sunburn, suberized stains due to resin exudation (elongated trails included) and healed bruises not exceeding 2,3,4,5 sq. cm. for size groups A, B, C, D respectively 10% by number or weight of mangoes not satisfying the requirements for the grade, but meeting those of Class II grade or, exceptionally coming within the tolerances of that grade. Class II This grade includes mangoes which do not qualify for inclusion in the higher grades, but satisfy the minimum requirements. Mangoes may have following defects, provided they retain their essential characteristics as regards the quality, keeping quality and presentation. -defects in shape, -slight skin defects due to rubbing or sunburn, suberized stains due to resin exudation (elongated trails included) and healed bruises not exceeding 4,5,6,7 sq. cm. for size groups A, B, C, D respectively 10% by number or weight of mangoes not satisfying the requirements of the grade, but meeting the minimum requirements. Foot note : In Class I and Class II, scattered suberized rusty lenticels, as well as yellowing of green varieties due to exposure to direct sunlight, not exceeding 40% of the surface and not showing any signs of necrosis are allowed  The development and condition of the mangoes must be such as to enable them: To ensure a continuation of the maturation process until they reach the appropriate degree of maturity corresponding to the varietal characteristics,  To withstand transport and handling, and  To arrive in satisfactory condition at the place of destination.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Size is determined by the weight of the fruit, in accordance with the following table:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Major export mode: air  Major export target area: Middle east and Gulf countries  Uniform approach to good practices  Group certification helps small / marginal farmers  Development of farm infrastructure  Improvement in environment and soil fertility  Availability of safe and healthy food  Employment generation  Increased competitiveness (value addition</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="7,72.00,4.50,282.00,187.50" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="9,51.00,287.13,393.00,216.87" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="9,66.00,46.13,338.50,211.87" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="10,42.00,35.99,254.72,224.13" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="10,31.75,306.38,274.25,205.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="10,426.00,276.00,294.00,228.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="12,384.00,294.00,336.00,212.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="12,378.00,63.88,324.00,206.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="13,48.25,240.00,203.75,270.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="13,520.00,246.00,200.00,264.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="22,453.75,60.00,254.25,216.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="23,54.00,258.00,228.00,228.63" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="23,285.88,258.00,434.12,273.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="24,66.00,269.25,336.00,230.38" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="25,468.00,72.00,246.00,222.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="25,450.00,300.00,270.00,240.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="34,23.88,230.28,696.12,88.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="37,498.00,48.00,215.90,348.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="39,492.60,270.06,227.94,227.94" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="42,54.00,338.50,324.00,195.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="42,36.00,71.99,342.00,235.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="42,380.06,77.99,342.00,229.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="43,43.26,78.00,340.56,234.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="43,393.02,78.00,324.48,240.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="45,35.93,60.00,342.07,234.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="45,382.47,60.00,331.53,234.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="45,444.00,303.14,265.24,199.76" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="46,449.73,270.00,262.00,204.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="47,46.13,72.00,306.00,211.56" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="47,372.00,73.45,336.00,208.55" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="47,46.39,360.00,305.73,182.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="47,384.00,352.75,318.00,187.25" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="53,48.00,294.00,288.00,244.71" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="53,338.33,294.00,223.87,243.75" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="54,55.79,277.08,346.21,259.88" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="54,414.00,282.00,288.00,255.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="57,48.00,54.00,502.84,438.83" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="58,52.13,57.44,415.87,451.29" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="62,540.78,204.01,173.22,319.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="111,55.85,38.95,249.10,208.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="113,55.85,38.95,249.10,208.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="133,6.00,332.63,306.00,201.37" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="137,463.50,54.00,256.50,342.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="148,102.00,12.00,594.00,186.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="148,114.00,210.00,522.00,330.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="155,25.75,211.05,352.25,292.95" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>emergence of fruitfly starts from April onwards and the maximum population is recorded during MayJuly, which coincides with fruit maturity.  The population declines slowly from August to September after that it is non-existent up to March. Creates hindrance in export of fresh fruits.  It is a common pest of mango in southern India. Varieties with high TSS and sugar such as Alphonso, Bangalora, Neelum, etc. are more prone to attack by this pest.  Female lay eggs under the rind of ripening fruits.  Newly emerged grubs bore through the pulp, feed on seed coat and later cause damage to cotyledons. Pupation takes place inside the seed.  Pulp is discoloured around the affected portion.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Control:  Bait sprays of Carbaryl (0.2%)+protein hydrolysate (0.1%) or molasses starting at first week of April and repeated once after 21 days or hanging traps containing 100 ml water emulsion of Methyl Euginol (0.1%) + Malathion (0.1%) during fruiting is effective. Damage:  Control:  The pest population can be kept under check by destroying the affected fruits and exposing the hibernating weevils by digging the soil.  Spraying the trees with Fenthion (0.01%) is found effective.  In Alphonso and Banganapalli, a single spray of Monocrotophos 36 EC 1.5ml/litre of water at marble stage gave 100% and 97.5% control of stone weevil  Hot water treatment at 48 Cont respectively. In Totapuri, Carbaryl 50 % WDP @ 4 g/ litre</cell></row><row><cell>of water is effective in controlling stone weevil.</cell></row></table><note>o C for one hour can result in total control in Alphonso and Totapuri (IIHR, Bangalore).Fruit fly (Daccus dorsalis;, D. zonatus and D. correctus)</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>TABLE ` A'------- PROVISIONS CONCERNING SIZING Size is determined by the weight of bunches (in g) The following minimum (in g) requirements per bunch are laid down for large and small berries grapes.</head><label>`</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Grade</cell><cell>Large berries</cell><cell>Small berries</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">________________________________________________</cell></row><row><cell>Extra class</cell><cell>200</cell><cell>150</cell></row><row><cell>Class I</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>100</cell></row><row><cell>Class II</cell><cell>100</cell><cell>75</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">_________________________________________________</cell></row></table><note>SIZE TOLERANCE:Extra class, Class I, Class II : 10 % by weight of bunches not satisfying the size requirements for the grade, but meeting the size requirements for the grade immediately below.</note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0">*Outer ply of white duplex board or bleached kraft **Or any other suitable style which provides equal strength and performance</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1">Foot Note : Pigmentation due to sun is not a defect.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>State(s)</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Period of availability of grapes</head></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>(e) free of abnormal external moisture, excluding condensation following removal from cold storage;</p><p>(f) free from damage caused by low/or high temperature;</p><p>(g) free of any foreign smell and/or taste;</p><p>(h) free of damage caused by pests;</p><p>(i) sufficiently developed and display satisfactory ripeness;</p><p>(ii) When a peduncle is present, it shall not be no longer than 1.0 cm.</p><p>(iii) Mangoes shall comply with the residue levels of heavy metals, pesticides and other food safety parameters as laid down by the Codex Alimentarius Commission for exports.</p><p>How is GAP related to the Concept of Best Practices?:</p><p>Among a wide range of Good Practice Options, the "Best" practices are related to the identification of practices "more suitable" to the characteristics (environmental, social, economical etc.) of the farm and the crop growing regions. • GLOBALGAP is the fresh produce food standards set by Europe's leading Food Retailers to give their Customers more assurance of Food safety.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ICAR-Indian</head><note type="other">Agricultural</note><p>• Only Certified Growers can supply Produce to the retailers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ICAR-Indian</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agricultural</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research</head><p>Institute.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>New</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Delhi</head><p>What is GLOBALGAP ?</p><p>•  New Delhi GAP includes practices that have to be followed at the primary production, in order to ensure a Safe and wholesome product whilst also minimizing the negative impact of those practices on the Environment and on Workers' Health.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IndiaGAP Components absent in EurepGAP</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ICAR-Indian</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agricultural</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Research</head><p>Institute.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>New</head><p>Delhi</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GMP includes practices oriented to the prevention and control of hazards associated</head><p>to the fresh fruits and postharvest chain, ensuring a safe and wholesome product, whilst also minimizing the negative impact of those practices on the environment and on workers' health. Under EurepGap/ GlobalGap, there are about fifteen selected agricultural components to be adhered to which are listed below:</p><p>• Eurocert India,</p><p>• Foodcert India (p) Ltd,</p><p>• IMO Control Private Ltd,</p><p>• Control Union Inspections India Pvt Ltd,</p><p>• Skal International India and</p><p>• SGS March to May are the peak months for export of Indian grapes to the EU (70% 0f total). And, India is the only country capable of feeding the EU market in those months. Hence, both parties want to avoid a repeat of last year.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>GAP Certification Agencies in India</head><p>In 2010, Indian grape exports faced a setback, with EU reluctant to accept Indian table grape consignments as Chlormequat chloride -a plant growth regulator -was detected in excess of the prescribed maximum residue level (MRL).</p><p>In 2009, EU had come up with new regulations on pesticides, raising the chemicals to be monitored from 98 to 167. Unaware of the changed rules, Indian exporters who did not meet the new standards, faced rejection. Resellers of chemicals will be accredited and screened to ensure that chemicals are not adulterated or tainted.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Setback in Export of Fresh Grapes</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control measures</head><p>Spraying of Quinolphos 0.06% or Carbaryl WP 0.2% four days after pruning is done to control the pest. Spraying of neem cake extract (4%) is also useful. Imdiacloprid 17.8 SL @ 0.3-0.4 ml / l or Lamda cyhalothirn 5 CS @ 0.5 ml/l or Fipronil 80 WG @ 0.06 g/l.  </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Table Grapes shall be fruits obtained from varieties (cultivars) of Vitis vinifera L</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Grower&apos;s Record 4</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Seeds and Plants</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Cultural Practices 7. Transplanting</title>
				<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Crop Maturity 13. Harvesting 14. Post Harvest Handling 15. Packaging 16. Loading &amp; transport 17</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Manuring</forename><surname>Manures</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Crop Protection</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Irrigation Control Points and Compliance Criteria 10. Drainage System 11. General 18. Environmental Issues 19. Complaint Procedure</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
