<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Indian States and Capitals -GK in PDF</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Indian States and Capitals -GK in PDF</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">BCD16199993323618A9F0F92AAD07927</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Your preparation for any competitive exam, be it Railways RRB, Bank PO, Bank Clerk, LIC AAO, etc., is incomplete without having a good knowledge in Current Affairs &amp; General Knowledge. The most trivial way through which these exams put your General Knowledge to test is by asking direct questions on Indian States and Capitals. If prepared in a correct manner, they can be aced in no time whatsoever. Don't forget to download this complete list of Indian States and Capitals in PDF.</p><p>Below is given the list of capitals of the various States and Union Territories.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>STATES AND CAPITALS</head><p>With the inclusion of Telangana, India now has 29 States and 7 Union Territories. Do check out the complete list of states and capitals. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sr. No</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>UNION TERRITORIES AND CAPITALS</head><p>Union Territories are those regions that fall directly under the control of the Union Government.</p><p>Each UT has its own Lieutenant-Governor and Administrator. Only two UTs have Chief Ministers though as they have been granted partial statehood.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TRIVIA ABOUT JAMMU &amp; KASHMIR</head><p>Multiple capitals is not new thing and it is practiced all around the world. South Africa has three capitals. The state of Jammu and Kashmir has two capitals -Jammu as Winter Capital and Srinagar as summer capital. The reasons for J&amp;K having two capitals are:</p><p>• As far as the strategic location is concerned, Srinagar is the most suitable place to control the political, territorial and functional working as it is located nearly in the middle of the populated area of Jammu and Kashmir. </p></div>		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>summers.</p><p>• But in winters it becomes a geographically challenging place due to its climate with mercury falling down below zero degree.</p><p>• Moreover, in winter the active financial area is mostly the southern part of J&amp;K. While the northern part is sometimes also not accessible due to blockage of National Highway 10 as the result of landslide or other geographical activities.</p><p>• So, it becomes a compulsion both economically, functionally and geographically to move the capital from Srinagar to Jammu in winter.</p><p>If you know more about this topic that you think the article hasn't included, then comment below.</p><p>You can find details about other GK topics here: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>List of Important</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Go to Testbook Practice</head><p>Finally, if you want to suggest some another topic that we should write on, tell us on Testbook Discuss.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Go to Testbook Discuss</head></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
