<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">A9A407E1CBFBD33099EE09576A5A4435</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:42+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>MAIZE</head><p>Maize dwarf mosaic virus (MDMV) and corm stunt virus (CSV) symptoms are the appearance of faint yellowish strips on plants 6 to 7 weeks old and shortened internodes excessive tilering with many grainless ears may be observed.</p><p>Bacterial wilt or stewarts disease caused by Bacterium stewarti found especially in sweat corm.</p><p>Brown spot caused by the fungus Physooderma zeamaydis. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Small longitudinal red spots on leaves which turn grey or brown.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Reduce yield</head><p>Prevention control through:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>The use of clean seeds Wild and rank (too thickly) growth. It is wild and rank in growth habitat. E.g Chromolaena odorata, Andropogon spp. They grow rapidly, branch or tiller profusely and cover extensive areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>They are persistent and resistant to control or eradication e.g purple and yellow nutsedge (Cyperus rotundus), C. esculentus have well developed tubers and viable seeds, Imperata cylindrica has extensive rhizome systems and seeds, Bryophyllum pinnatum spreads by seed and leaf bulbil (It is resistant to dessication)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>They have high reproductive capacity. Some weeds produce large quantities of seeds e.g Amaranthus spinosus (235,00 seeds per plant)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>Ability to exhibit seed dormancy. A condition in which a seed fails to germinate in the presence of environmental condition that are normally optimal or seed germination. The forms of dormancy so exhibited by weed species include induced dormancy, enforced dormancy and innate dormancy.</p><p>Induced dormancy = inability of a mature viable seed to germinate because of an after ripening experience(exposure to high CO 2 level, hard seed coat or allelochemicals) Enforced dormancy= result of exposure of mature viable seeds to adverse environmental condition e.g low moisture or high temperature and poor aeration.</p><p>Innate dormancy= occurs if a viable mature seed fails to germinate when exposed to environmental conditions that are favorable to vegetative growth because of immature embryo or the presence of inhibitor chemicals either in the seed coat in the fruit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.</head><p>Weeds may grow in an undesirable location. They can be found in cultivated fields, tennis courts or recreational sites and cracks of concrete.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7.</head><p>Weeds have large populations. E. g Euphorbia heterophylla, Ageratum conyzoides, Aspilia africana. They are able to compeete better with crops because of this numerical superiority.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>8.</head><p>Humans often find them useless, unwanted, undesirable. Many weeds have some morphological features such as thorns, prickles etc which make them objectionable e.g Amaranthus spinosus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>9.</head><p>Spontaneous growth, appearing without being sown. Such weeds have small, obscured seeds that are buried in soil e.g Amaranthus spinosus, Talinum triangulare.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>10.</head><p>Aggresiveness: Many weeds rapid seedling growth and wide tolerance to edaphic and environmental factors. Some are very competitive and deep roots and have the ability to form canopy over associated crops e.g Euphorbia heterophylla.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>11.</head><p>Unsightly. Many weeds have unattractive flowers and foliage and tend to disfigure the landscape e.g Panicum spp,Aandropogon spp and Pennisetum spp.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Economic Importance of Weeds</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Direct Losses by weeds</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.</head><p>Weeds cause reduction in crop yield through competition for light, nutrient, water and space. They can also reduce the yield of crop through the release of toxic substances or exudates which inhibit crop growth. This is called allelopathy. Uncontrolled weed infestation can lead to 95% yield loss in cassava, 40% in maize, 53% in cowpea, soyabean and pigeon pea.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Weeds can reduce the quality of harvested agricultural products.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Weeds interfere with harvest operations and increase the cost of harvesting in both small holder and large scale farms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Weeds may poison animals e.g Amaranthus spp can adversely affect livestock because of the high nitrate content of the shoots.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>The cost of controlling weeds is high.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.</head><p>The presence of weeds can impede water flow in irrigation canals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7.</head><p>The presence of weeds in lakes and reservoir can increase loss of water by transpiration.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Indirect Losses caused by weeds 1.</head><p>Weeds serve as alternate hosts to many plant diseases and animal pests e.g insects, rodents, birds etc that attack crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>The presence of weeds imposes a limit on farm size.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>The presence of weeds can also reduce the economic value of lakes by preventing or limiting fishing activities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Weeds such as Imperata cylindrica become fire hazards in the dry season throughout the savanna vegetation zone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Non Agricultural Losses</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.</head><p>Weeds affect health of humans, stinging nettle can cause skin rashes and the flowers of some other weeds can be associated with allergies in humans 2.</p><p>Weeds impair visibility along roads and railway lines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Uncontrolled weed growth reduces the value of real estates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>In situations where farmers depend on human labour for weeding, children have to miss school at peak of weeding periods. This reduces the quality of education that these children can get during their early years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Beneficial Effects of Weeds</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.</head><p>Weeds provide a vegetative cover that protects the soil surface against erosive action of rain and wind.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Weeds play an important part in nutrient recycling. Roots of weeds tap nutrients from the lower soil depths and return these to the soil surface as litter when the weeds shed their leaves or when the entire plant plants dies and decays.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Weeds add organic matter to the soil both from the roots and from the above ground parts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Many plants that are designated weeds are used as potherbs e.g Talinum triangulare.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>Weeds are sources of pesticides e.g Chrysanthemum cinerariifolium which provides insecticide pyrethrum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.</head><p>Weeds provide food and cover for animal. Wildlife generally depend on weeds for survival as food and shelter.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7.</head><p>Weeds serve as an important source of genetic materials for crop improvement such as breeding for resistance to pests and diseases which are made possible by genetic materials provided by wild species of the crop plants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>8.</head><p>Weeds serve as hosts beneficial insects, and at the same time provide nectar for bees.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>9.</head><p>Many weeds help to beautify the landscape. E.g a good ground cover of Cynodon dactylon beautifies the home.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Classification of Weeds</head><p>Weeds can be classified based on: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Aquatic weeds e.g. water hyacinth, water lily.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Weed Control Methods</head><p>Weed control involves any action that seeks to restrict the spread of weeds and destroys or reduce their population in a given location.</p><p>Generally weeds can be controlled using the following methods:</p><p>1 </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Quarantine laws and services to prevent accidental introduction of exotic plants or their propagules.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cultural Weed Control</head><p>This involves all aspect of good crop husbandry used by farmer to minimize weed interference with crop or any practice adopted by the farmers which aid in weed suppression. This method include:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Hand weeding. This can be done by using hand pulling, hand hoeing, handslashing or push type weeders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Mechanical weeding: This can be done with animal drawn weeders or machine-powered weeders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ  Tillage</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ  Burning</head><p>п‚·пЂ  Flooding</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ  Mulching</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Crop rotation</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Biological Weed Control</head><p>This refers to the control or suppression of weeds by the action of one or more organisms through natural means or by manipulation of the weed, organism or environment. This involves the use of the following:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Live mulch: This is a crop production system in which a food crop is planted directly in the living cover of an established cover crop without destruction of the fallow vegetation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Biological control with invetebrate animals e.g the use of insects to control weeds; use of cactoblastis moth on Opuntia (Prickly pear) in India; the use of grasshoppers(Paulina acuminata) to control Salvinia molesta in Zambia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Biological control with vertebrate animal e.g. goats to graze down woody weeds; ducks and fish for control of aquatic weeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Microbial weed control . This involves the use of microorganisms such as fungi, bacterial, bacteria, nematodes and viruses. E.g. of microbial weed control is the use of soil borne fungi ( Phytophthora palmivora) now sold as mycoherbicides -sevine to control strangler vine (Morrenia odorata). Mycoherbicides is the use of plant pathogens to control weeds. The use of aerial fungus Collectotrichum gloeosporoides (sold as mycoherbicides-collego) for the control northernjointvetch in paddy rice.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Allelopathy; This is the detrimental effect of chemical or exudates produced by one living plant species on the germination, growth or development of another plant species, or microorganisms sharing the same habitat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>п‚·пЂ </head><p>Plant canopy: The major effect of plant canopy is to shade the understorey plants and limit their ability to synthesize carbohydrates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical Weed Control</head><p>The practice whereby undesirable vegetation (weeds) is killed with herbicide is called chemical weed control A chemical used to control,suppress or kill plants or to severely interrupt their normal growth process is called herbicides.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Herbicides can be selective or non-selective</head><p>Selective herbicides are those that have the ability to suppress certain member of weeds species and leave others unhurt. Eg. Atrazine, propanil, dalapon etc Non selective herbicides are those that are generally toxic to all plants (they destroy any weeds that come their way) e.g glyphosate, paraquat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integrated Weed Management</head><p>This is a form of weed management that involves the combination of two or more weed control methods at low inputs to obtain a level of weed suppression superior to the ordinarily obtained when one weed management system is used. e.g.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical +cultural method</head><p>Herbicide + organic mulch Biological +Chemical +Cultural method</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Morphology of weedsThe criterion defines classification on the basis of leaf shape.(a)Grasses: the leaf lamina in relation to the breadth is very high e.g Panicum maximum, Andropogon gayanus, Eleusine indica (b) Broadleaves: the ratio of leaf lamina to the breadth is smaller e.g Sida acuta, Talinum triangulare, Euphorbia heterophylla, Ageratum conyzoides (c) Sedges : all the leaves tend to arise from the same point e.g Cyperus rotundus, Cyperus esculentus, Mariscus alternifolius. Classification based on Life cycle п‚·пЂ  Ephemerals e.g Euphorbia, Digitaria, Eluesine, Spigelia anthelmia. п‚·пЂ  Annuals e.g. Pennisettum spp, Rottboelia cochinchinensis, п‚·пЂ  Biennial e.g Taraxacum officinale п‚·пЂ  Perennials e.g Imperata cylindrica, Sida acuta. Classification based on Growth habit п‚·пЂ  Free living weeds e.g Siam weed п‚·пЂ  Parasitic weeds e.g Sriga spp Classification based on Habitat п‚·пЂ  Terrestrial weeds or upland weeds e.g Imperata cylindrica, Euphorbia heterophylla.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>A weed is a plant out of place or a plant growing where it is not wanted. A plant is regarded as a weed either because it interferes with human activity / welfare or because it occurs spontaneously in humandisturbed habitats. Weeds are generally undesirable and may be prolific, persistent, competitive, harmful or even poisonous.Characteristics of Weeds 1.It is harmful to humans, animals and crops. It may contain poisonous alkaloids e.g leaves of stinging nettle (Fleurya aestuans), pods of Mucuna pruriens, high level of nitrates in Amaranthus is poisonous to animal, parasitic crop (Striga spp) 2.</figDesc><table><row><cell>п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Use disease free stem Crop rotation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Symptoms include: Farm sanitation п‚·пЂ  Use resistant varieties</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Galling of roots</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">(2) п‚·пЂ  WEEDS AND THEIR CONTROL Leaf blight of cassava caused by a bacterium called Xanthosomonas manihotis Retarded growth Definition of a Weed:</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Symptoms include п‚·пЂ  Early death of plant</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Wilting of plant Reduction in yield</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Prevention and control by: Falling off of leaves</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Reduced yield Soil sterilization</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Canker of stem -die back of stem Crop rotation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Prevention and Control п‚·пЂ  Use resistant varieties</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Use resistant varieties Uproot and burn infected plants</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Avoid heavy use of N fertilizers Use disease-free cuttings</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ  Disease of Tomato Use resistant varieties Early planting</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Bacteria wilt (Pseudomonas solanacerus) Practice crop rotation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Collar rot (Sclerotium rolfsii)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Cocoa Black Pod Disease Early blight (Acternaria solani)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Grey leaf spot (Stemphiflium solani) Caused by fungus Phytophithora palmivora</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Symptoms include Late blight (Phytophtora infestions)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Leaf mould (Cladosporium fulvum) Brown spot on pod</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Septoriia leaf spot (Septoria lycopersici) Rottening of pods</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Target leaf spot (Corynespora cassicola) Entire pod turns black</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ  Tomato wilt (Fugarium oxyporum) Low yield Mosaic pattern on leaves Cowpea</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Prevention and control measures Leaf spot of cowpea caused by a fungus Cercopora Stem/leaf distortion п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ  Remove and destroy infected pods Symptoms include: Stunted plant п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ  Regular weeding п‚·пЂ  Reddish brown spot on leaves Reduction in yield п‚·пЂ  Spray with fungicides e.g. Bordeaux mixture п‚·пЂ  Lesion on leaves</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Prevention and control by п‚·пЂ  Avoid overcrowding of cocoa plants. п‚·пЂ  Chlorosis</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ  п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Use of resistant varieties Dropping of leaves</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Tomato Prevention and control by Uproot and burn infected plants</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">п‚·пЂ  Root knot of tomato caused by: Spray insecticides to kill vector п‚·пЂ  Nematode, it is soil borne п‚·пЂ  Spray with fungicides</cell></row></table><note>(ii) Seedling blight caused by Sclerotium rolfii (iii) Brown leaf spot caused by Helminthosporium oryzae (vi) Rice blast (or rotten neck) caused by Piriicularia oryzae (vi) Stem rot caused by the fungus Magraparthe salvinii Cassava (i)Cassava mosaic disease caused by a virus transmitted by piercing and sucking insect (whitefly) Bemisia nigerrensis with system which include:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Preventive weed control refers those measures necessary to prevent the introduction of new weed species into a given geographical area as well as the multiplication and spread of existing weed species.</figDesc><table><row><cell>.</cell><cell>Preventive Weed control</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Cultural Weed control</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell>Biological Weed control</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Chemical Weed control</cell></row><row><cell>5.</cell><cell>Integrated Weed control</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Preventive Weed control</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Preventive weed control includes the following:</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Use of clean crop seeds for planting</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Fallowing</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Preventing weeds from setting seeds</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Use of clean machinery</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Controlled movement of livestock</cell></row><row><cell>п‚·пЂ </cell><cell>Screening of irrigated canals to prevent weeds from being transported from infested field to</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">clean areas</cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
