<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">PESTS AND SAFE USE OF PESTICIDES DEPARTMENT OF ENTOMOLOGY COLLEGE OF AGRICULTURE CSK HIMACHAL PRADESH KRISHI VISHVAVIDYALAYA PALAMPUR176 062, HP PREFACE</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">D</forename><forename type="middle">C</forename><surname>Sharma</surname></persName>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">PESTS AND SAFE USE OF PESTICIDES DEPARTMENT OF ENTOMOLOGY COLLEGE OF AGRICULTURE CSK HIMACHAL PRADESH KRISHI VISHVAVIDYALAYA PALAMPUR176 062, HP PREFACE</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">D45F909C795FF5FF0551A9D789C5B98B</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:43+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Pests and diseases destroy upto one third of the crops during growth, harvest and storage. Pesticides are invaluable inputs for increasing agricultural production in order to reduce losses caused by pests and diseases. Besides, these chemicals are indispensable for the successful control of vectors of human and animal diseases. In India, the consumption of pesticides has shown a rapid increase during the past decades. However, the rapidly increasing usage of pesticides, often with insufficient technical advice has resulted in many hazards and environmental problems inimical to the interest of man.</p><p>All the pesticides are poisonous and during field application, farmers and spray operators are exposed to them, thus putting their health and safety at risk. They also do not take enough care, may be because of their unawareness to the safety precautions required or they do not give adequate importance to them. While use of pesticides is necessary to protect the crops, it is rather essential to have caution and precautions for their use. Safe and judicious use of pesticides is one of the measures to minimize the risk of exposure to them and check the environment related problems.</p><p>Therefore, it is necessary that pesticides should be used judiciously by taking care to ensure the safety of the people who use them. The purpose of this practical manual on 'Pests and safe use of pesticides' is to serve as a field guide for students, fields functionaries, farmers and spray operators.</p><p>The manual provides basic knowledge on different types of pests, pesticides and their safe &amp; judicious use right from the purchase to the field application. To make reference easy, the manual is divided into eight chapters having an important aspect in each part.</p><p>We are grateful to Dr. K.K. Katoch, Hon'ble ViceChancellor and Dr. S.P. Sharma, Director of Research for their constant encouragement and invaluable guidance. We express our special gratitude to Dr. P.K. Sharma, Dean, College of Agriculture for providing us the financial assistance under the Central Development Assistance (ICAR) for publication of this manual. Thanks are due to various sources from where different materials were used to compile this information with significant input.</p><p>The authors are also grateful to the faculty members of Department of Entomology, CSK Himachal Pradesh Krishi Vishvavidyalaya, Palampur for providing their valuable inputs during the preparation of this manual. The computer assistance rendered by Sh. Baljit Singh is duly acknowledged.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CONTENTS</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>PRINCIPLES OF PEST MANAGEMENT</head><p>The term 'Pest' is commonly used very broadly to insects.</p><p>A pest is any organism that:</p><p>q Competes with humans, domestic animals or desirable plants for food or water q Injures humans, animals, desirable plants, structures or possessions q Spreads diseases to humans, domestic animals, wild life or desirable plants</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Types of pests q</head><p>Insects such as cockroaches, termites, mosquitoes, aphids, beetles, fleas and caterpillars q Insectlike organisms, such as mites, ticks and spiders q Microbial organisms such as bacteria, 'fungi' nematodes, viruses, protozoans and mycoplasmas.</p><p>q Noxious plants such as weeds etc.</p><p>q Molluscs such as snails and slugs q Vertebrates such as rats, mice, birds, bats, fish, snakes and wild animals Most organisms are not pests. A species may be a pest in some situations and not in others. An organism should not be considered a pest until it is proven to be one. An insect reaches the status of a pest when its number increases and inflicts significant damage. Pests are also classified in various categories on different basis.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. Classification based on morphological difference</head><p>i. Insect pest: Generally, insects have three body regions namely head, thorax and abdomen.</p><p>They also have one or two pairs of wings. They multiply rapidly and buildup a huge population causing economic loss to crops and other properties, or it's a nuisance and health hazard to man and his livestock, e.g. grasshoppers, whiteflies.</p><p>ii. Mite pest: Mites are not actually insects but these insect -like creatures belong to the related class Arachnida, which also includes spiders, scorpions and ticks. They cause considerable injury to plant and animals. Morphologically, they have two body regions, head and abdomen and possess four pairs of legs. The body of mite is divided into two regions -a front partcalled cephalothorax (or prosoma) and a hind part called the abdomen (or opisthosoma) or obvious constriction between these parts and superficially the body appears undivided. Adult mites possess the usual arachnid appendages, chelicerae (jaws) and palps (a pair of appendages) at the front end and four pairs of legs, e.g. red spider mite.</p><p>iii. Nematodes: Several crop diseases are caused by plant parasitic nematodes. They are usually small in size, e.g. Meloidogyne sp. causing root galls.</p><p>iv. Vertebrate pest: Vertebrate pests include animals such as wild pig, monkeys, bear, elephant, deer, rodents and birds. They cause huge damage to the crops.</p><p>v. Molluscs: These include slugs and snails. They feed on leaves of the plants.</p><p>vi. Pathogen pests: Pathogens are those microbial organisms like bacteria, viruses, fungi, protozoans, rickettsia etc. that cause disease or physiological disturbance to plants.</p><p>vii. Weeds and parasitic plants: Weeds are unwanted plants in field that compete with the crop plants for water, nutrient, light and space, e.g. Echinochloa species in rice field. Many parasitic plants depend on the host trees for their growth and reproduction; e.g. Loranthus -found in citrus, peach trees; Striga sp. in maize and sorghum plants. In order to arrive at a definite and predictable concept, different categories of pest are defined in terms of the general equilibrium position (GEP), the economic injury level (EIL) and the damage boundary (DB).</p><p>GEP: General equilibrium position is the mean value of pest density around which the pest population tends to fluctuate as changes occur in the biotic and abiotic components of the environment without accompanied by a permanent modification in the composition of the environment. A permanent modification of any component of the environment may alter the GEP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Damage Boundary (DB):</head><p>The lowest level of injury where the damage can be measured is called damage boundary.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Economic Injury level (EIL):</head><p>The lowest number of insects that will cause economic damage is referred to as Economy injury level.</p><p>Economic damage: Amount of injury which will justify the cost of artificial conrol measures.</p><p>a. Negligible pest: Those pests that cause less than 5% loss in yield. The GEP in case of negligible pest lies below both EIL and DB. The population never increases high enough to cause economic injury (Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>).</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref> Negligible pest b. Minor pest: Those insectpests which normally cause a loss ranging from 5 to 10%. Here the GEP lies below both EIL and DB (Fig. <ref type="figure">2</ref>). Under favorable environmental conditions, the population may cross EIL and DB for usually a short interval. These pests are easily controlled by single application of insecticides, e.g. rice hispa, Dicladispa armigera.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 2 Minor pest c. Major pest:</head><p>Those pests which cause a loss of 10% or more in general, The GEP is close to the EIL and in some case both may essentially be at the same level (Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref>). Thus the population crosses EIL frequently and repeated control measures are necessary but economic damage is avoided by timely interventions, e.g. rice brown planthopper, Nilparvata lugens; leafhopper, Nephotettix sp.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">3</ref> Major pest d. Key pest: These are the most severe and damaging pests. The GEP lies well above DB and EIL (Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref>). Human intervention in the form of control measures may bring the population tempo rarily below the EIL but it rises back rapidly and repeated interventions (sprays) may be required to minimize damage. These pests present a persistent and perennial threat to our crops and are not bring satisfactorily controlled with the available technology. There is need to lower their GEP below EIL by permanent modification of one or more components of the environment, e.g. cotton bollworm, Helicoverpa armigera and diamondback moth, Plutella xylostella.</p><p>Fig. <ref type="figure">4</ref> Key pest e. Regular pest: These pests which occur most frequently (regularly) in a crop and have close association with that particular crop. The GEP of regular pest lies above EIL and DB and intervention is necessary at regular pest appearance, e.g. brinjal shoot and fruit borer, Leucinodes orbonalis and chilli thrips. f. Seasonal pest: Occurs mostly during a particular part of the year, and usually the incidence is governed by climatic conditions. The GEP lies above DB and EIL and during that particular season and human intervention in the form of control measures should be done, e.g: red hairy caterpillar on groundnut (June July) and rice grasshoppers (June July).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 6 Seasonal pest</head><p>g. Occasional pest: Occasionally their density reaches EIL when their population is affected by unusual weather conditions or the injudicious use of insecticides. At their peaks of population density some sort of intervention usually an insecticide is required to reduce their number to tolerable level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 7 Occasional pest</head><p>h. Sporadic pest: The population of these pests is usually negligible but in certain years under favorable environmental conditions, they appear in a visually epidemic form, crossing many times over DB and EIL (Fig. <ref type="figure">8</ref>). Under these conditions, the pest has to be controlled by undertaking suitable management strategies. These pests are highly sensitive to abiotic conditions and once the favorable season is over, only a residual population survives, e.g. white grubs, Brahmina coriacea, Holotrichia sp. and cut worm, Agrotis ipsilon.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Fig. 8 Sporadic pest</head><p>i. Potential pest: These insects are permanently not causing any economic damage and therefore, as such should not be labeled as pests. Their GEP lies below the DB and does not cross EIL even under favorable condition. Any change (cropping pattern, cultural practices) in the ecosystem may, however, push their GEP higher and there is a danger of economic damage from these pests if control operations against the other categories of pests are undertaken in an indiscriminate manner, e.g. Spodoptera litura on cotton and sunflower and armyworm on wheat are presently potential pests. k. Epidemic pest: These are those pests which occur in a region or locality at a particular season or time only, e.g. rice hispa, Dicladispa armigera and rice leaf roller, Cnaphalocrocis medinalis.</p><p>l. Endemic pest: Those pests which occur regularly and confined mostly to a particular area or locality, e.g. red hairy caterpillar, Amsacta albistriga or stem borer of rice.</p><p>m. Perennial pest: EILs are slightly above the GEP and intervention is necessary at nearly every upward population fluctuation. The general practice is to intervene with insecticides whenever necessary to produce a modified average population density well below the EIL. Resurgence of sucking pests q Indiscriminate use of pesticides In man's struggle against pests, one must take several steps prior to choosing a strategy of pest management: q Identify the pest q Know what control methods are available q Evaluate the benefits and risks of control methods q Recognize when direct action such as a pesticide application is necessary q Choose the methods that are most effective but cause the least harm to living fauna and the environment q Know the correct use of the control methods q Use each tactic correctly in the strategy q Observe local, state and central regulations that apply to the situations q Evaluate the strategy and make adjustment as necessary</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pest management strategies</head><p>Any time when you are considering whether pest management is necessary, remember that: q Control a pest only when it is causing or expected to cause more harm than is reasonable to accept q Use a tactic or combination of tactics that will reduce pest numbers to an acceptable level q Cause as little harm as possible to everything except the pest Because even though a pest is present, it may not do much harm. It could cost more to manage the pest than would be lost because of the damage by the pest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pest management goals</head><p>Whenever you manage a pest, you need to achieve one or a combination or three goals: i) Prevention: Keeping a pest away from becoming a problem.</p><p>ii) Suppression: Reducing pest numbers or damage to an acceptable level.</p><p>iii) Eradication: Destroying an entire pest population.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integrated pest management (IPM)</head><p>Integrated pest management is the use of all appropriate and economic strategies to manage pests and their damage to acceptable levels with the least disruption to the environment. Relying only on pesticides for pest control can cause pests to develop resistance to pesticides and may cause outbreaks of other pests. IPM provides the applicator with a diverse pest management programme that avoids sole reliance on one technique and its potential shortcomings.</p><p>According to FAO, Integrated pest management may be defined as "a system that in the context of the associated environment and the population dynamics of pest species, utilizes all suitable techniques and methods in as compatible a manner as possible and maintains the pest population at levels below those causing economic injury". Integrated pest management is based on ecological principles and involves the integration and synthesis of different components/control tactics into a pest management system.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Advantages of IPM</head><p>q More efficient and cheaper method of control q Does not upset the balance in nature q Considerably delays the development of resistance q Minimizes residue hazards of pesticides considerably</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>What IPM involves</head><p>A) Pest monitoring: Regular monitoring can be helpful in following ways: q What kinds of pests are present? q Are the numbers large enough to do damage and to warrant control measures? q Is natural control present and working? q When is the appropriate time to initiate control measures? q Have management efforts successfully reduced the number of pests? B) Pest identification: Correct identification is necessary for an effective pest management programme.</p><p>Never attempt a pest control programme until the pest has been correctly identified. The more you know about the pest and factors that influence its development and spread, pest management will be the easier, more cost effective and more successful. Correct identification of a pest allows determining basic information about it, including its life cycle, what stage is most destructive and when it is most susceptible to being controlled. To be able to identify and manage pests, there is need to know:</p><p>q</p><p>The physical features of the pests q Characteristics of the damage they cause q Their development and biology q What is the pest management goal ?</p><p>C) Threshold levels: Thresholds are the levels of pest populations at which pest management action should be initiated to prevent the pests from causing unacceptable damage. The threshold often is set at the level where the economic losses caused by pest damage would be greater than the cost of controlling the pests which sometimes are called 'economic thresholds'.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D) Techniques used in pest management</head><p>a) Natural control: Some natural forces act on all organisms, causing their populations to rise and fall which act independently of humans and may either help or hinder pest control. Natural forces that affect pest populations include climate, natural enemies, natural barriers, availability of shelter, food and water supplies.</p><p>b) Applied control: Unfortunately, natural control often does not check pests quickly or completely enough to prevent acceptable injury or damage, then other management measures given below must be adopted:</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">q Physical control q Cultural control q Host plant resistance q Mechanical control q Biological control q Legislative control q Chemical control</formula><p>Physical control: Light, heat and refrigeration can alter the environment enough to suppress or eradicate some pest populations. Altering the amount of water including humidity can control some pests.</p><p>Cultural control: Cultural practices are used to reduce the numbers of pests that attack cultivated plants. These practices alter the environment, the condition of the host plant or the behaviour of the pest to prevent or suppress an infestation. They disrupt the normal relationship between the pest and the host plant and make the pest less likely to survive, grow or reproduce.</p><p>Common cultural practices include the crop rotation, tillage, varying time of sowing or planting or harvesting, planting trap crops, adjusting row width, pruning, thinning, irrigating and fertilizing the plants. Sanitation practices help to prevent and suppress some pests by removing the pests themselves or their sources of food and shelter. Urban and industrial pests can be reduced drastically by improving cleanliness, eliminating pest' hiding places and increasing the frequency of garbage pickup. Carryover of agricultural pests from one planting to the next can be reduced by crop residue management or crop rotation. Other forms of sanitation that helps to prevent pest spread include using pestfree seeds or seedlings and decontaminating equipments, animals and other possible carriers before allowing them to enter a pestfree area or leave an infested area. The proper design of food handling areas can reduce access and shelter for many pests.</p><p>Host plant resistance: Some plants, animals and structures resist pests better than others. Use of resistant types, when available, helps keep pest populations below harmful levels by making conditions less favourable for the pests. Host plant resistance works in three main ways:</p><p>1. Chemicals in the host plant repel the pest or prevent the pest from completing its life cycle.</p><p>2. The host plant is more vigorous or tolerant than other varieties and thus less likely to be seriously damaged by pest attacks.</p><p>3. The host plant has physical characteristics that make it more difficult to attack.</p><p>Mechanical control: includes the use of devices and machines to control the pests. These techniques are sometimes used to prevent the spread of pests into an area or to remove pests from an area, e.g. traps, screens, barriers, fences, nets, radiation and electricity etc.</p><p>Biological control: Biological control involves the use of natural enemies such as parasitoids, predators and pathogens. There is always a time lag between pest population increase and the corresponding increase in natural enemies which can be supplemented by releasing more of a pest's enemies into the target area or by introducing new enemies that were not in the area before. Biological control also includes methods by which the pest is biologically altered, as in the production and release of large numbers of sterile males, and the use of pheromones or juvenile hormones.</p><p>Chemical control: Chemical control includes naturally derived or synthetic chemicals called pesticides that kill, repel, attract, sterilize or otherwise interfere with the normal behavour of pests. These are:</p><p>q Stomach poisons q Contact poisons q Fumigants q Attractants or baits q Repellents q Antifeedants q Insect growth regulars (IGR)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E) Evaluation and recordkeeping</head><p>It is extremely important to evaluate the results of pest management programmes. This can be done in several ways such as monitoring pest population or infestation before and after treatment, comparative damage ratings etc. Take note of the conditions during pest management activities such as timings, pest numbers, temperature and any other factor that may influence the outcome of these efforts. Record the results from evaluation for further reference.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CHAPTER2 INTRODUCTION TO PESTICIDES</head><p>Pesticides are substances or mixture of substances which intend to prevent, destroy, repel or mitigate the pests. It is a broad term representing many types of chemicals used for pest control. Pesticides are classified according to a number of functions (e.g. growth regulator, defoliant); pests managed (e.g. insecticide, rodenticide); mode of action (e.g. sterilant, stomach poison); application techniques (foliar or soil) etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>What is an insecticide?</head><p>An insecticide may be defined as a substance or a mixture of substances that may be used to kill or otherwise control any unwanted insect species. As the term control does not necessarily imply killing, chemicals such as attractants, repellents, growth as well as fertility regulators which may bring about physiological disorders in insect pests are also to be considered in the category of insecticides.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nomenclature of insecticides</head><p>A single insecticide may be coded in a variety of ways and usually has several synonymous trade and chemical names. It is, however, usual to refer them according to their chemical or common or generic names.</p><p>Common or generic names are assigned by organizations such as International Standards Organization, British Standards Institution, Entomological Society of America, Japan, Ministry of Agriculture and Forestry and USA Standards Institution. Such names start with an initial small letter (e.g. cypermethrin) whereas, manufacturer's name or proprietary name or trade name and the manufacturer's code number starts with an initial capital letter (e.g. Ripcord/NRDC 149).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Classification of insecticides</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I. Based on the chemical nature</head><p>A. Inorganic insecticides: comprise compounds of mineral origin and elemental sulphur. This group includes arsenate and fluorine compounds as insecticides, sulphur as acaricide and zinc phosphide as rodenticide.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Organic insecticides:</head><p>1. Insecticides of animal origin: Nereistoxin isolated from marine annelids, fish oil resin soap from fishes etc.</p><p>2. Plant origin insecticides or botanical insecticides: nicotinoids, pyrethroids, rotenoids etc.</p><p>3. Synthetic organic insecticides: Organochlorines, Organophosphorous, Carbamate insecticides etc.</p><p>4. Neonicotinoids etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Major groups of insecticides:</head><p>A. Inorganic insecticides</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Arsenic compounds</head><p>In an arsenical compound, the total arsenic content and the water soluble arsenic content are of importance, the water solubility of arsenic may result in entering the foliage and causing burning injury to plants, and hence water insoluble compounds are preferred for insect control. Arsenates are more stable and safe for application on plants then arsenites. Arsenites are mainly used in poison baits since they are phytotoxic. However, arsenates are less toxic to insects then arsenites.</p><p>Examples: Calcium arsenate, lead arsenate.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Flourine compounds</head><p>These compounds were in use since 1890. They are principally stomach poisons and to a limited extent contact poisons. The kill is more rapid than that of arsenicals. Their insecticidal properties are related to the fluorine content and solubility in the digestive juices of insect, e.g. Sodium fluoride.</p><p>Other inorganic compounds: Sulphur, lime sulphur.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Organic insecticides</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Insecticides of plant origin</head><p>The insecticides of plant origin extracted from seeds, flowers, leaves, stem and roots, are termed as botanical insecticides. Insecticides of plant origin unlike synthetic organic insecticides are safer to use but since they are expensive and lack residual toxicity, their use has been limited. Examples: neem (Azadirachta indica), nicotine, rotenone, Plumbagin, pyrethrum etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Synthetic organic insecticides</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organochlorines (Chlorinated hydrocarbons)</head><p>The plant protection in India owes its growth to the chemicals under this group which have revolutionized the control of pests. The properties which have lead to their extensive use are high insecticidal efficacy, long residual action, wide range of insect susceptibility, cheapness per unit area and available in different formulations. They are also known as chlorinated hydrocarbons.</p><p>The important organochlorines are DDT, hexa chloro cyclohexane (HCH).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cyclodienes</head><p>Cyclodienes also act as neurotoxicants. The outstanding characteristic of the cyclodienes is their longer stability in the soil, resulting in more control of soil inhabiting insect pests. Some of the compounds belonging to this group are chlordane, aldrin and dieldrin, heptachlor, endrin, mirex and endosulfan. Among them aldrin, chlordane and heptachlor were often in use for termite control as they are most effective, long lasting and economical insecticides but now banned by Government of India. Endosulfan has also been banned by the Supreme Court of India w.e.f. 13.5.2011 for production, use and sale all over India till further orders.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Organophosphates</head><p>Organophosphates </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E) Phenyl pyrazoles (Fiproles): These include</head><p>Fipronil: GABA receptor is the target site for fipronil. Blockage of GABA gated chloride channel reduces neuronal inhibition which leads to hyperexcitation of the central nervous system, convulsions and death of the target pest. Broad spectrum systemic insecticide with contact and stomach poison activity. Used as a foliar application against stem borer, leaf miner, hoppers, root worm and mites. Formulations: 0.3 G, 5 SC (Regent, Front line, Zoom, Bilgran).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F) Macrocyclic lactones: These insecticides include</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Spinosyns Spinosad</head><p>The extract of the fermentation broth that contains spinosad is produced by the microorganism, Saccharopolyspora spinosa. The primary components are spinosyn A and spinosyn D. Spinosad kills insects by causing rapid excitation by activation of nicotinic acetylcholine receptors of the insect nervous system, leading to involuntary muscle contractions, prostration with tremors, and paralysis. It also effects GABA receptor functioning. Spinosad is a contact and stomach poison with some translaminar movement in leaf tissue. LD 50 value: 3738 mg/kg. Formulations: 45 SC, 2.5 SC (Tracer, Spintor, Precise, Success, Laser, Caribstar and Conserve).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Avermectins</head><p>Avermectins form a new class of compounds having nematicidal, miticidal and insecticidal activity. These are produced by the soil microorganism, Streptomyces avermitilis. Avermectins activate the GABA gated chloride channel, causing an inhibitory effect, which, when excessive, results in the insect's death. This channel normally blocks reactions in some nerves, preventing excess stimulation of CNS. Emamectin benzoate and abamectin are the two major compounds in this group which are contact and stomach poisons. a) Emamectin benzoate: It is nonsystemic insecticide which penetrates by translaminar movement and effective against Lepidopterous pests. It has low toxicity to nontarget organisms. LD 50 value: 300 mg/kg. Formulation: 5 SG (Proclaim). b) Abamectin: It is a broad spectrum insecticide acting on mites of Tetranychidae, Eriophyidae and Tarsonemidae families. It is also effective against tobacco hornworm, diamondback moth, tobacco budworm, serpentine leaf miner and less potent against certain Homoptera (aphids) and Lepidoptera. It is less toxic to beneficial arthropods. Formulations: 1.8 EC (Avid, Agrimec, Vertimec, Affirm and Avert).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>G) Oxadiazines:</head><p>Indoxacarb: Indoxacarb works by inhibiting sodium ion entry into nerve cells, resulting in paralysis and death of targeted pests. Indoxacarb is a stomach poison with slight contact action. Indoxacarb affects insects from direct exposure and through ingestion of treated foliage/fruit. Once indoxacarb is absorbed or ingested, feeding cessation occurs almost immediately. It kills by binding to a site on sodium channels and blocking the flow of sodium ions into nerve cells. This results in impaired nerve function, feeding cessation, paralysis, and death. Formulations: 14.5 SC, 30 WDG (Avaunt, Steward, Torando).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>H) Thiourea derivatives:</head><p>Diafenthiuron is new type of thiourea derivative which acts specially on sucking pests such as mites, whiteflies and aphids. Diafenthiuron is photochemically converted within a few hours in sunlight to its carbodiimide derivative which is much more powerful acaricide/insecticide than diafenthiuron. It is an inhibitor of oxidative phosphorylation via distruption of ATP formation (inhibitor of ATP synthase). It acts as acaricidecuminsecticide as a foliar spray against mites, sucking pests and lepidopteran insect pests. LD 50 value: 2068 mg/kg. Formulation: 50 WP (Polo).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I) Pyridine azomethines:</head><p>Pymetrozine is a new insecticide, highly active and specific against sucking insect pests. Pymetrozine is the only representative of the pyridine azomethine. It has high degree of selectivity, low mammalian toxicity and safety to birds, fish and nontarget arthropods. On insertion of the stylets of sucking insects into the pymetrozine treated plant tissues, stylets are almost immediately blocked. The sucking insects die by starvation a few days later (feeding depressant). LD 50 value: 5693 mg/kg. Formulation: 50 WDG (Fullfill, Chess). Ketoenols act as insecticide and acaricides against all developmental stages and is a valuable new tool in the resistance management. They are tetronic acid insecticides with acaricidal action. Their mode of action is to inhibit lipogenesis in treated insects, resulting in decreased lipid contents, growth inhibition of younger insects, and reduced ability of adult insects to reproduce. Examples:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>J) Pyrroles</head><p>1. Spiromesifen: Spiromesifen is a lipid biosynthesis inhibitor and interferes with the spidermite and whitefly lipogenesis by preventing biosynthesis of fatty acids and their subsequent biochemical derivatives. Effective against whitefly, spider mites and psyllids. It is is particularly active against juvenile stages. However, it also strongly affects fecundity of mite and whitefly adults by transovariole effects.</p><p>LD 50 value: &gt;2000 mg/kg Formulations: 22.9 SC, 4 F Trade names: Oberon, Forbid</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Spirodiclofen:</head><p>Spirodiclofen is a tetronic acid with acaricidal action. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Cyantraniliprole:</head><p>Cyantraniliprole is another diamide efficacious against a cross spectrum of chewing and sucking pests. It works as toxicant in ingestion orally and has systemic activity. It targets and disrupts Ca 2+ balance in nervous system. It is formulated as OD (Oil dispersion) and SC (suspension concentrate) and generally applied @ 10100 g a.i/ha; Trade name: Cyazypyr.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Flubendiamide:</head><p>It is a new insecticide and acts by ingestion. It disrupts Ca 2+ balance in the nervous system resulting in rapid cessation of feeding and has extended residual control of important lepidopteran pests.</p><p>Formulations: 20 WG, 480 SC Trade names: Fame, Belt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>N) Synthetic pyrethroids</head><p>Synthetic pyrethroids have got the properties of plant derivative pyrethrum as insecticides but are considerably more stable in light and air. Allethrin was first synthetic analogue of pyrethroids. The synthetic pyrethroids have extremely high insecticidal activity at extremely low doses and are bio degradable in nature. Their activity is most pronounced against lepidopterous pests and they are very effective against beetle, leaf miner and bugs. They are very effective against eggs, larval and adult stages of insects. They have antifeedant and repellent properties. They are not readily washed off from the plants by rain due to lipophilic characters. These synthetic pyrethroids are very less toxic to mammals, have a quick knock down activity to insects, lower toxicity to mammals and increased safety for the user.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations q</head><p>A major limitation of synthetic pyrethroids is that these are generally not effective as soil insecticide q Even at low dosages kill nontarget species q Synthetic pyrethroids cause resurgence of several groups of insect pests especially whiteflies and aphids q Rapid development of resistance to synthetic pyrethroids in many insect species. This may be due to high selection pressure exerted by high mortality caused by synthetic pyrethroids q Synthetic pyrethroids are poor acaricides</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Generations of synthetic pyrethroids</head><p>First generation: First generation pyrethroids are considered to be of low toxicity to mammals because they are rapidly broken down in the body. First generation pyrethroids decompose quickly in sunlight and air and thus pose little risk in the environment but all pyrethroids are toxic to aquatic animals, e.g. allethrin.</p><p>Second generation: Second generation pyrethroids are not acutely toxic to mammals. These pyrethroids decompose rapidly in sunlight. They pose little threat to the environment, but for the same reason they are not suitable for agricultural use, e.g. resmethrin, bioresmethrin, bioallethrin (dtrans -allethrin).</p><p>Third generation: Third generation pyrethroids do not decompose in sunlight and contain some of the most powerful insecticides known. Third generation pyrethoids are not highly toxic to mammals mainly because they decompose rapidly in the body, e.g. fenvalerate, permethrin.</p><p>Fourth generation: Offer the most resistance to exposure to sunlight and air and, therefore, are more persistent. This group is more toxic than other pyrethroids and therefore, requires more care in use. More stable in the environment, e.g. cyhalothrin, cyfluthrin, cypermethrin, fenpropathrin, flucythrinate, decamethrin (deltamethrin), fluvalinate, fenfluthrin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II. Based on the mode of entry of the insecticides into the body of the insect i) Contact poisons:</head><p>These insecticides are capable of gaining entry into the insect body either through spiracles and trachea or through the cuticle itself. Hence, these poisons can kill the insects by mere coming in contact with the body of the insects, e.g. DDT and HCH.</p><p>ii) Stomach poisons: The insecticides are applied on the leaves and other parts of plants. When ingested, act on the digestive system of the insect and bring about the kill of the insect, e.g. Calcium arsenate, lead arsenate.</p><p>iii) Fumigants: A fumigant is a chemical substance which is volatile at ordinary temperatures and sufficiently toxic to the insects. Fumigation is the process of subjecting the infested material to the toxic fumes or vapours of chemicals or gases which have insecticidal properties. Chemical used is the fumigant and a reasonably airtight container or room is known as fumigation chamber or "Fumigatorium". Fumigants mostly gain entry into the body of the insect through spiracles or the trachea.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Commonly used fumigants and their doses</head><p>1. Aluminium phosphide, marketed as Celphos tablets used against field rats, groundnut bruchids etc. @ 1 tablet (12 g) per ton of foodgrains or 600 g per 100 m 3 2. Carbon disulphide @ 820 lbs/1000 cuft of foodgrains 3. EDCT (Ethylene Dichloride Carbon Tetrachloride) @ 2030 lbs/1000 cuft of foodgrains 4. EDB (Ethylene dibromide) @ 1 lb/1000 cuft of foodgrains.</p><p>5. SO 2 : By burning sulphur in godowns, SO 2 fumes are released.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>iv) Systemic insecticides</head><p>Chemicals those are capable of moving through the vascular systems of plants irrespective of site of application and poisoning insects that feed on the plants. For example: methyl demeton, phosphamidon, acephate. 'Nonsystemic insecticides' are not possessing systemic action. Some nonsystemic insecticides, however, have ability to move from one surface leaf to the other. They are called as 'translaminar insecticides', e.g. malathion, diazinon, spinosad etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>An ideal systemic insecticide must have qualities:</head><p>1. Should have high intrinsic pesticidal activity 2. The toxicant must be adequately liposoluble for it to be absorbed by the plant system and water soluble for it to be translocated in the plant system.</p><p>3. The toxicant or its metabolites should be stable for sufficiently long period to exercise residual effect.</p><p>4. Should degrade to nontoxic form in reasonable time to avoid toxicity to consumer.</p><p>Systemic insecticides are applied as seed dressing, granular formulations, sprays etc. In the leaf, the entry of the toxicant is through stomata and cuticle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III. Based on mode of action</head><p>1. Physical poisons: Bring about the kill of insects by exerting a physical effect, e.g. Heavy oils, tar oils etc. which cause death by asphyxiation. Inert dusts effect loss of body moisture by their abrasiveness as in aluminium oxide or absorb moisture from the body as in charcoal.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Protoplasmic poisons:</head><p>A toxicant responsible for precipitation of protein especially destruction of cellular protoplasm of midgut epithelium, e.g. arsenical compounds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Respiratory poisons:</head><p>Chemicals which block cellular respiration as in hydrogen cyanide (HCN), carbon monoxide etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Nerve poisons:</head><p>Chemicals which block acetyl cholinesterase (AChE) and affect the nervous system, e.g. Organophosphorous, carbamates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Chitin inhibitors:</head><p>Chitin inhibitors interfere with process of synthesis of chitin due to which normal moulting and development is disrupted, e.g. novaluron, diflubenzuron, lufenuron, buprofezin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.">General poisons:</head><p>Compounds which produce neurotoxic symptoms after some period and do not belong to the above categories, e.g. chlordane, toxaphene, aldrin. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV. Based on mammalian toxicity</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VII. Based on pesticides' mode of action and other functions</head><p>Protectants: Pesticides applied to plants, animals, structures, mechanical systems and products to prevent pest establishment are considered protectants.</p><p>Sterilants: Pesticides that manage pests by rendering them incapable of normal reproduction are known as sterilants.</p><p>Selective: A pesticide is selective if it is effective against one type of organisms and not another.</p><p>Nonselective: When a pesticide kills or adversely affects many organisms in a target site, it is considered nonselective.</p><p>Broadspectrum: Pesticides that control a wide range of pests are considered broadspectrum. They are also sometimes labeled as multipurpose pesticides.</p><p>Contact: Pesticides that kill or adversely affect pests simply by contacting them are known as contact pesticides.</p><p>Systemic: Pesticides that are absorbed by one part of the animal or plant and distributed internally to other parts are known as systemic pesticides. These can kill the pest without harming the host.</p><p>Persistent: Pesticides that remain active for a period of time after application and give continued protection against the pest. They are also referred to as residual pesticides.</p><p>Nonpersistent: Pesticides that control pests at the time of application and then breakdown quickly are nonpersistent.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VIII. Classification based on activity or types of pests managed</head><p>Pesticides commonly are classified according to the types of pests/target species they control or the function they perform: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pesticide classification</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Biopesticides:</head><p>Biopesticides are certain types of pesticides derived from such natural materials as animals, plants, bacteria, and certain minerals. For example, canola oil and baking soda have pesticidal applications and are considered biopesticides. Biopesticides fall into three major classes:</p><p>1. Microbial pesticides consist of a microorganism (e.g., a bacterium, fungus, virus or protozoan) as the active ingredient. Microbial pesticides can control many different kinds of pests, although each separate active ingredient is relatively specific for its target pests.</p><p>2. The most widely used microbial pesticides are subspecies and strains of Bacillus thuringiensis, or Bt. Each strain of this bacterium produces a different mix of proteins, and specifically kills one or a few related species of insect larvae.</p><p>3. PlantIncorporatedProtectants (PIPs) are pesticidal substances that plants produce from genetic material that has been added to the plant. For example, scientists can take the gene for the Bt pesticidal protein, and introduce the gene into the plant's own genetic material. Then the plant, instead of the Bt bacterium, manufactures the substance that destroys the pest. The protein and its genetic material, but not the plant itself, are regulated by EPA.</p><p>4. Biochemical pesticides are naturally occurring substances that control pests by nontoxic mechanisms. Conventional pesticides, by contrast, are generally synthetic materials that directly kill or inactivate the pest. Biochemical pesticides include substances, such as insect sex pheromones, that interfere with mating, as well as various scented plant extracts that attract insect pests to traps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pesticide formulations</head><p>The component of a pesticide that controls the target pests is called the active ingredient. During the manufacturing process, active ingredients are mixed with liquid or dry inert ingredients, which are nonpesticide. Thus, mixture of active and inert/inactive ingredients is called pesticide formulation.</p><p>Insecticidal formulation may be defined as a combination of insecticides with carriers, diluents, surface active agents (wetters, speaders, emulsifying agents) and other adjuvants, according to predetermined formula with a view to produce a final consumer product.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Necessity of formulations</head><p>i) The prime purpose of formulation is the dilution of the high concentration pesticide down to a level at which it should be toxic to the pest, but will not cause damage to mammals, birds and fish.</p><p>ii) There is a need for uniform distribution of small quantities over large area which is only possible by making formulations.</p><p>iii) Formulations enable to use less amount of pesticide over large area thus making the process economical.</p><p>iv) Higher concentration may leave more residues and may induce resistance in pests, hence, formulation is must.</p><p>v) Small quantities of toxicants are very difficult to be fed in the application equipments; hence large volumes in formulation can easily be fed and handled.</p><p>vi) Formulation may be necessary so as to be able to use water as carrier or diluent. Since most of the pesticides are insoluble in water but soluble in organic solvents and if we want to use water as diluent, we have to use surfactants, emulsifiable agents and also proper type of solvents.</p><p>vii) To improve shelflife, stabilizers and antioxidants are added.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>How to choose a formulation?</head><p>A single pesticide is often sold in different formulations. Different formulations of the same active ingredient often behave differently. For example, some types of formulations may mix better in water, while others may increase the chance of crop injury. Choose the formulation that is suitable for the job. Important points include: q Percentage of active ingredient (a.i.) q Ease in handling and mixing q Personal safety risk q Type of environment (agriculture, forest, urban, etc.) q Effectiveness against the pest q Habits of the pest q The crop to be protected q Type of application machinery q Danger of drift or runoff q Possible injury to crop q</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cost</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Classification of formulations</head><p>The formulations are generally classified into three groups: Liquid formulations, Solid formulations and Gaseous formulations.</p><p>A) Liquid formulations: Liquid formulations are generally mixed with water, but in some instances, labels may permit the use of crop oil, diesel fuel, kerosene, or some other light oil as a carrier. The common liquid pesticide formulations are:</p><p>1) Emulsifiable concentrates (EC): These preparations are usually solutions containing a high concentration of the pesticide. Most of them are designed to be mixed with water or oil and contain wetting agents, stickers, and other additives. They usually contain a liquid active ingredient, one or more petroleum based solvents and an agent that allows the formulation to be mixed with water to form an emulsion. The active ingredient ranges from 2.5 to 100 per cent. When sprayed the solvent evaporates quickly leaving a deposit of toxicant from which water also evaporates. ECs are among the most versatile formulations. Upon mixing with water, they take on a "milky" appearance. Emulsifier reduces the surface tension of spray.</p><p>The emulsifying agents are alkaline soaps, organic amines, alginates, carbohydrates, gums, lipids, proteins etc. Some of the EC formulations are: malathion 50 EC, cypermethrin 10 EC, 25 EC, endosulfan 35 EC, chlorpyriphos 20 EC, profenophos 50 EC etc. 2) Solution (S): Some pesticide a.i. dissolves readily in a liquid solvent. When mixed with the solvent, they form a solution that will not settle out or separate. They are ready to use formulations, applied against household pests, e.g. carbaryl along with molasses as 40%, Baygon sprays (2 % propoxur in kerosene).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Merits</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Water soluble concentrates (WS or WSC):</head><p>The solutions are sold as concentrates that must be further diluted with a liquid solvent before application. It is a liquid formulation resembling EC. The solvent used for dissolving the toxicant is miscible in water, so that after dilution with water, it gives a sort of insecticidal solution, e. g. monocrotophos 36 WSC, thiamethoxam (Cruiser 70 WS), phosphamidon 85 WSC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4) Suspension concentrates (SC):</head><p>The active ingredient is absorbed on to a filler which is then suspended in liquid matrix (water). It is not dusty and easier to disperse in water, e.g. dimecron 100 SC, spinosad 48 SC, indoxacarb 15 SC.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) Ultralow volume (ULV):</head><p>These concentrations may approach 100 % a.i. which is designed to be used as it is or to be diluted with only small quantities of specified solvents. Also known as low volumes concentrate (LVC) or Concentrated Insecticide Liquid (CIL). The technical grade of the toxicant at highly concentrated level is dissolved in nonvolatile solvents.</p><p>Emulsifier is not added. These are generally applied from high altitudes in extremely fine droplets without being diluted with water at ultra volume rates. e.g. malathion 95 LVC, bifenthrin, fenitrothion. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Merits</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6) Flowables (F):</head><p>When an active ingredient is insoluble in water or organic solvents, a flowable formulation is developed. The toxicant is milled with a solid carrier such as inert clay and subsequently dispensed in a small quantity of water. Prior to application it has to be diluted with water. Flowables do not usually clog nozzles and require only moderate agitation. These formulations are easy to handle and apply, e.g. methoxyfenozide (Intrepid 2 F).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations:</head><p>a) These require moderate agitation, may leave visible residue.</p><p>b) Since they are liquids, they are subject to spilling and splashing. c) They contain solid particles, so they contribute to abrasive wear of nozzles and pumps.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7) Aerosol (A):</head><p>Aerosols (pressurized cans, "bug bombs") contain a small amount of pesticide, or a combination of pesticides that are driven through a fine opening by a chemically inactive gas under pressure, when the nozzle is triggered. Usually they are small, weighing about one pound. The toxicant is suspended as minute particles (0.1 to 30 microns) in air as fog or mist.</p><p>The toxicant is dissolved in a liquified gas and if released through a small hole causes the toxicant particles to float in air with rapid evaporation of the released gas. e.g. allethrin (Tortoise coils).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Merits:</head><p>a) These are ready to use, retain potency for a long time.</p><p>b) Aerosols are very convenient in that they are always ready to use. c) They are also a convenient way to buy small quantities of a pesticide. d) They are easily stored and the pesticides do not lose their strength (potency, activity) while in the can during their normal period of use.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations:</head><p>Practicable for limited uses, risk of inhalation, hazardous if punctured, over heated, difficult to confine to target site or pest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>8) Insecticide mixtures:</head><p>Insecticide mixtures involve combinations of two or more insecticides in the right concentration into a single spray solution. Insecticide mixtures are widely used to deal with the array of pests encountered in greenhouses and field production systems due to the savings in labour. Further, the use of pesticide mixtures may result in enhanced efficacy and the minimization of resistance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Examples:</head><p>Chlorpyriphos16% </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>9) ReadytoUse low concentration solutions (RTU)</head><p>Lowconcentrate RTU formulations are ready to use and require no further dilution before application. They consist of a small amount of active ingredient (often 1 % or less per unit volume) dissolved in an organic solvent. They usually do not stain fabrics nor have unpleasant odors. They are especially useful for structural and institutional pests and for household use.</p><p>Major disadvantages of lowconcentrate formulations include limited availability and high cost per unit of active ingredient. These preparations are usually solutions in highly refined oils that contain low concentrations of the pesticide. They are generally used as purchased.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>10) Liquid baits</head><p>An increasing number of insecticides and rodenticides are being formulated as liquid baits.</p><p>Liquid rodenticides are mixed with water and placed in bait stations designed for these products.</p><p>They have two major benefits. Liquid rodenticides are effective in controlling rodents, especially rats, in areas where they cannot find water. They are also effective in areas of poor sanitation where readily available food renders traditional baits ineffective.</p><p>Liquid insecticide baits are used primarily by the structural pest control industry for controlling ants and, to a lesser extent, cockroaches. They are packaged as readytouse, sugarbased liquids placed inside bait stations. Liquid insecticide ant baits have a number of advantages. They are very effective against certain species of sugarfeeding ants. These ants typically accept and transfer liquid baits into the ant colonies. However, some ants will not feed on liquid baits. Liquid baits also must be replaced often.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B) Solid formulations 1) Dusts (D):</head><p>These are ready to use insecticides in powder form. In a dust formulation the toxicant is diluted either by mixing with or by impregnation on a suitable finely divided carrier which may be an organic flour or pulverized mineral like lime, gypsum, talc etc., or clay like attapulgite, bentonite etc. The toxicant in a dust formulation ranges from 0.15 to 25% and the particle size in dust formulations is less than 100 microns. With the decrease in particle size the toxicity of the formulation increases. Dusts are always used dry.</p><p>In the selection of a dust formulation its compatibility, fineness, bulk density, flowability, abrasiveness, absorbability, specific gravity and cost should be taken into consideration. The dust should flow freely and must not cake or ball in the hopper. The application of dust must be done in a calm weather and early in the morning when the plant is wet with dew, e.g. malathion 5 D, methyl parathion 2 D, fenval 0.4 D, chlorpyriphos 1.5 D. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Merits</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Granules or Pelleted insecticides (G):</head><p>It is a type of insecticidal formulation prepared by applying liquid insecticide to coarse particles of porous material like clay, walnut shells. These are also ready to use granular or pelleted forms of insecticides. In this formulation, the particle is composed of a base such as an inert material impregnated or fused with the toxicant which is released from the formulation in its intact form or as it disintegrates giving controlled release. The particle size ranges from 0.25 to 2.38 mm, or 250 to 1250 microns and contains 2 to 40% concentration of the toxicant. The granules are applied in water or whorls of plants or in soil. Granular formulations of systemic insecticides are used for the control of sucking and soil pests by application to soil. Whorl application is done for the control of borer pests of crops such as sorghum, maize and sugarcane etc. Examples: phorate 10 G, carbofuran 3 G, carbaryl 4 G, lindane 6 G, cartap hydrochloride 4 G, chlorpyriphos 10 G etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Merits:</head><p>a) There is very little drift b) Undesirable contamination is prevented c) There is no undue loss of insecticides d) Residue problem is less since granules do not adhere to plant surface e) Release of toxicant is achieved over a long period than does a spray deposit f) These formulations are easy for application as water is not required for application and g) They are less harmful to natural enemies</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Limitations:</head><p>a) Do not stick to foliage b) They may need to be incorporated into the soil or planting medium c) They may need moisture to start action d) They may be hazardous to water fowl and other birds e) It is not effective as sprays against most crawling insects f) Scorching of plant parts may occur if the toxicant is concentrated in a smaller volume of carrier</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Wettable Powders (WP):</head><p>Wettable powder is a powdered formulation which yields a rather stable suspension when diluted with water. WP is dry, finely ground formulations that look like dusts. Usually they must be mixed with water for application or spray. WP contains 5 95% a.i. usually 50% or more. WP pesticides do not dissolve in water. They settle out quickly and constant agitation is used to keep them suspended. They are one of the most widely used pesticide formulations. It is formulated by blending the toxicant with diluents such as attapulgite, a surface active agent and an auxiliary material such as sodium salts of sulfo acids. Sometimes stickers are added to improve retention on plants and other surfaces; e.g. carbaryl 50 WP. The requirements of a wettable powder formulation are: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4) Soluble Powders (SP):</head><p>Soluble powder formulations look like wettable powders. However, when mixed with water, soluble powders dissolve readily and form a true solution. Addition of surfactants improves the wetting power of the spray fluid. Sometimes an anticaking agent is added which prevents formation of lumps in storage. This formulation usually contains a high concentration of toxicant and therefore convenient to store and transport. Few pesticides are available in this formulation because only a few active ingredients are readily soluble in water. After they are mixed thoroughly, no additional agitation is necessary. The amount of active ingredient in soluble powders ranges from 15 to 95 per cent by weight; usually more than 50 per cent. Soluble powders have all the advantages of wettable powders and none of the disadvantages except the inhalation hazard during mixing, e.g. acephate 75 SP, acetamiprid 20 SP.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) Water dispersible granules (WDG):</head><p>Waterdispersible granules, also known as dry flowables, are like wettable powders except instead of being dustlike, they are formulated as small, easily measured granules. This formulation appears as small pellets or granules. It is easier and safer to handle and mix than wettable powders. When the granules are mixed for spray with water, they break apart and with agitation, the active ingredient becomes distributed throughout the spray mixture. Waterdispersible granules must be mixed with water to be applied. The percentage of active ingredient is high, often as much as 90 per cent by weight.</p><p>The formulation requires constant agitation to keep them suspended in water, e.g. thiamethoxam 25 WDG.</p><p>Waterdispersible granules share many of the same advantages and disadvantages of wettable powders except:</p><p>q They are more easily measured and mixed q Because of low dust, they cause less inhalation hazard to the applicator during handling 6) Baits (B): Poisonous bait is a food or other substance mixed with a pesticide that will attract and be eaten by pests and eventually cause their death. A bait formulation is an active ingredient mixed with food or other attractive substance. Pests are killed by eating the pesticide, the bait contains. The amount of a.i. in most bait formulations is quite low, usually less than 5%. Their main use is for the control of vertebrate pests such as rodents, other mammals and birds. The poison baits are used for the control of fruit flies, chewing insects, wireworms, white grubs in the soil, household pests, rats in the field and storage, snails and slugs. This method is ideal under conditions where spray application is rather difficult. For successful poison baiting the attractivity, palatability, toxicity, stability and physical condition of the baits, as also the time, place and method of exposure must be considered. The high cost of the attractants and nonpersistence for a longer period are some of the limiting factors in successful poison baits used in pest control. Examples: 2.5% carbaryl baits for grasshoppers, 0.05% malathion bait spray having 1% molasses, sugar or gur against fruit fly.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>7) Micro encapsulated pesticides (M):</head><p>Micro encapsulated pesticides are particles of pesticides (liquid or dry) surrounded by a plastic coating. Once applied, the capsule slowly releases the pesticide. The encapsulation process can prolong the active life of the pesticide by providing a timed release of the active ingredient. Microencapsulated pesticides are mixed with water and sprayed in the same manner as other sprayable formulations. After spraying, the plastic coating breaks down and slowly releases the active ingredient, e.g. lambdacyhalothrin.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>8) Seed dressers (SD):</head><p>Used for presowing treatment of seeds so as to save the seedlings from the attack of insectpests, e.g. carbosulfan 50 SD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>9) Watersoluble packets (WSB or WSP):</head><p>Watersoluble packets reduce the mixing and handling hazards of some highly toxic pesticides. Manufacturers package precise amounts of wettable powder or soluble powder formulations in a special type of plastic bag. When these bags are dropped into a filled spray tank, they dissolve and release their contents to mix with the water. There are no risks of inhaling or contacting the undiluted pesticide as long as you do not open the packets. Once mixed with water, however, pesticides packaged in water soluble packets are no safer than other diluted pesticides.</p><p>Other solid formulations: Tablets (WT, DT), Emulsifiable granules (EG), Floating granules (FG).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C) Gaseous formulations</head><p>Fumigants: A chemical compound which is volatile at ordinary temperature and sufficiently toxic is known as fumigant. Most fumigants are liquids held in cans or tanks and quite often they are mixtures of two or more gases. Fumigants are pesticides that form gases or vapors toxic to plants, animals, and microorganisms. Some active ingredients are formulated, packaged, and released as gases; others are liquids when packaged under high pressure and change to gases when they are released. Other active ingredients are volatile liquids when enclosed in an ordinary container and therefore, are not formulated under pressure. Others are solids that release gases when applied under conditions of high humidity or in the presence of water vapor. Fumigants are used for structural pest control, in food and grain storage facilities, and in regulatory pest control at ports of entry and at state and national borders. In agricultural pest control, fumigants are used in soil, greenhouses, granaries, and grain bins.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Merits:</head><p>a) The places not easily accessible to other chemicals can be easily reached due to penetration and dispersal effect of the gas, e.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Abbreviations for some formulations</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CHAPTER3 HOW TO READ A PESTICIDE PRODUCT LABEL</head><p>One of the most important tools for safe and judicious use of pesticides is the information on the product label. Label on the pesticide container and the enclosed leaflet are the key to the information about a pesticide you are planning to use. Both of these not only give directions about the target pests, dosages, how to use and apply the pesticide, but also offer guidelines for safe handling, storage and protection of the environment. Information in label and leaflet is the most expensive literature because considerable amount of multidisciplinary research and development is required to generate the knowledge about a pesticide (Fig. <ref type="figure">11</ref>).</p><p>Rule 19 of the Insecticide Act calls for the following information to be necessarily displayed on the label:</p><p>1. Name of the insecticide including common name, chemical name and trade name.</p><p>2. The name of the manufacturer: The full name and address of the manufacturer is given.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Registration number of insecticide.</head><p>4. Name of the active ingredient, inert ingredient etc. as also the percentage composition of each.</p><p>5. Type of formulation such as emulsifiable concentrate, wettable powder, dust or granules etc.</p><p>6. Net content of the package.</p><p>7. Batch number.</p><p>8. Date of manufacture and Expiry date. 9. Antidote statement.</p><p>10. Warning symbols and signal words.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The information on leaflet:</head><p>For each pack one leaflet is provided by the manufacturer. The leaflet contains very useful information. Due to limitation of space on the pesticide container, detailed information on the use of pesticide is given on the leaflet. The following information is normally available on the leaflet:</p><p>1. Particular application of leaflet: This includes the names of the insects, weeds, diseases etc.</p><p>for particular crops against which the pesticide may be used.</p><p>2. Directions of use: This gives the dosage to be applied, manner of spraying, time of application and other useful information related to the method of use of the insecticide.</p><p>3. Warning and cautionary statement: This includes the symptoms and poisoning, safety measures required, emergency firstaid treatment and antidotes.</p><p>4. Container disposal: The instructions are given about the decontamination of the empty containers and their disposal methods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Storage information:</head><p>This includes the information on method of storage. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>TYPES OF CROPS, VISÀVIS SPRAY EQUIPMENT AND PROTECTIVE CLOTHING</head><p>Crops vary quite substantially in height, making different spraying methods necessary for each. The chances of exposure to pesticides, consequently, are different for different types of crops.</p><p>Naturally, the type of spray equipments and protective clothings required also vary with the height of the crop.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A) Orchard and tall plantation crops</head><p>These crops are also called overhead crops and represent the maximum chances of exposure to pesticide drift during spraying. To minimize the exposure, it is necessary to select a proper sprayer, nozzle and protective clothings. i) Sprayer: Rocker or hydraulic power operated sprayer for insecticides/fungicides spray and back pack plastic body sprayer for herbicide spray. Tractor mounted sprayer is also used for herbicide spray.</p><p>ii) Nozzle: Adjustable triple action nozzle for a rocker sprayer and high jet spray gun for hydraulic power operated sprayer for insecticides/fungicides spray and flood jet or flat fan nozzle for herbicide spray.</p><p>iii) Protective clothings: One or two piece protective garments or clothings prepared out of empty plastic sacks or sheets, face shield, a cap and gloves. Full pant, full sleeves shirt and shoes are a must. Costly protective garments can be replaced with cheap ones prepared out of empty plastic sacks or sheets.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B) Bushy plantation crops</head><p>Tea bushes are almost of chest height and the climate remains warm and humid. Because the pesticide drift can reach upto head height, the chances of exposure are very high. i) Sprayer: Suitable sprayer is knapsack or mist blower for insecticide/fungicide sprays and back pack plastic body sprayer for herbicide sprays.</p><p>ii) Nozzles: Hollow cone for insecticide/fungicide spray with knapsack sprayer and mist blower. For herbicide sprays, use flood jet or flat fan nozzle.</p><p>iii) Protective clothings: Same as given above under orchard and tall plantation crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C) Field crops</head><p>This group includes crops like paddy, gram, vegetables, groundnut and so on -all crops that grow substantially less than chest height.</p><p>Because some of these cops are quite tall while others are very short in height, two types of clothings are recommended one each for low and high field crops. i) Sprayer: Knapsack or mist blower or tractor mounted sprayer.</p><p>ii) Nozzle: Insecticide/fungicide sprays -Hollow cone; Herbicide sprays -Flood jet or flat fan.</p><p>iii) Protective clothings Low field crops: One or two piece protective garments or clothings prepared out of plastic sacks or sheets, a pair of boots, full pant, full sleeves shirt. Face shield in case of tractor mounted sprayer.</p><p>High field crops: One or two piece protective garments or clothings prepared out of plastic sacks or sheets, hand gloves, face mask, cap, a pair of boots, full pant and full sleeved shirt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Application techniques of spray fluids</head><p>The pesticide application plays an important role in pest management. The main purpose of pesticide application technique is to cover the target species and safety to the nontarget organisms and the environment. The complete knowledge of pest is essential for correct time of application. Most of the pesticides are applied as sprays.</p><p>Spraying is classified on the basis of the droplet size of the spray as:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Spray Type Droplet size Equipment</head><p>Coarse spray 400100 µ 1. High volume spraying (HVS) or Full cover spraying or conventional spraying: Pesticide is diluted with water and droplet size is larger. Spray fluid requirement is 500 -1000 lit/ha in case of field crops and 1500 -2000 lit/ha for orchard crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Low volume spray (LVS):</head><p>The low volume sprays are 825 times more concentrated than high volume spraying. Spray fluid requirement ranges from 12125 lit/ha. The droplet size is 70 -150µ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Ultra low volume spray (ULVS):</head><p>ULV sprayer or air craft with special nozzles require 0.5 5.6 lit/ha with droplet size of 20 -70 µ.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Hydraulic sprayer</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mist blower</head><p>Micron sprayer, ULV Aerosols, Fogging machine</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Smoke generator</head><p>Vapour generator 4. Aerial spraying: Aerial aircrafts have been employed for application of agricultural and public health pesticides. It is used for spraying, dusting and application of baits. However, spray formulations are more suitable than dusts because of wind speed should not be more than 5 KMPH. It has to be done at low heights and in the early hours of the days to ensure uniform deposition of dust particles.</p><p>Application Techniques: Apart from spraying and dusting, the pesticides can also be applied in following ways:</p><p>• Seed treatment: Many soil insects</p><p>• Seedling dip method: Effective against stem borer, gall midge</p><p>• Root zone placement: Effective against stem borers, leaf hoppers, whorl maggots</p><p>• Whorl application: Effective against stem borers</p><p>• Chemigation: by injection into the water flowing through irrigation system</p><p>• Infusion and injection: injection through xylem tissues of the fruit and ornamental trees</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CHAPTER5 PROPER PESTICIDE APPLCATION TECHNIQUES</head><p>How to spray and when, are as important as what to spray? One should not only have to use the right pesticide, but also the right equipment to spray it with at the right time of the day. In addition to this, adjust your spraying technique to suit factors beyond your control, such as the velocity and directions of the wind.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Need to keep track of so many things q</head><p>Because doing it the wrong way, one can endanger the health and that of helpers q Besides, you get the best control of the pests when spraying technique is right</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Important guidelines q</head><p>Choose right pesticide to control the right pest, e.g. systemic insecticide ---sucking pests, Contact insecticide---caterpillar pests q Do not make cocktails: Because in cocktails, each pesticide partner is used at a lower dose than recommended, which is not fully effective but there is every chance of the pests' developing resistance q Use one pesticide at full recommended dose q Use the correct spray equipments, e.g. i) For orchard and tall planted crops---use Rocker or hydraulic power operated sprayer ii) Bushy planted crops---knapsack or mist blower iii) Field crops----knapsack or mist blower q Use the correct nozzle i) Field and bushy plantation crops--Hollow cone nozzle ii) Orchard and tall planted crops--Adjustable triple gun nozzle iii) All crops ---Herbicide spray ---Flood jet or flat cone nozzle q Medium size droplets are ideal i.e. 100300 microns, because a) If the droplets are too fine, there are chances of the spray drifting away or drying before reaching the target, b) If the droplets are too coarse, they may damage crop and result in poor distribution q Spray only when the wind velocity is less than 5 kmph q Spray during cooler hours of the day i.e. morning and late afternoon q Always keep a slight overlap during spraying q Use correct spray volume to ensure proper and uniform coverage q Calibrate water quantity before actual spray q Use proper pesticide formulation according to the availability of spraying equipment q Use proper and good maintained spraying equipments because i) poor maintenance leads to poor application and in turn poor control, ii) it also endangers the health of an operator q Direct the nozzles of the spraying equipment to the target for uniform and effective coverage of spray material q Spillage of spray material during spraying should be avoided as it leads to pesticide poisoning and phytotoxicity q Always calibrate equipment properly before spraying. Because correctly calibrated equipment reduces the chance of applying too much q Avoid pesticide applications when there is forecast for heavy rain q Follow instructions from the label of the pesticide container q During the application, notice whether the pesticide looks the way it should be: i. Application of wettable powers (WPs) usually are whitish ii. Granules and dusts should appear dry and not form clumps iii. Emulsifiable concentrate (ECs) usually look milky If the pesticide does not look right, be sure that there should be the right mixture which still needs blending evenly. q Always turn equipment off whenever there is pause for any reason</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Calibration of a sprayer</head><p>Whatever be the progress in spraying technology, we need to stress more on calibration of sprayer for spraying which is very much lacking in spraying work done in farmers' fields. Some simple ways of calibration are given below:</p><p>1) Measuring the crop field q Measure row to row distance and count the number of rows. Multiply these two figures and get the width (W) of the field.</p><p>q Walk with your normal speed along the first and last row of the crop from outside avoiding any hindrance in the way. Note the time in seconds and average these figures. The average figure will be an average length (L) in meters. This is because man in general walks at a speed of 1.00 ± 0.05 meter/second. q Get the area of the field by multiplying L x W. If the field is not close a square or rectangle, apply some simple geometric calculations.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Measuring the flow rate of the sprayer q</head><p>First check the sprayer nozzle for leakage if any by spraying just water. Change or set the nozzle and repair the nozzle for leakage, if required. Operate the sprayer with a normal pressure or speed and collect spray fluid in an empty container for a minute. Measure this volume. Repeat three times and get the average flow rate per minute.</p><p>3) Calculating spray solution required for the field q Take a measured quantity of water in the sprayer and spray a 10 meter row giving a thorough coverage on the crop. Note the time and water required q With these figures work out the total spray solution and time required for spraying the known area of the crop field Example: A farmer is to apply monocrotophos 36 SL @ 540 g a.i./ha with a knapsack sprayer. Find out the quantity of spray solution required and insecticide to be purchased if the operator's walking speed is 60 m/minute and swath width is 1.0 meter and nozzle discharge rate is 1.5 litres/minute.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Solution:</head><p>Area sprayed = Swath width x walking speed = 1 x 60 = 60 m 2 /min Application rate = Nozzle discharge rate × area to be treated Area sprayed = 1.5 x 10000 60 = 250 litres/ha Quantity of insecticide to be purchased</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">C 1 V 1 = 100 × R × A (R= Recommended rate; A = Area to be treated) 36 × V 1 = 100 × 540 × 1</formula><p>V 1 = 1500 g or 1500 ml or 1.5 litre</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CHAPTER6 PESTICIDE APPLICATION EQUIPMENTS, THEIR MAINTENANCE AND REPAIR</head><p>Pesticide application equipments are important to the success of pest control. Selection of the right kind of application equipment and using it correctly to suite the need are necessary in addition to taking proper and good care. There are some criteria that deserve major emphasis when considering pesticide application apart from other factors affecting the ability to place a pesticide on the target in the manner and amount for most effective results and with the least undesirable side effects and at the lowest possible cost.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Necessity of application equipments</head><p>Insecticide application equipments are essential for four reasons:</p><p>q Insecticides are costly and would be wasted if not applied by machines q Insecticides need to be evenly spread on the target (foliage) surface which is possible only through equipments q Application equipments take less time and need less labour and therefore, are economical; and q Insecticides can be aimed to impinge on the targets or reach tall trees only through equipments Pest control equipments are now available in numerous types, model, sizes and makes. Most of them control pests by dispersing pesticides, while others do so without the use of pesticides. Various types of equipments used include sprayers, dusters, vapour and smoke generators, agriculture aircrafts; granule applicators, soil injectors, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Sprayers:</head><p>The main function of sprayer is to discharge the spray fluid in small droplets with some force for distributing it properly. Sprayer atomizes the spray fluid which may be a suspension, an emulsion or a solution. The sprayers function on three main principles:</p><p>q By pressing the spray liquid directly through a plunger (piston) to force it out.</p><p>q By compressing a layer of air through a plunger which in turn, presses the underlying spray liquid to force it out.</p><p>q By producing an air blast through a plunger or a blower (fan) which atomizes the spray liquid and carries it along to the target (air blast sprayers to spray blowers, when a blower is employed).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Dusters: Appliances which are used to distribute dust formulations are known as dusters. These dusters may be manually operated or power operated.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Parts of sprayer:</head><p>The important parts of manually operated sprayer are given below: ii) Pump: Pumps are mostly used to pump air and to develop pressure over a spray fluid in an air tight container. In some models, the pump is used to create a slight pressure in the spray containers and therefore, required to be operated continuously during the spraying operations. Plunger pumps are also used in the household sprayers. They take in definite volume of spray fluid from inlet and transfer it without possibility of escape to the outlet. The output of the fluid increases with increase in the pumping movements of the pump.</p><p>iii) Agitator: Most of the pesticidal materials in spray fluids are not in solution. Therefore, it is desirable to provide agitator for keeping the pesticidal material uniformly dispersed. In some cases of stirrup -pump sprayer, agitation is provided by the return flow of some spray fluid from the pump. Agitation is also provided by paddles or propellers as in case of knapsack sprayers.</p><p>iv) Pressure gauge: It is provided on compression knapsack sprayers. It guides the operator in properly adjusting the pressure for each spray job. It also provides a quick means of determining whether the sprayer is functioning correctly or not.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>v) Valves:</head><p>Valves govern the direction of flow of a spray material. In sprayers, ball valves are commonly used. In this case, a round ball of metal fits perfectly on a circular seat. When the ball is pressed against the seat, it produces a water tight seal and prevents the return flow of liquid. The cleaning of ball and its seat usually improves the performance of the pump.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>vi) Filters:</head><p>The liquid must be well filtered to: a) protect the pump from abrasion, b) avoid interference with the function of valves, and c) prevent the blocking of nozzles. The filters are usually provided on filter hole, between the tank and the pump unit, and within the spray lance.</p><p>vii) Air chamber: The plunger pump delivers liquid only on the pressure stroke, because the pressure is relaxed during the suction stroke. An air chamber is provided in the bigger kitchen sprayers, e.g. stirrup pump sprayer that works on the pump system. It prevents fluctuation in the pressure and ensures continuity in the spraying.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>viii) Tubes:</head><p>A good tube is light, non absorbent, oil resistant, durable and flexible. The plastic and nylon tubes are more common in these days because of being light and cheap.</p><p>ix) Nozzles: Nozzle mostly consists of small chamber with a device inside it to atomize the liquid and spread it out into spray droplets through the orifice. Nozzles are designed to produce fan shaped, solid cone, or hollow cone spray pattern. Different parts of nozzle are: Body, strainer, whirl plate, gasket, disc and cap.</p><p>The body encloses all other parts except the cap. The strainer filters out larger particles to prevent clogging of orifices. The whirl plate has two or more slanting holes which twist the liquid about at a high velocity before it is discharged through the disc. The whirling motion breaks the liquid into droplets and the resulting swirling action of the spray moves the foliage to provide a better coverage of the surfaces. The gasket prevents leakage and the cap holds the disc in position.</p><p>Types of nozzles: Nozzles are usually classified and named after the energy used to form droplets.</p><p>a) Hydraulic nozzles: Mostly used in sprayers. Large quantity of water is used. These nozzles produce coarse sprays. These are of different types:</p><p>q Flood jet nozzles Operate at low pressure giving a coarse spray without any drift q Flat fan nozzles Discharge rate: 5003000 ml/min. Fine to coarse sprays without much drift.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Suitable for insecticides and fungicides</head><p>q Cone nozzles Hollow cone nozzles are preferred q Adjustable nozzles Both form cones (solid or broken) and jets q Swivel nozzles Can spray at any angle from 0180 0 and can be locked at any desired angle.</p><p>They are of single swivel or double swivel types b) Gaseous/Pneumatic nozzles: Used with mist blowers. The atomization occurs by impact of air blast on the drop of a pesticide falling with gravity. Suitable for ULV spraying.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>c) Centrifugal nozzles:</head><p>The spray fluid is fed to a rotating disc and the centrifugal force disintegrates it into droplets of very fine size. Used in rotatary disc ULV sprayers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>d) Thermal/ hot tube nozzles:</head><p>A fog composed of very fine droplets can be produced by condensing a pesticide which has been injected into a stream of hot gas to shear the liquid into droplets which are immediately vapourized. These vapours later on condense into very fine droplets which are suspended in air for sometime till they finally settle on a surface. It is suitable for controlling flying insects in enclosed spaces.</p><p>x)</p><p>Spray lances and cut off devices: The nozzle of a sprayer is usually attached to a brass rod (extension rod, spray lance) of variable designs and lengths. It facilitates spraying the lower sides of leaves. This is a simple pump to which a dust chamber is connected. The pump generates an air blast that is passed on to the dust chamber causing the dust to blow out through a delivery tube. It is suited for smallscale operations like kitchengardens, poultry houses, cattlesheds etc. The machine is also known as foot pump duster or cyano gas pump since it can be employed in fumigating the rodent (rat) burrows with calcium cyanide (cyanogas) or sodium cyanide (cynamag).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Classification of pesticide application equipments</head><p>(II) Bellows duster: It works on compressing bellows (which may be of leather, rubber or plastic) to produce an air blast for ejecting the dust out in small clouds. The machine comes in many shapes and models, and is suitable for domestic purposes or for kitchen gardens.</p><p>(III) Rotary (crank) duster: In this machine, the air blast is produced by employing a blower (fan) enclosed in a box. Through gears, the fan is connected to a handle. The slow rotation of the crank is converted into fast rotation of the fan by the gears. The air blast produced by the fan sucks the dust through a suction pipe so as to pass it out through the discharge pipe. An agitator connected to the gears keeps the dust fluffy in the hopper to prevent blocking of the passage to the suction pipe.</p><p>Rotary dusters are useful for treating small acreage and row crops like potato, tobacco, cotton etc. Two models of this duster are available one which rests on the belly of the operator and the other mounted on his shoulder.</p><p>(IV) Traction dusters: For a large scale dusting, the duster is mounted on wheels and the blower fan is connected to the wheel or wheels. Traction of the duster runs the fan which blows the dust out.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Poweroperated dusters</head><p>These dusters are provided with a petroldriven motor which runs both the agitator inside the hopper and blower (fan). The blower produces the air blast which, as usual, carries the dust particles to the delivery tube (hose) to be expelled out through the nozzles mounted on a boom. These appliances are used for much larger areas.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II) Sprayers</head><p>A. Hand operated hydraulic sprayers I) Syringes: Simplest hydraulic sprayers consisting of a cylinder and a plunger. The liquid is drawn in by the upward (suction) stroke and passed out by the downward (compression) stroke of the plunger. These sprayers are tiring to use. Suitable for small areas like household flower beds and kitchen gardens.</p><p>II) Bucket (or stirrup) pump sprayers: These machines are composed of a plunger with a D or T shaped handle, one or two barrels (cylinder), a stirrup and a footrest.</p><p>i) Single barrel pump Spray is emitted only during downward stroke and intermittently.</p><p>ii) Double barrel pump Spray is emitted in both downward and upward strokes because of the provision of a second barrel (broader) which acts as a pressure or air chamber maintaining the spray pressure even during the upward stroke. Continuous spray is emitted.</p><p>There are two valves in the doublebarrel pump a suction valve with a strainer at the bottom of the pump and a delivery valve at the bottom of the pressure chamber. These valves allow the flow in one direction only. The delivery tube is fitted on the top of the pressure chamber extending inside it. The pump is dipped in a bucket containing the spray liquid and retained in position by pressing the footrest. Two persons are needed to work on this pump one to operate the pump and other to handle the delivery tube and the spray lance.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>III) Knapsack sprayers:</head><p>This type of sprayer works on the same principle as the stirrup pump but is provided with a tank that sits comfortably on the back of the operator. Accordingly, it is single or double barreled and can be operated by a single person. Suitable for hilly and muddy terrains where use of larger sprayers or power sprayers is not possible.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IV) Foot (or pedal) pump sprayers</head><p>The piston of this type of sprayer is operated by foot and, therefore the pump has been inverted to connect it to the pedal. Another change is that the pump itself has two sections the lower section containing the piston is the pump proper and the upper section functions as a pressure or air chamber. The liquid is sucked in by the pump through a strainerfitted suction hose and passed on to the air chamber, which, in turn, discharge it through the delivery tube. The pump can develop a pressure upto 200 lbs which can send the spray to the height of 20 ft. Therefore, the pump is suitable for spraying trees in the orchards but can also be used for crop on mediumsized farms.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>V) Rocker sprayer</head><p>Here the piston is connected to a lever (instead of a pedal) which can be rocked to and fro to operate the piston. It has a larger and detachable air chamber.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>VI) Wheelbarrow sprayers</head><p>A rocker or a pedal spray pump can be mounted on a trolley provided with a tank to make a wheel barrow sprayers. The advantage of this machine is that the operator is saved from carrying the weight of the machine and spray fluid and the disadvantage is that it is tiring to push the machine, particularly on uneven grounds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Compression sprayers I) Pneumatic hand sprayers:</head><p>These sprayers employ air pressure to force the liquid out and, therefore, are kept partly empty to provide space for development of air pressure. They comprise a tank and an air pump to develop pressure and are provided with an aircheck valve at one end and a delivery tube connected outside to a nozzle through a triggercontrol valve.</p><p>The sprayer is suitable for the household and for kitchen gardens. Due to the prior development of air pressure, pumping process during spraying is minimized and its negative point is that one has to bend over low plants which is tiring.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II) Pneumatic Knapsack sprayers:</head><p>These are composed of a strongly built brass or copper tank with a capacity of 725 litres, a vertical air pump passing through the top and tightly fixed to it, a pressure gauge to indicate pressure inside and a delivery tube with a spray lance. The tank is filled upto 2/3 rd to 3/4 th , so as to leave an air space. The pump can produce a pressure of 55 60 lbs/inch 2 . The pump may then be loaded and strapped on the back and the trigger valve of the lance pressed to release the spray. The sprayer is good for large areas and is particularly good for public health insects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C. Air Blast Sprayers</head><p>Hand Atomizer (or Flit pump): This is the simplest air blast sprayer which consists of a pump, bearing a minute hole called nozzle in the middle of its closed end, a small tank, a cap and a small delivery tube that rises above the cap upto lowerhalf of the nozzle hole and below it upto the bottom of the tank. The barrel bears a small hole at its posterior end for the incoming and outgoing air. When the plunger is pushed forward, the pump ejects a gust of air from its nozzle which in turn drives the air above the delivery tube away creating a momentary vacuum due to which the spray fluid rises out of the tube. Now, when the plunger is drawn backward (upstroke), fresh air enters the barrel through its nozzle only to be expelled out by the next downstroke. The outgoing (second) gust of air not only breaks (atomizes) the oozed out spray liquid on top of the delivery tube into minute droplets but also carries them along to the target. A succession of up and down strokes thus throws out intermittent jets of the spray liquid. Working the pump is a tiring process, and therefore, it is suitable for household and kitchen gardens.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D. Poweroperated sprayers</head><p>I) Hydraulic (Power) sprayers: These machines are powered by 15 hp petrol engines and are composed of a pump, a tank with an agitator, a pressure regulator valve, a pressure gauge, suction and delivery hoses(13) having a spray gun or lance with a nozzle or several nozzles mounted on a boom.</p><p>According to their capacity to discharge liquids, they can be categorized as low pressure (15 125 psi), low volume sprayers (5100 litres/min. delivery) or high pressure (4001000 psi), high volume sprayers (40450 lit/min.delivery). High volume spraying needs the water and obviously more labour, and is suitable for partially soluble or low dispersibility chemicals of highly soluble products. Due to high degree of dilution, the degree of phytotoxicity is minimized and clogging is avoided due to larger apertures of the nozzles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>II) Spray blowers:</head><p>These combine a low pressure low volume hydraulic sprayer and an air blower. Atomization of the spray fluid is first done by pump by forcing the liquid to pass through a series of nozzles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>E. Miscellaneous appliances q</head><p>Mist blowers, Fog generators, Smoke generators, Soil injecting guns q Liquefied gas aerosols, Dust applicators for burrows.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>F) Electrostatic sprayers</head><p>Electrostatic sprayers have been used to serve the agricultural, sanitization and industrial markets. The sprayers can effectively apply most commonly used chemicals, pesticides, disinfectants and additives; providing with 2550% better coverage than a conventional sprayer or fogger. These are of various types but two are given here as under: i) Backpack (BP) electrostatic sprayer q Includes 1 MaxCharge™ airassisted electrostatic spraygun, 2 or 3headed sprayguns available q Backpack available in 9.5 and 15.1 litres sizes q Standard 150 ft hose, 250 ft optional q Requires an external air supply q PVC tank with UV inhibitors q Padded nylon straps q Air line pressure 60 70 PSI q Spray range of 15 20 ft (4.6 to 6.1 m) q Compatible with all conventional, waterbased chemicals and fungicides ii) Mobile backpack (MBP) electrostatic sprayer q Includes 1 Max Charge™ airassisted electrostatic spraygun, 2headed sprayguns available q Ergonomically balanced cart is easy to maneuver; handles provided front and back for 2man team operation q Sturdy construction-built to withstand hard use q Backpack available in 9.5 and 15.1 litre sizes q Standard 100 ft hose, 250 ft optional q 6.5 HP Briggs and Stratton gasoline engine provides power for onboard compressor q Compatible with all conventional, waterbased chemicals and fungicides Two things are important with electro static sprayers: Keeping the nozzles clean and monitoring the electronics. With the small orifices it is imperative to thoroughly flush the units after each use and then to check the spray patterns of each nozzle.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Maintenance and repair</head><p>Pesticides are very expensive, so must be applied efficiently. The proper maintenance of equipment is, therefore, essential, yet users seldom pay much attention to routine cleaning and checking of equipments. Careless handling and poor maintenance can ruin even the best equipment. Years of good performance can be obtained when the machines are used and serviced correctly.</p><p>The proper operation, maintenance, and repair of pesticide application equipments require some considerations before using, while using and after using the equipments. a) Before using the equipments i) Before putting into service, the recommendations for lubrication, operation and maintenance should be carefully read.</p><p>ii) The lubrication instructions should be followed faithfully using the specified lubricant.</p><p>iii) It should be given a careful general inspection for cracks, loose connections or other malfunctions that may have resulted from vibrations in earlier usage.</p><p>iv) In order to apply the correct dose of the chemical per hectare, the machine should be calibrated.</p><p>v) Clean water should be used for preparing spray fluids which should anyway be strained. It is important to mix wettable powders with a small amount of water to form a paste before adding the remaining water to it which avoids the formation of lumps. In the case of motorized knapsack sprayerscumdusters, the spray fluid should be filled into the tank, using a funnel. The fluid must not fall on the carburetor and the spark plug.</p><p>vi) Only those formulations should be applied with a machine for which it is designed.</p><p>vii) The spray fluid in the tank should be agitated to mix it well. After every interruption in the spraying operations, the spray fluid should be again agitated.</p><p>viii) In the case of difficulty in fitting a plastic hose or parts, it is advisable to dip them into hot water for a short time before fitting. This will prevent the cracking of these parts.</p><p>b) While using the equipments i) Nozzlesetting is important with hydraulic sprayers, because this influences the spray pattern.</p><p>The height of the nozzle should be adjusted to suit the crop and wind conditions.</p><p>ii) Nozzles should be examined for any deformity or inconsistency in the spray pattern, as also for their blockage.</p><p>iii) During the spraying operation, close watch should be kept on the pressuregauge. This is necessary to ensure that the required pressure is being maintained. iv) When changing from one duster to another, the machine should be cleaned out and the application rate rechecked. The same setting will not necessarily give the same rate with a new material.</p><p>v) When changing from one chemical to another, it may be essential to thoroughly clean the spray system to remove the chemical used earlier.</p><p>vi) Hoses should not be bent at angles because bending results in reduced pressure.</p><p>vii) Engines should not be run continuously for long periods because they get overheated.</p><p>viii) The operator should walk at a constant speed for ensuring a uniform distribution of the material.</p><p>A slight alteration especially in the case of concentrate sprays, may lead to uneven coverage that may give discouraging results in pest control.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>c) After using the equipments</head><p>Pesticide application equipment, like other machines, need periodic repair and replacement of parts.</p><p>The maintenance after pesticide application falls into following categories: a) There is the daily routine of cleaning, adjustment, greasing and lubrication.</p><p>b) At the end of the season, all wearing parts, such as nozzles, pumps, valves, nuts and ball bearings, should be inspected.</p><p>c) A similar examination should also be made of hoses and plastic parts which crack or break due to prolonged use and ageing. d) In order to prevent untimely breakdowns and delays in the middle of the season of heavy demand, it is desirable to arrange necessary replacements well before the start of the season and also have some extra parts. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Defects common to several types of manually operated sprayers and their remedies</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Common mistakes during application of pesticides and their corrective measures</head><p>The proper way to use pesticides involves many safety precautions and it is quite easy to forget some of them. Infact, the person who follows them all is rare, while the person who misses out on some is frequently seen. Some commonly seen mistakes which occur during field application of pesticides are listed below along with the necessary corrective measures:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Common mistakes</head><p>Corrective action q Sprayer leaking on the back of operator q Spillage of spray solution on sprayer body at the time of pouring q No washing of sprayer buckets, measuring jar, etc. after the operation q Worn out nozzle q Smelling of pesticide q Opening of pesticide bottle with bare hands q Mixing pesticide with bare hands q Smoking, chewing tobacco, drinking water or eating during spraying q Use of unwashed protective clothings q Spraying on an empty stomach q Children, cattle and pets present at spraying site q Child labour as spray operator q Spraying with cuts and open wounds on hands, face and feet q Washing of sprayer, buckets, measuring jar in river, stream or pond q Empty containers are used for storing food or drinking water Clean the nozzle with the help of a thin grass stem or petiole of the leaf or with some needle, if available q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q Spillage soaked in dry soil and buried away from water source, use hand gloves Not correct. Read label and leaflet carefully before use and observe strictly the safety precautions Dangerous practice. Spray during cooler hours of the day. It is for one's benefit. Red is most toxic product followed by yellow, blue and green in descending order.</p><p>q Spillage soaked in a duster with bare hands or washed away with water q Label and leaflet not read before use q Spraying during hotter hours of the day q Unaware of toxicity symbols q q q q</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5 Regular pest</figDesc><graphic coords="10,165.12,162.72,262.08,205.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 9</head><label>9</label><figDesc>Fig. 9 Potential pest</figDesc><graphic coords="12,171.12,238.08,260.16,264.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 10</head><label>10</label><figDesc>Fig. 10 Perennial pest n. Severe pest: They have EIL below the GEP. Regular and constant interventions with insecticides are required to produce marketable crops. EIL decreases as the value of crop increases. It also depends on the stage of the crop, stage of the pest etc., e.g. yellow stem borer of rice, Scirpophaga incertulus.Causes for insects attaining pest status q</figDesc><graphic coords="13,164.16,159.60,243.12,192.96" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>: a) ECs are easy to handle, transport and store b) Little agitation required; will not settle out or separate when equipment is running c) Not abrasive d) Will not plug screens or nozzles e) Little visible residue on treated surfaces Limitations: a) Some may be phytotoxic b) In some cases compatibility can be a problem (fertilizers) c) High a.i. concentration makes it easy to overdose or under dose through mixing or calibration errors d) Easily absorbed through skin of humans or animals e) Solvents may cause rubber or plastic hoses, gaskets, and pump parts and surfaces to deteriorate f) May cause pitting or discoloration of painted finishes g) Flammable, should be used and stored away from heat or open flame h) May be corrosive</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>: a) Relatively easy to handle, transport and store b) Remain in solution; little agitation required c) Not abrasive to equipment d) Will not plug screens and nozzles e) Leave little visible residue on treated surfaces f) Less loss through evaporation Limitations: a) Difficult to keep pesticide on target-high drift hazard b) Specialized equipment required c) Easily absorbed through skin of humans or animals d) Solvents may cause rubber or plastic hoses, gaskets, and pump parts and surfaces to deteriorate e) Calibration and application must be done very carefully because of the high concentration of active ingredient</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>: a) Usually ready to use formulations b) They are effective where moisture from a spray might cause damage c) They require simple equipments d) They can be used in water scarcity situations e) It is cheaper pesticide formulation f) It can be applied very fast Limitations: a) Easily drift off target during application b) They may irritate eyes, nose, throat and skin c) They are difficult to get an uniform distribution of particles on surfaces d) Their residues easily moved off the target by air movement or water e) The cost of carriers used in the preparation of this formulation is comparatively more f) Because of drift problem there is less deposition of the pesticide on treated plant surfaces and hence effectiveness is reduced g) Will not stick to surfaces as well as liquids h) Dampness can cause clogging and lumping</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>i) Stability in storage and absence of caking ii) Quick formation of suspension and slow settling out of solid particles iii) Good wettability and spreading on treated surface and iv) Retention on treated surface for a longer period Merits: a) Easy to store, transport, handle, less skin and eye absorption b) Less harm to treated plants, animals and surfaces Limitations: a) They often clog nozzles and pumps, abrasive to pumps b) Inhalation hazard to applicator while measuring and mixing the concentrated powder c) Require good and constant agitation (usually mechanical) in the spray tank d) Difficult to mix in very hard, alkaline water e) Residues may be visible on treated surfaces</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>g. Aluminium phosphide, EDB, EDCT, MB b) Toxic to a wide range of pests c) Can penetrate cracks, crevices, wood, and tightly packed areas such as soil or stored grains d) Single treatment usually kills most pests in treated area Limitations: a) Fumigants are limited to live plants or products in tight containers b) The target site must be enclosed or covered to prevent the gas from escaping c) Nonspecific, they are highly toxic to humans and all other living organisms d) Require the use of specialized protective equipment, including respirators specifically approved for use with fumigants.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig 11. A typical Pesticide Product label</figDesc><graphic coords="44,60.24,265.44,486.00,417.12" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>of volume of spray fluid per unit area, spraying is classified as:</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>q</head><label></label><figDesc>The rate of application of spray fluid per unit area is determined by four factors: a) Operating pressure b) Size of nozzle orifice c) Swath width d) Speed of the operator Swath width: It is the width of the area sprayed during a spray in one direction. It is space covered effectively by the pattern of the nozzle.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>i</head><label></label><figDesc>) Container: A small sprayer is mostly provided with a builtin container. A good container has number of qualities: (a) The size of container should be such as to provide for about 15 minutes of spraying. (b) The tank should be of non corrosive material such as plastic brass, steel or glass (c) the tank should have rounded corners and bottom to facilitate cleaning (d) the lids and caps to all openings should be leak proof. (e) The container should have strainer in filler hole (f) It should also be possible to drain and clean the container quickly.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="9,156.72,523.68,286.08,199.92" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="11,176.16,464.64,250.08,228.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Compounds and Mode of action Trade name &amp; LD 50 (mg/kg) Formulation Diflubenzuron: Stomach and</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>2) Acetamiprid: It is a systemic insecticide with contact and stomach action. Used as a soil and</cell></row><row><cell>foliar application against Homoptera especially aphids and leafhoppers, Thysanoptera and</cell></row><row><cell>Lepidoptera. LD 50 value: &gt;2000 mg/kg. Formulated as acetamiprid 20 SP (Pride, Profil,</cell></row><row><cell>Supreme).</cell></row><row><cell>3) Thiamethoxam: Contact and stomach poison with translaminar and systemic movement, is</cell></row><row><cell>used as a seed treatment and foliar application against sucking insects. It has very strong</cell></row><row><cell>effect on viral transmitting insects. LD 50 value: 1563 mg/kg. Formulated as thiamethoxam 25</cell></row><row><cell>WG, 70 WS (Actara, Cruiser, Meridian, Rinova).</cell></row><row><cell>4) Clothianidin: It is systemic and translaminar in action. It shows inhibitory action on oviposition</cell></row><row><cell>came to limelight during Second World War. The biological activity of these and feeding. LD 50 value: &gt;5000 mg/kg. Formulated as clothianidin 50 WG (Dantop, Celeso).</cell></row><row><cell>compounds was first discovered by W. Lange and Krueger in 1932. OP compounds as insecticides 5) Thiacloprid: Used as a foliar spray against sucking pests such as aphids, thrips, whitefly,</cell></row><row><cell>were mainly due to the work of Gerhard Schrader in 1937 in Germany. First OP compounds were beetles and leaf miner. It acts as an acute and stomach poison. LD 50 value: 500 mg/kg. Available TEPP (Tetra ethyl pyrophosphate) followed by parathion and Schradan, the first systemic as thiacloprid 36 WG, 70 WG (Calypso, Bariard, Alanto).</cell></row><row><cell>insecticide. Organophosphate insecticides have two most important properties such as higher potency</cell></row><row><cell>and low residual life. These compounds interfere in cholinergic transmission. Organophosphates D) Chitin synthesis inhibitors: Chitin synthesis inhibitors disrupt moulting by blocking the formation</cell></row><row><cell>phosphorylate the enzyme, cholinestrase (ChE) which does not recover readily. Examples: of chitin, the building block of insect exoskeleton. Without the ability to synthesize chitin, moulting</cell></row><row><cell>malathion, methyl parathion, diazinon, dichlorvos, fenitrothion, quinalphos, phosalone, is incomplete, resulting in malformed insects that soon die. It suppresses egglaying and causes</cell></row><row><cell>chlorpyriphos, phosphamidon, monocrotophos, methyl demeton, dimethoate, triazophos, egg sterility in treated adults through secondary hormonal activity. Examples:</cell></row><row><cell>profenophos, acephate, phorate etc.</cell></row><row><cell>Carbamates</cell></row><row><cell>All carbamates are derivatives of carbamic acid. Many of the carbamic esters are insecticidal and contact poison Dimilin 25 WP 4640</cell></row><row><cell>that acts by inhibiting chitin synthesis, thus interferes a few are effective molluscicides. Like organophosphates, the carbamate insecticides interfere in cholinergic transmission. Carbamates have an analogous action, carbamylating rather than with formation of cuticle</cell></row><row><cell>Flufenoxuron: Broad spectrum insect and mite growth phosphorylating the enzyme and the cholinestrase (ChE) recovers more readily from carbamates Cascade10 WDG 3000 than from organophosphates. Thus, unlike, organophosphates, they are known as reversible regulator with contact and stomach action</cell></row><row><cell>Chlorfluazuron: is used in subterranean termite baiting inhibitors, e.g. carbaryl, propoxur (Arprocarb), carbofuran, carbosulfan, thiodicarb, aldicarb, Atabron 5 SC 8500 methomyl etc. stations.</cell></row><row><cell>Triflumuron: Broad spectrum Insect growth regulator C) Neonicotinoids: They represent a novel and distinct chemical class of insecticides with remarkable Starycide 25 WP &gt;5000 Teflubenzuron: It is effective against Lepidoptera, Nomolt, Dart, 2250 chemical and biological properties. They are similar to nicotines in activity, partially to structure. Coleoptera, Diptera, Hymenoptera Aleyrodidae, and Nemolt 15 SC Imidacloprid and other neonicotinoids interact with acetylcholine (Ach) binding site of nicotinic Psyllidae</cell></row><row><cell>Ach receptor which causes excitation and eventually paralysis leading to death of insects. These Novaluron: It acts mainly by ingestion, but has shown Rimon10 EC 5000 are selective and safe to nontarget organisms. Examples: some contact activity. It does not have ovicidal activity,</cell></row><row><cell>1) Imidacloprid: It is a systemic insecticide with translaminar activity and has contact and but a high percentage of mortality of first instars</cell></row><row><cell>stomach action. Used as a seed dressing, soil application and foliar application against sucking hatching from eggs laid on sprayed foliage occurs</cell></row><row><cell>insects including leaf hoppers, plant hoppers, aphids, thrips and whitefly, also effective against Buprofezin: Contact and stomach, persistent chitin Applaud 25 SC, 2198</cell></row><row><cell>synthesis inhibitor with miticidal action. Effective soil insects, termites. It is highly toxic to birds. LD 50 value: 450 mg/kg. Formulated as 70 WP imidacloprid 17.8 SL, 70 WS (Confidor, Gaucho, Admire, Provado). against Homopteran pests</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>It has marked translaminar and systemic activity. It shows a strong repellent antifeedant action on both lepidopterous larvae and mites. It appears to interfere with amine mediated control of nervous and endocrine systems in a variety of ways. It has good ovicidal activity. Non toxic to nontarget organisms except predaceous mites. It is a nonsystemic insecticide and acaricide with contact and respiratory action. It is used to control red spider mites, leaf miners, scale insects, and aphids. Amitraz has been found to have an insect repellent effect, works as an insecticide and also as a pesticide synergist. Less harmful to mammals.</figDesc><table><row><cell>LD 50 value: 340 mg/kg</cell></row><row><cell>Formulations: 50 SP, 4 EC</cell></row><row><cell>Trade names: Galecron, Fundal, Spike</cell></row><row><cell>2. Amitraz:</cell></row></table><note>: Pyrroles are oxidative phosphorylation inhibitors. It works by uncoupling oxidative phosphorylation from electron transport process in mitochondria. Oxidative phosphorylation is the process through which ATP is synthesized in plants and animals. It interferes with formation of ATP which is essential for muscle contraction. Example: Chlorfenapyr: It is an acaricide and insecticide. Chlorfenapyr has broad spectrum of activity against many species of Coleoptera, Lepidoptera, Acarina and Thysanoptera. It is mainly a stomach poison and has contact action also. LD 50 value: 626 mg/kg. Formulation: 3 SC (Pirate, Pylon). K) Formamidines: Formamidines are represented by Chlordimeform and Amitraz with very unique actions by acting as agonists of octapamine receptors. Octapamine act as neurotransmitter, neuromodulator and is involved in energy metabolism and stress responses. Examples: 1. Chlordimeform: LD 50 value: 523 800 mg/kg Formulations: 50 SP, 20 EC Trade names: Acarac, Amitraz, Baam L) Ketoenols:</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>It is active by contact to mite eggs, all nymphal stages and adult females. It is selective, nonsystemic foliar insecticide and acaricide. It is effective against mites and San Jose scale. Spirotetramat is effective against aphids, whiteflies, scales, mealybugs, psylla, phylloxera, thrips, and mites on crops like citrus, vegetables, grapes, potato, other tuberous crops, livestock commodities, and greenhouses/nurseries. It is a systemic insecticide which is sprayed on the plants.</figDesc><table><row><cell>3. Spirotetramat: LD 50 value: &gt;2000 mg/kg</cell></row><row><cell>Formulations: 14.5 SC, 22.4 SC</cell></row><row><cell>Trade names: Movento, Ultor</cell></row><row><cell>LD 50 value: &gt;2500 mg/kg</cell></row><row><cell>Formulations: 2 SC</cell></row><row><cell>Trade names: Envidor</cell></row></table><note>M) Diamides: These include1. Chlorantraniliprole:Chlorantraniliprole is a novel anthranilic diamide insecticide, efficacious for control of lepidopteran insect pests as well as some species in the orders Coleoptera, Diptera and Hemiptera. It is active on chewing pest insects primarily by ingestion and secondarily by contact. It exhibits larvicidal activity as an orally ingested toxicant by targeting and disrupting the Ca 2+ balance. It has low mammalian toxicity. Chlorantraniliprole can be used as foliar spray on insect pests of fruits and vegetable crops @ 10 to 60 g/ha. Trade names: Coragen 20 SC and Altacor 35 WG.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Category Classification Symbol Oral LD 50 Dermal LD 50 &amp; colour of lower (mg/kg body (mg/kg body triangle weight) weight)</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">V. Based on stage specificity</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1. Ovicides e.g. Benzotriazole</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2. Larvicides</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3. Pupicides</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>4. Adulticides</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>VI. Generationwise</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Extremely toxic</cell><cell>Skull &amp; Poison (Red)</cell><cell>150</cell><cell>11200</cell></row><row><cell>Highly toxic</cell><cell>Poison (Yellow)</cell><cell>51500</cell><cell>2012000</cell></row><row><cell>Moderately toxic</cell><cell>Danger (Blue)</cell><cell>5015000</cell><cell>200120,000</cell></row><row><cell>Slightly toxic</cell><cell>Caution (Green)</cell><cell>&gt;5000</cell><cell>&gt;20,000</cell></row></table><note>q First generation Inorganics and Botanicals q Second generation Synthetic organics q Third generation Recent chemicals for reproductive control, IGRs like MH &amp; JH mimics q Fourth generation Synthetic pyrethroids q Fifth generation Chitin synthesis inhibitors, Insect hormones, etc.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Other chemicals classified as pesticides not Function bearing the suffix -cide</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Pests managed</cell></row><row><cell>Algaecide</cell><cell>Algae</cell></row><row><cell>Biocide</cell><cell>Microbial organisms</cell></row><row><cell>Fungicide</cell><cell>Fungi</cell></row><row><cell>Insecticide</cell><cell>Insects and other related animals</cell></row><row><cell>Herbicide/Weedicide</cell><cell>Weeds</cell></row><row><cell>Miticide/Acaricide</cell><cell>Mites</cell></row><row><cell>Nematicides</cell><cell>Nematodes</cell></row><row><cell>Rodenticide</cell><cell>Rodents</cell></row><row><cell>Avicide</cell><cell>Birds</cell></row><row><cell>Piscicide</cell><cell>Fish</cell></row><row><cell>Molluscicide</cell><cell>Slugs and snails</cell></row><row><cell>Ovicide</cell><cell>Eggs of animals</cell></row><row><cell>Growth regular</cell><cell>Modifies plant or insect development</cell></row><row><cell>Defoliant</cell><cell>Removes plant foliage</cell></row><row><cell>Desiccant</cell><cell>Dries plant foliage</cell></row><row><cell>Repellent</cell><cell>Diverts a pest</cell></row><row><cell>Attractant</cell><cell>Lures a pest</cell></row><row><cell>Pheromone</cell><cell>May attract pests or disrupt behaviour</cell></row><row><cell>Sterilant</cell><cell>Renders pest to sterility (unable to reproduce)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Failure to retain pressureLid of the tank may be loose or Tighten the lid and check the the gaskets may be spoiled.gasket and replace it, if necessary.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Defects</cell><cell>Possible causes</cell><cell cols="2">Suggested remedies</cell></row><row><cell>Pressure lower down</cell><cell>a) Clogged suction screens.</cell><cell>a) Clean them.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>b) Loose connections or missing</cell><cell cols="3">b) Find out the specific cause and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>gaskets in suction line or partially</cell><cell cols="2">rectify the fault.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>opened suction valve; broken or</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>leaky suction hose or suction pipe;</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>drain cocks not closed.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>c) Imperfect sealing due to deposition</cell><cell cols="3">c) Cleaning the ball and its seat</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of grains or sand under the ball</cell><cell>usually</cell><cell>improves</cell><cell>t he</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>valve or certain solids on the</cell><cell cols="3">performance of the pump. If</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>surface of the ball or wearingout</cell><cell cols="3">necessary, replace the valve</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>of valve and its seat.</cell><cell cols="2">seat or valve, or both.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>d) Wornout nozzle disc.</cell><cell cols="3">d) Replace the disc. Oft en</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>e) Pump speed slow</cell><cell cols="3">increasing the pump speed is</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">all that is needed to regain</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>pressure.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Leakage</cell><cell>Loose nuts and clamps</cell><cell cols="3">Tighten the nuts and replace the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>or wornout gaskets</cell><cell>gaskets.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Lack of suction</cell><cell>Cup leather (plunger bucket)</cell><cell cols="3">Clean the suction assembly set.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>is either wrinkled or worn out</cell><cell cols="2">Replace the cup leather, if</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>or it is completely dried.</cell><cell cols="3">wrinkled or wornout. If cup</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="3">leather is hard and dry, lubricate</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">with a vegetable oil.</cell></row><row><cell>Difficult working of the</cell><cell>Plunger may be bent through</cell><cell cols="3">Straighten the plunger rod, if</cell></row><row><cell>plunger</cell><cell>the full length of the barrel.</cell><cell>found bent.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Uneven discharge of</cell><cell>Nozzle obstructed.</cell><cell cols="3">Open the nozzle and clean its</cell></row><row><cell>spray</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">various parts, especially the</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>orifice.</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Blowing the nozzle with mouth Repair the leakage Use a funnel Wash sprayer, buckets, measuring jar, etc. after the operation. Change nozzle cone or disc. If not repairable, replace it Dangerous practice. Do not smell the pesticide. Use hand gloves and apron Dangerous practice. Mix pesticide with the help of a stick/rod Dangerous. Wash hands and face with soap and water before smoking, chewing tobacco and drinking water or eating Dangerous activity, source of contamination. Use washed protective clothings every day Not good. Have breakfast or a full meal before the start of the spray Not advisable. Keep away children, cattle and pests from the spraying site Not advisable. Employ male adult labour as spray operator Seal the cuts and open wounds with medicated water proof tape before the start of the spray Dangerous act. Never do it. Wash them away from the water source Dangerous practice. Rinse them with water thoroughly. Break them and bury them away from water source Dangerous practice.</figDesc><table /><note>q</note></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>CHAPTER7</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAFE PESTICIDE HANDLING</head><p>Danger of exposure always exists whenever pesticides are handled. The greatest risk to the applicator is in handling and applying toxic materials and in mixing and loading pesticide concentration. Before beginning pesticide handling activities, be sure and prepare to deal with emergencies such as spills, injuries and poisoning. Emergencies supplies should include atleast; q Personal decontamination equipment and supplies: Clean water, detergent and paper towels in a protected container to allow for fast decontamination in an emergency q First aid equipments q Spill cleanup equipments Remember that pesticides are poisonous and they are to be handled with utmost care. Keep the following things in mind while dealing with the pesticides: A) Purchase q Buy the correct products. Buy only recommended products in required pack for use. Check carefully the brand as well as chemical names q Do not buy damaged packs. Check seals carefully for signs of tampering. Refuse to take any pack that is damaged, leaking or whose seals have been tampered with or which do not possess original labels q Purchase the pesticides from authorized dealer or distributor. This ensures to get a genuine product q Check the date of manufacture and expiry on the pesticide pack. Do not purchase dateexpired stock q Insist on getting a bill q Do not purchase any loose pesticide</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B) Transport</head><p>q Obey laws and regulations regarding transportation of pesticides q Keep pesticides away from passengers, livestock and food stuffs q Load and unload carefully q Transport pesticides alone from retailer shop to the farm house</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>C) Storage</head><p>q Do not store pesticide along with food or animal feeds q Keep pesticides under lock and key away from children and animals q Keep in a cool dry place. Check labels for advice on storage. Keep away from fires and direct sunlight q Never store pesticides for farm use in living quarters q Inspect package regularly for leaks and signs of damage q Do not store pesticides in a damp room q Do not store pesticides on the floor. Instead store them in a rack q Do not store pesticides in refilled packs. Store in original packs q Do not store empty containers on the floor but break them and keep in a drum till their destruction q Do not store pesticides along with seeds q Do not eat, drink, smoke or chew tobacco in the pesticide store q Do not have temporary and old electric wiring connection in pesticide store</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>D) Measuring and mixing of pesticides q</head><p>Always adhere to the recommended doses and dilutions q Read the label and instructions leaflet carefully to determine the proper dose rate, mixing instructions and equipments to be used q Ready for use solid/liquid products such as dusts, granules and ULV sprays can be tipped or scooped from their packs directly into application equipment q Do not use bare hands while handling pesticides q The tank should be filled with water to the correct level and mixed with a stick q Do not fill sprayers upto the brim, they may spill during use q If a stock or spray liquid is being prepared, do not make up more than what can be used up during the same day. Avoid keeping spray liquid overnight q Wear protective clothing while spraying q Do not measure out or mix pesticides in or near houses or where livestock are kept q Take care not to contaminate water supplies or puddles from which animals may drink q Use suitable equipments for measuring pesticides q</p><p>Use buckets or open topped drum and use stick or paddle for mixing q Never suck liquid pesticide with mouth, even with a tube q Handle dusts and wettable powders carefully to avoid fluffing up q Wash all equipments after use q Mixing vessels and measures used for pesticides must not be used for any other purpose q Closeup packages after use to prevent leakage or contamination and store safely q Small quantities of leftover and unwanted concentrates should be tipped into a hole in the ground away from dwellings, wells, water ways and crops E) Application equipment -Use, maintenance and repair q Clean and check equipment at the end of each day's operations. Pay particular attention to thorough cleaning of the equipment especially if not to be used again for sometime because residual pesticides may cause corrosion and clogging q Take the most needed spare parts and tools into the field, so that running repairs can be</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
