<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">10 . Application for Grant Provisional Fire Safety Certificate Department of Local Government</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Punjab 11. Application for Grant Final Fire Safety Certificate Department of Local Government</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Punjab</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">Water Connection Department of Local Government</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Punjab</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff2">
								<orgName type="department">Sewer Connection Department of Local Government</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Punjab</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff3">
								<orgName type="department" key="dep1">Notice of Completion and Part Completion Department of Housing and Urban Development 7. Notice of Permission to Occupy Department of Housing and Urban Development 8. Building Plan Approvals Department of Local Government</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep2">Approvals Department of Labour</orgName>
								<orgName type="department" key="dep3">Punjab 10. Building Plan Approvals (Factories) Department of Labour</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>Punjab 9. Building Plan, Punjab 11</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff4">
								<orgName type="department">Renewal of License for Cold Storage Department of Food Processing</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>Punjab</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff5">
								<orgName type="department">Economic Division Ministry of Food Processing Industries</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">Government of India Panchsheel Bhawan</orgName>
								<address>
									<settlement>New Delhi -110049</settlement>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">B697C6A74854C4F331D7CD551F9E1EE6</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Growth and Linkages in the Indian Food Processing Sector:</head><p>The Indian food-processing sector has witnessed remarkable growth, during the last 9 years ending 2023-24, Food Processing Industries sector has been growing at an Average Annual Growth Rate (AAGR) of around 6.55% as compared to around 6.06% in manufacturing at 2011-12 prices. The sector constituted as much as 7.93% share of FPI in the manufacturing sector in 2023-2024. The sector is one of the largest employment providers in the organized manufacturing sector with 12.91% employment in the total registered/organized sector. This highlights its competitiveness and capacity to cater to global markets.</p><p>India is the world's largest producer of milk, pulses and jute and ranks as the second largest producer of rice, wheat, sugarcane, groundnut, vegetables, fruit and cotton. It is also one of the leading producers of spices, fish, poultry, livestock and plantation crops. This abundant raw material base offers immense potential for value addition and export. Notably, India reported the processed food exports amounted to USD 10.09 billion in 2024-2025 with significant shares in processed vegetables and fruits, pulses, cereal preparations etc. Further, the sector has attracted 7.21 billion FDI inflow in the last one-decade ending 2024-25. Recognizing the sector's significance, the Ministry of Food Processing Industries has extended support and incentives for creation of modern infrastructure with efficient supply chain management, creation of employment opportunities, reducing post-harvest losses, increasing the processing level and enhancing export of processed foods.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agricultural Strength and Economic Advantages of Punjab:</head><p>Punjab, a State known for its strong agricultural sector and robust economy, registered a Gross State Domestic Product (GSDP) of USD 87.32 billion at current prices in 2023-24. Punjab's GSDP grew at an average rate of 5.2% between 2015-16 and 2023-24. Agriculture and allied activities continue to play a crucial role in State's Gross State Value Added (GSVA) and are expected to contribute a share of 25% of Punjab's GSVA in 2024-25. <ref type="bibr">1</ref> Punjab has achieved several milestones, such as being the first State to implement barcode-based traceability on packaging. It has been classified as an "Fast Mover" within the Landlocked cluster based on the DPIIT's LEADS 2024 assessment<ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">2</ref> . Furthermore, Punjab has emerged as 'top performer' in the start-up ecosystem, as indicated by the Start-up Ranking Results of 2022<ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">3</ref> . Punjab is also known as the "Food Bowl of India" due to its significant contribution to India's agricultural output.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Diverse Opportunities in Food Processing:</head><p>Punjab has a wide range of prospects in the food processing industry ranging from millets, milk, Basmati (Rice), grains, fruits, and vegetables. The State holds prominent positions in agricultural production, being the largest producer of carrots, pears and peaches in the country. Punjab also ranks third in the production of wheat, radish, cucumber, peas, and honey. The rice yield will be raised to 82 quintals per hectare and the wheat yield to 66 quintals per hectare by 2047. <ref type="bibr">4</ref> These achievements highlight Punjab's significant contribution to the agricultural landscape of India and its potential for further growth and development in the food processing industry.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Overview</head><p>Punjab is situated in the northern region of India and is also known by the popular sobriquet "land of five rivers". Punjab shares borders with Jammu and Kashmir, Himachal Pradesh, Haryana, Rajasthan as well as international border with Pakistan. The capital city of Punjab is Chandigarh, the Union Territory. The economy of Punjab is predominantly based on agriculture, which is the mainstay of the State's economy. Punjab is recognized as the "Food Bowl of India," as it accounts for approximately two-thirds of the total production of food grains. Agro and Food Processing is a crucial economic sector in Punjab. The State has fertile soil for agriculture, and the primary crops grown are paddy, wheat, and maize. For enhancing the area under maize to five lakh hectares by 2025, there is a need to augment its use as feed in poultry and dairy farming. <ref type="bibr">5</ref> Additionally, Punjab produces a variety of fruits such as kinnow, peach, pear, and honey, and vegetables such as potato, peas, cabbage, carrot, and cauliflower.  2 nd highest tele-density in the country -higher than the national level  "Food Bowl of India" due to its significant contribution to the country's agricultural output  Highest area under irrigation, with 98% of the net irrigated area  High cropping intensity at 191.7%, which is higher than the national average of 152.7%</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Local Food System</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Indigenous Produce</head><p>Punjab (land of the five rivers) is one of the most fertile regions on earth. The state has diverse agriclimate zones which are favourable to horticulture crops such as Kinnow, Sweet Orange, Guava, Pear, Peach etc. Punjab also enjoys the status of being 'India's granary' and contributes to 9.57% and 15.18% of country's rice and wheat production respectively. <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">18</ref> Punjab has been also focusing on fresh water fish production in 2023-24, the state produced 203.67 million fish seed and achieved the target of 0.18 million tonnes of fish production. The shrimp farming in fresh water has increased to more than 2,793 tonnes in 1,315.82 acres. <ref type="bibr">19</ref> The state produced 14.00 million tonnes of milk in 2023-24 <ref type="bibr">20</ref>  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Production Clusters</head><p>The list below showcases the Production Clusters within the State of Punjab as approved under the Pradhan Mantri Formalisation of Micro Food Processing Enterprises Scheme (PMFME) of Ministry of Food Processing Industries, Government of India: </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Agricultural Marketing</head><p>The Punjab State Agriculture Marketing Board (Punjab Mandi Board) was established in 1961 with an objective to control and supervise the marketing network of sale, purchase, storage and processing of processed or non-processed agricultural produce so notified from agricultural, horticulture, animal husbandry and forest produce. The board aims to enhance the agricultural marketing system and improve its efficiency by focussing on coordinating the work of Mandi Parishad/Mandi Committees. By 2047, all regulated 'mandis' and sub-yards will be connected to e-NAM portal for price discovery, higher price realization of farm produce and notify more number and location of warehouses for storage purposes.</p><p>The target is to expand the network of markets in the coming 15 years and to increase the number of regulated markets to 200 by 2047.  Opportunities exist in manufacturing of frozen fruits and vegetables, read to eat/cook products, Juice (Kinnow, guava), Guava candy, Pear jam/murrabah, Potato chips, Tomato puree/ketchup etc.</p><p> The following vision in the coming fifteen years may be adopted to diversify agriculture and raise the income of farmers:</p><p> Area Expansion under Horticulture Crops: The department proposes to bring an addition of 1,30,000 hectares area under horticulture crops by 2030. The area under vegetables and fruits will be expanded to six lakh hectares by 2047. For achieving this target vegetable and fruit cultivation will be further improved by providing high-quality yielding seeds of vegetables and plants of fruits to farmers. Crop improvement research efforts in the case of vegetable crops will continue to be targeted at harnessing premium marketing, nutritional, consumer preference and other commercial traits. The cultivation of specific vegetables that have a longer shelf-life and high and continuous demand in big urban centres will be promoted by assured marketing at a remunerative price and easy safe transportation to big urban centres.</p><p>  The shrimp culture will be promoted by raising the area under it to 2800 hectares (7,000 acres) by 2030. <ref type="bibr">52</ref>  There are opportunities in shrimp farming, re-circulatory aquaculture system, bio-floc systems, fish feed mills, value-addition etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">State Government Initiatives and Schemes</head><p>State Government has undertaken several reforms to offer an enabling and investor-friendly business climate for investors keen on setting up business in the State.</p><p>'Punjab business first portal' is a single window portal which was awarded silver recognition under Digital initiative for ease of doing business as the same is integrated to national single window system.</p><p>The portal offers a one-stop solution to investors in obtaining all State-related regulatory approvals and fiscal incentives. Smart dashboards for applying incentives and end to end online &amp; transparent system tracing the application processes is also a major highlight of the system.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_18">53</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.1">State Industrial Land Bank</head><p>The facility is a GIS system created to showcase land and infrastructure availability for businesses.</p><p>The system has information related to, Government owned factories and offices, and shows the land costs, tariffs, how easy it is to get there, and what utilities (like electricity and water) are available.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_19">54</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.2">Central Industrial Land Bank Portal</head><p>Industrial parks serving as a one-stop repository of all infrastructure-related information such as connectivity, infra, natural resources and terrain, plot-level information on vacant plots, and contact details.<ref type="foot" target="#foot_20">55</ref> </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.3">Supporting MSMEs across sectors through attractive incentives available under Punjab Industrial &amp; Business Development Policy 2022.</head><p>The state has also extended MSE facilitation councils to support resolution of payment issues.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.4">Punjab Anti-Red Tape Act, 2021</head><p>The State Government has implemented the said act to eliminate red-tapism and improve ease of doing business in the State. The Act mandates reduction of the compliance burden to businesses and citizens.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.5">Public Procurement (Preference to Make in Punjab) Order, 2019</head><p>Government of Punjab launched the initiative to boost the manufacturing sector through incentivizing local value addition by providing them a purchase preference done by the State Government departments and its agencies.</p><p>Punjab is one of the most preferable places for establishment of food and allied industries as the State offers robust infrastructure, skilled labour, ease of logistics, reduced compliance through various initiatives, speedy approvals and incentives. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Recurring Expense Reimbursement</head><p>Operational Subsidy assistance up to Rs 3 lakh/year for 5 years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Mentoring &amp; Training</head><p>Mentoring Assistance support up to Rs 3 lakh per year for 5 years to address priority issues like fundraising, scaling, recruitment, and product interface.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Startup Competition Assistance</head><p>Assistance up to Rs 5 lakh per event for organizing startup competition fest to encourage the entrepreneurship culture in colleges.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B.</head><p>Start-up Units</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.</head><p>Interest Subsidy 8% per annum interest subsidy for 5 years, on loans obtained from scheduled banks/financial institutions, with a maximum limit of Rs 5 lakh per year. No separate interest subsidy will be provided as MSME.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Lease rental subsidy</head><p>Reimbursement of 25% of lease rental subsidy, up to Rs 3 lakh per annum for 1 year</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Seed Funding</head><p>Seed Grant up to Rs 3 lakh per startup for validation of idea, prototype development, assistance towards travelling costs and carrying out field/ market research/ skill training/ marketing and initial activities to setup a Startup etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Scale up Funding</head><p>Facilitation of Venture Capital through Punjab Innovation Fund, which will have a dedicated fund of Rs 150 Cr to facilitate venture capital. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Reimbursement from Stamp</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : Punjab Overview</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>State Capital</cell><cell>Chandigarh</cell></row><row><cell>Geographic Area 6</cell><cell>50,362 sq. km</cell></row><row><cell>Population (Census 2011) 7</cell><cell>27.74 million</cell></row><row><cell>Total Road Length (March 2019) 8</cell><cell>1,47,862 kms</cell></row><row><cell>Gross State Domestic Product (GSDP) at current prices 9 , 2023-24</cell><cell>USD 89.33 billion</cell></row><row><cell>Airport 10</cell><cell>2 International Airports-Chandigarh &amp; Amritsar</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>3 Domestic Airports-Bathinda, Ludhiana, Pathankot</cell></row><row><cell>Rail network (2023) 11</cell><cell>2,265 kms</cell></row><row><cell>Industrial Area</cell><cell>No of industrial parks: 63 12 No of operational SEZ: 3 13</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2 Air Cargo Terminal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>8 Inland Container Depot (ICD)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>6 Private Freight Terminal (PFT)</cell></row><row><cell>Infrastructure 14</cell><cell>78 Railway Goods Sheds</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2.35 million MT Cold Storage Capacity</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>5.85 million MT Warehouse Capacity</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>3 Integrated Check Posts / Land Customs Station</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>3 Multi-Modal Logistics Parks</cell></row><row><cell>Installed Power 15</cell><cell>14455.87 MW</cell></row><row><cell>Available land 16</cell><cell>1974.53 ha</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>th largest milk producer in India 32 3.3. Key production statistics: Table 2: Crops ('000 MT) 33 , 2023-24 S.No. Particulars Production</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>. Punjab's per capita milk availability (1,245 grams/day) is three times higher than the national average (471 grams/day) 21 . The State Government is making efforts to develop Punjab as the 'Model Dairy State of India'. Punjab also produced 4.70 billion eggs and 0.26 million MT of meat in 2023-24. 22 The milk, egg and meat production have registered an annual growth rate of 3.78%, 3.18%, 4.95% respectively in 2023-24. 23 3.2. Key Production highlights  Highest yield/productivity of paddy across states in India 24  Largest producer of Carrots Pear and Peaches 25  2 nd largest producer of Raddish 26  3 rd largest producer of Mandarin (Kinnow, Orange) 27  3 rd largest producer of Wheat 28  4 th largest producer of Paddy 29  3 rd largest producer of Peas 30  4 th largest producer of Muskmelon 31 Wheat 17,737.2 2. Rice 14,356.0 3. Sugarcane 7,509.5  6 1. 4. Total Foodgrains 32,544.0</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>Table 3 : Fruits ('000 MT) 34 , 2023-24 S.No. Particulars Production</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Mandarin/Kinnow</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 4 : Vegetables ('000 MT) 35 , 2023-24 S.No. Particulars Production</head><label>4</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Potato</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 : Spices ('000 MT) 36 , 2023-24 S.No. Particulars Production</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Garlic</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 6 : Livestock 37 , 2023-24 &amp; Fisheries S.No. Particulars Production</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Milk ('000 MT)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 7 : List of One District One Product (ODOP) under PMFME Scheme 39 : ODOP District</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Pickle &amp; Murabba</cell><cell>Amritsar</cell></row><row><cell>Meat/ Chicken/ Poultry based products</cell><cell>Barnala</cell></row><row><cell>Honey based products</cell><cell>Bathinda</cell></row><row><cell>Jaggery &amp; allied products</cell><cell>Fatehgarh Sahib, Hoshiarpur</cell></row><row><cell>Kinnow based products</cell><cell>Fazilka</cell></row><row><cell>Milk based products</cell><cell>Faridkot, Mansa, Sri Mukatsar Sahib</cell></row><row><cell>Chillies based products</cell><cell>Ferozpur</cell></row><row><cell>Sugarcane based products</cell><cell>Gurdaspur, Sahibzada Ajit Singh Nagar</cell></row><row><cell>Potato based products</cell><cell>Jalandhar, Moga</cell></row><row><cell>Tomato products</cell><cell>Kapurthala</cell></row><row><cell>Animal feed</cell><cell>Malerkotla</cell></row><row><cell>Litchi based products</cell><cell>Pathankot</cell></row><row><cell>Guava based products</cell><cell>Patiala</cell></row><row><cell>Mango based products</cell><cell>Roopnagar</cell></row><row><cell>Mushroom</cell><cell>Sangrur</cell></row><row><cell>Peas based products</cell><cell>Shaheed Bhagat Singh Nagar</cell></row><row><cell>Pear based products</cell><cell>Tarntaran</cell></row><row><cell>Bakery products</cell><cell>Ludhiana</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>40    Punjab is blessed to have a wide variety of crops and horticulture production due to a combination of factors including excellent soil fertility, robust infrastructure, State Government's initiatives for adoption of technologies. While wheat and rice are the primary crops in Punjab, the State produces a range of fruits and vegetables, dairy, poultry &amp; meat products. Given the overall agro-climatic and socioeconomic profile of the State, processing of these produce offers enormous opportunities to potential investors.46    Punjab is the 6 th largest producer of milk in India and contributes around 6.20% of the total milk production. The milk production in Punjab in the year 2023-24 was of 14.00 million tonnes. The Government has implemented extensive veterinary infrastructure for animal healthcare and is making special efforts to develop Punjab as a "Model Dairy State of India".</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">6. Potential Opportunities</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">6.1. Dairy Product</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Punjab Agriculture Markets</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">S.No. Particulars</cell><cell>Details</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Notified market areas / APMCs 41</cell><cell>154</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Sub-market yards 42</cell><cell>283</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell>eNAM mandis 43</cell><cell>79</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Food Processing Industries 44</cell><cell>3457</cell></row><row><cell>5.</cell><cell>Farmer Producer Organizations 45</cell><cell>76</cell></row></table><note> The Punjab State Cooperative Milk Producers Federation Limited popularly known as 'MILKFED' was established in 1973 for improving dairy farming in the state, promoting production, providing technical inputs, procurement and processing of milk for the economic development of milk producers.  Opportunities exist in value-added dairy products such as butter, ghee, curd, cheese, ice cream, Infant Food, etc.  Hence, with the present pace of growth in milk production, readiness to commercialize and adoption of new technologies by the Department and Dairy farmers, Punjab -"Dairy and Breeder State" can be visualized to double the milk production by 2047. 47 6.2. Fruits &amp; vegetables  Punjab has diverse agro-climatic zones which are favourable to production of various fruits such as Kinnow, Sweet Orange, Guava, Pear, Litchi, Mango and Peach. The total production of fruits in 2023-24 was 2.50 million tonnes. Top three fruits with the highest production recorded in 2023-24 were Kinnow, Guava and Mangoes.  Horticulture Department of Punjab has identified a 100 acres land at Attari for the establishment of Post Graduate Institute of Horticulture Research and Education in Amritsar. The institute will be established by Indian Council for Agriculture Research (ICAR) in collaboration with the Punjab Government. Five Citrus Estates have been established in Bhunga (Hoshiarpur), Badal (Sri Muktsar Sahib), Abohar and Tahliwala Jattan (Fazilka).</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Mushroom Production: Presently, 5044 tonnes of mushroom are being produced in Punjab, which is 4.20% of the national production. In this background, 70 more such mushroom units are proposed to be established in Punjab by 2030. Pea being the important vegetables, covers an area of 22,149 hectares with an annual production of 2.28 lakh MT. Amritsar, Hoshiarpur, Shaheed Bhagat Singh Nagar and Patiala are major growing districts in Punjab. It is proposed to establish Pea Estate at Hoshiarpur where world-class facilities will be provided. Fresh water fisheries sector has emerged as one of the import sectors in the State of Punjab in recent years. Special efforts are being made to bring saline affected waterlogged wasteland of southwestern district of Sri Muktsar Sahib, Ferozepur, Mansa, Fazilka, Bathinda and Faridkot under fish culture. As per the vision of the Directorate of Fisheries, the target is to raise the area under fishery up to 40,000 hectares by 2030 and 60,000 hectares by 2047. This will raise fish production to 3 lakh tonnes by 2030 and to 6 lakh tonnes by 2047.50     Starting from 1 acre area in 2016, shrimp farming has expanded to 1315.82 acres area in the year 2023-24. The shrimp production in the state has increased to more than 2,793 tonnes in 2023-24 in comparison to 2400 tonnes last year. Increasing shrimp production will create opportunities for shrimp processing in the near future.51    </figDesc><table><row><cell>6.4. Fisheries</cell></row><row><cell>  In the year 2023-24, Punjab produced 203.67 million fish seed, 40,406.05 acres (16,351.74</cell></row><row><cell>hectares) of existing land was kept under fish culture and 3,566.70 acres (1,443.39 hectares) of</cell></row><row><cell>new land was brought under fish culture. The goal of 1,81,188.7 tons of fish production was</cell></row><row><cell>accomplished in 2023-2024. 49</cell></row><row><cell></cell></row><row><cell> Presently, major Export Destinations are Oman, Maldives, Indonesia, Vietnam, Bhutan, Japan</cell></row><row><cell>and Russia and with growth in sector, export will increase.</cell></row><row><cell> Hence, with the present pace of growth in production, readiness to commercialize and adoption</cell></row><row><cell>of new technologies by the Department and poultry owners, state can be visualized to double</cell></row><row><cell>poultry production (egg and meat) by 2047. Egg production expected to reach 14.23 billion</cell></row><row><cell>eggs by 2027. 48</cell></row></table><note> Establishment of Pea Estate: 6.3. Poultry  Poultry population in Punjab is 174.26 lakhs. Poultry farming is a popular and profitable activity in the state. In 2023-24, the egg and meat production have registered growth of 3.18% and 4.95% respectively as compared to the previous year.  Meat and egg production in 2023-24 was 0.263 million tonnes and 4.70 billion eggs respectively.  In Punjab, NABARD plays an active role in Poultry Development by Poultry Venture Capital Funds -A Central Sector Plan Scheme in which commercial layer and broiler unit, backyard poultry, Feed mixing units, transport vehicles-open cage and refrigerated are provided for expansion of the sector.  Active institutions supporting the Poultry Co-operatives are National Agricultural Co-operative Marketing Federation, National Co-operative Development Corporation, National Scheduled Caste and Scheduled Tribe Finance and Development Corporation, Poultry Egg and Meat Production Co-operatives and Poultry Federation of India  Opportunities exist in processing &amp; value-addition, frozen/chilled products, Ready to cook and eat products, new technologies for meat &amp; poultry processing etc.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Table 8 : Key incentives available for the food processing industry under major policies 56 : S.No Key Initiatives Punjab Industrial &amp; Business Development Policy 2022</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>A.</cell><cell>Incubators</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Nature of Incentive</cell><cell>Extent of Incentive</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Govt. Host Institutes: 100% capital grant of FCI, up to Rs 1</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Capital Investment subsidy</cell><cell>Crore. Private Host Institutes &amp; Stand-alone Incubators: 50%</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>capital grant of FCI, up to Rs 50 lakh</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head>Fiscal Incentives for MSME Units: Access to finance</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>9.</cell><cell>5. 1. F.</cell><cell cols="3">Additional State Support of reimbursement of guarantee fee charged under CGTMSE Scheme Food Processing Industries Additional Sector-Specific Special Incentives 100% reimbursement of guaranteed fee, up to Rs 2 lakhs per industries of commercial production State taxes and fees on raw material for food processing year for 5 years to micro and small enterprises from the date Exemption of market fee, rural development fee, and other</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Financial assistance to</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="5">6. 8. Regulatory framework: Registration / NOCs / Licenses MSMEs for 'Emerge' exchange platform set up by 25% of the cost of Public Issue expenses, up to Rs 10 lakhs</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">NSE Table below represents the indicative information regarding Regulatory Mechanism available in the Access to Technology Assistance for Technology State of Punjab: 50% of the cost, up to Rs 25 lakhs, for adopting technology 1. Acquisition from a recognized National Institute. 8.1. For starting operations</cell></row><row><cell cols="5">Additional support to ZED Table 9: Regulatory mechanism for setting operations Reimbursement of 50% of expenses, up to Rs 5 lakh, incurred on plant and machinery/testing equipment for obtaining at 2. scheme of GOI least gold category status under ZED scheme to First 100 units. Reimbursement of expenses Authority/ Agency/ Office/ S.No. Name of Service Department officer granting approval 75% reimbursement up to Rs 1.5 lakh each for 3. incurred for Audits energy/environment/steam audit/water audit and Safety Audit 1. License for Cold Storage Directorate of Food Processing</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">50% financial support, up to a maximum of Rs 25 lakh, for</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>4.</cell><cell cols="3">Assistance for Environmental Compliance Registration under FSSAI Act,2006, setting up effluent treatment plants, installing Water Pollution Control Devices, and implementing zero liquid discharge FSSAI, Health &amp; Family Welfare regulation 2011 Department, &amp; Food Safety</cell></row><row><cell>3. 4. 5.</cell><cell>5.</cell><cell cols="3">technology once during the validity period of the Policy. (a) For industries using surface water for 50% of their License under FSSAI Act,2006, regulation Exemption from Ground Extraction Charges for new MSME units FSSAI, Health &amp; Family Welfare 2011 Department, &amp; Food Safety total water requirement, a 25% exemption from ground water charges for 7 years from the date of commercial production. (b) License under Contract Labour Act, Labour Commissionerate (Regulation and Abolition), 1970 The Department of Water Resources will work with the Punjab Water Resource Development Authority to rationalize the ground water charges. Registration under GST (Goods and Services Tax Rules, 2017) Department of Goods and Services Tax</cell></row><row><cell>6.</cell><cell>D.</cell><cell cols="2">Fiscal Incentives for Large Units Consent to Operate (CTO)-Air</cell><cell>Punjab Pollution Control Board</cell></row><row><cell>7.</cell><cell>1.</cell><cell>Investment subsidy (reimbursement of net SGST) Consent to Operate (CTO)-Water</cell><cell cols="2">75% of net SGST for 7 years from the date of commercial production, capped at 100% of Fixed Capital Investment Punjab Pollution Control Board</cell></row><row><cell>8. 9.</cell><cell>2. C. 1. 2. 3. 4. 4. 3. 2. 1. E. 4. 3.</cell><cell cols="3">Duty Exemption from Electricity Hazardous Waste Management Duty Investment subsidy (reimbursement of net SGST) Capital subsidy to New Micro and Small manufacturing enterprises Interest Subsidy for Border Districts, Kandi Areas, and Additional State Support of interest subsidy under CLCSS from CLU/EDC Exemption/reimbursement from Stamp Duty Exemption/reimbursement Women and SC Enterprises Duty Exemption from Electricity (reimbursement of net SGST) Investment subsidy Fiscal Incentives for Units in Thrust Sectors 100% reimbursement from Stamp Duty on registration of MoA/AoA for Punjab-based startups. 100% exemption for 10 years up to 100% of FCI or power Punjab Pollution Control Board consumption corresponding to installed capacity, whichever is lower 100% reimbursement of net SGST for 7 years from the date 50% of Fixed Capital Investment, up to Rs 50 Lakh per unit Mansa, Muktsar, Sangrur, Malerkotla, Barnala), and 20% of 5% interest subsidy, up to Rs 5 lakhs per year for 5 years, for (CLU) and External Development Charges (EDC) 100% exemption / reimbursement from Change of Land Use units eligible under CLCSS scheme. and building purchase or lease 100% exemption / reimbursement from Stamp Duty for land 5% per annum interest subsidy, up to Rs 5 lakhs per year for 5 years. is lower consumption corresponding to installed capacity, whichever 100% exemption for 10 years up to 100% of FCI or power FCI, up to Rs 50 Lakhs in other districts. production, capped at 125% of FCI 100% of net SGST for 10 years from the date of commercial Aspirational Districts, and Districts Bathinda, Faridkot, in specified districts (Border districts, Kandi areas, production (excluding service industries) Exemption from Property Tax 50% exemption for 7 years from the date of commercial of commercial production, capped at 100% of FCI. Exemption/reimbursement from Stamp Duty 100% exemption/reimbursement from Stamp Duty for land and building purchase or lease Application for Registration / Grant of Factory Licence under the Factories Act 1948 Department of Labour, Punjab</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>5.</cell><cell>Exemption from Property Tax</cell><cell cols="2">100% exemption for 10 years from the date of commercial production (excluding service industries)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Major Players in Food Processing and Allied Sectors 9.1 Beneficiaries under the Production Linked Incentive Scheme (PLIS) of MoFPI, Government of India Table 11: Details of operational units under PLI Scheme Beneficiary Name Name of the scheme Sector</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>District</cell><cell>Status</cell></row><row><cell>DEL MONTE FOODS</cell><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell cols="2">Fruits &amp; Vegetables Ludhiana</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>PRIVATE LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>HINDUSTAN</cell><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell cols="2">Fruits &amp; Vegetables Patiala</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>UNILEVER LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>TATA CONSUMER</cell><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell cols="2">Fruits &amp; Vegetables Ludhiana</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>PRODUCTS LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>VARUN BEVERAGES</cell><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell cols="3">Fruits &amp; Vegetables Pathankot Operational</cell></row><row><cell>LTD.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>GUJARAT CO-</cell><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>RTC/RTE</cell><cell>Ludhiana</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>OPERATIVE MILK</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MARKETING</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>FEDERATION LTD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>HINDUSTAN</cell><cell>PLISMBP</cell><cell>Millet LE</cell><cell cols="2">Kapurthala Operational</cell></row><row><cell>UNILEVER LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MRS BECTORS FOOD</cell><cell>PLISMBP</cell><cell>Millet LE</cell><cell>Patiala</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>SPECIALITIES LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>ISCON BALAJI FOODS</cell><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell cols="2">Fruits &amp; Vegetables Ludhiana</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>PRIVATE LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MRS BECTORS FOOD</cell><cell>PLISMBP</cell><cell>Millet LE</cell><cell>Jalandhar</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>SPECIALITIES LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>9.2.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_12"><head>Beneficiaries of under Pradhan Mantri Kisan Sampada Yojana (PMKSY) of MoFPI, Government of India Table 12: Details of operational units under Mega Food Park Scheme S.No. Name of the firm Location Sector</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>International Mega Food Park Ltd. , Fazilka, Punjab</cell><cell>Fazilka</cell><cell>Fruits &amp; Vegetables, Grains Milling, Dairy Products</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Sukhjit Mega Food Park &amp; Infra Ltd. Kapurthala</cell><cell>Kapurthala</cell><cell>Fruits &amp; Vegetables, Grains Milling, Dairy Products</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 13 : Details of projects under Agro-Processing Clusters Scheme (APC) Scheme S.No. Name of Firm</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Location</cell><cell>Sector</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="1" xml:id="foot_0">https://finance.punjab.gov.in/uploads/26Mar2025/61da0595-913c-4e9d-8731-023538dc91cd.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="2" xml:id="foot_1"> DPIIT LEADS 2024   </note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_2">https://www.startupindia.gov.in/srf-2022/</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="4" xml:id="foot_3">https://punjab.gov.in/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Punjab_Vision_Docuement_2047.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_4">https://punjab.gov.in/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Punjab_Vision_Docuement_2047.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="16" xml:id="foot_5">https://iis.ncog.gov.in/parks/login1</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="40" xml:id="foot_6">https://punjab.gov.in/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Punjab_Vision_Docuement_2047.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="41" xml:id="foot_7">https://mandiboard.nic.in/</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="42" xml:id="foot_8">https://punjab.gov.in/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Punjab_Vision_Docuement_2047.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="43" xml:id="foot_9">https://www.pib.gov.in/PressReleasePage.aspx?PRID=2086484&amp;utm_source=chatgpt.com</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="44" xml:id="foot_10">Annual Survey of Industries 2022-23</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="45" xml:id="foot_11">State wise list of registered FPOs details under Central Sector Scheme for Formation and Promotion of 10,000 FPOs by SFAC as on 24-02-2025.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="46" xml:id="foot_12">https://finance.punjab.gov.in/uploads/26Mar2025/61da0595-913c-4e9d-8731-023538dc91cd.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="48" xml:id="foot_13">https://punjab.gov.in/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Punjab_Vision_Docuement_2047.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="49" xml:id="foot_14">https://finance.punjab.gov.in/uploads/26Mar2025/61da0595-913c-4e9d-8731-023538dc91cd.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="50" xml:id="foot_15">https://punjab.gov.in/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Punjab_Vision_Docuement_2047.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="51" xml:id="foot_16">https://finance.punjab.gov.in/uploads/26Mar2025/61da0595-913c-4e9d-8731-023538dc91cd.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="52" xml:id="foot_17">https://punjab.gov.in/wp-content/uploads/2025/02/Punjab_Vision_Docuement_2047.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="53" xml:id="foot_18">https://pbindustries.gov.in/static/</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="54" xml:id="foot_19">http://investpunjab.gov.in/home</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="55" xml:id="foot_20">https://iis.ncog.gov.in/IIS/login1</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="56" xml:id="foot_21">https://punjabinfotech.in/assets/pdf/Industrial_Policy_2022.pdf</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclaimer</head><p>Without limiting the rights under the copyright reserved, this publication or any part of it may not be translated, reproduced, stored, transmitted in any form (electronic, mechanical, photocopying, audio recording or otherwise) or circulated in any binding or cover other than the cover in which it is currently published, without the prior written permission of MoFPI.</p><p>All information, ideas, views, opinions, estimates, advice, suggestions, and recommendations (hereinafter 'content') in this publication should not be understood as professional advice in any manner or interpreted as policies, objectives, opinions, or suggestions of Ernst &amp; Young LLP. Readers are advised to use their discretion and seek professional advice before taking any action or decision, based on the contents of this publication. The content in this publication has been obtained or derived from sources believed to be reliable but MoFPI does not represent this information to be accurate or complete. MoFPI does not assume any responsibility and disclaim any liability for any loss, or damages caused due to any reason whatsoever, towards any person (natural or legal) who uses this publication.</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">14 Integrated Logistics &amp; Logistics Park Policy</title>
		<ptr target="https://cea.nic.in/wp-content/uploads/installed/2024/03/IC_Mar_2024_allocation_wise.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">15 Central Electricity Authority -All India Installed Capacity Report</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2023-04">2023. April 2024</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2022</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>9 ibid 10 Northern Region Airports | AIRPORTS AUTHORITY OF INDIA 11</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title/>
		<ptr target="https://dahd.gov.in/sites/default/files/2025-01/FinalBAHS2024Book14012025.pdf33https://rbidocs.rbi.org.in/rdocs/Publications/PDFs/HANDBOOK09122024426229B8B51C4BDE99607F1ADC64154A.PDF34https://agriwelfare.gov.in/sites/default/files/2023_24_FinalEstimates.xls35ibid36ibid37https://dahd.gov.in/sites/default/files/2025-01/FinalBAHS2024Book14012025.pdf38https://dof.gov.in/sites/default/files/2024-06/Handbook.pdf" />
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Punjab Economic Survey</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">32</biblScope>
			<date type="published" when="2024">2024. 26Mar2025/61da0595-913c-4e9d-8731-023538dc91cd.pdf 19. 26Mar2025/61da0595-913c-4e9d-8731-023538dc91cd.pdf 20. 26Mar2025/61da0595-913c-4e9d-8731-023538dc91cd.pdf 21</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>PDF 29 ibid 30 https://agriwelfare.gov.in/sites/default/files/2023_24_FinalEstimates.xls 31 ibid</note>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
