<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3D8F823E86FEACECA65E50A1A8C1AAA7</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><formula xml:id="formula_0">- - - - - - - - - Greengram - - - - - - - - - Cotton - - - - - - - - - Wheat - - 472 4252 472 4252 Barley - - - - - - - - -</formula><p>-To prevent lodging prop up the crop by end of August using trash twist method.</p><p>-Rice Do not apply more than recommended nitrogen. Avoid early planting of rice to keep the incidence of BLB under check.</p><p>---</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Horticulture</head><p>The excess rain water when stagnates for several days is harmful to the orchard trees.</p><p>---Adopt prompt measures to drain out excess water.</p><p>Outbreak of pests and diseases due to unseasonal rains Rice -Blight develops more in high humid conditions. Farmers should not allow stagnation of water in the fields.</p><p>If high humidity and cloudy weather prevails the crop may be sprayed with blitox/ copper oxychloride 50 WP @ 500 g in 200 litres of water/acre to control false smut and after 10 days of its application spray Tilt @ 200 ml/acre in 200 litres of water.</p><p>Start the spray at the boot stage.</p><p>-Potato -Late blight of potato develops in November-December months 1. Spray the crop with Ridomil @1250 ml/ha. 2. Cut the haulms Potato cultivars Kufri Chandermukhi, Kufri Jyoti and Kufri Chipsona-1 can be stored successfully for 5 months at 10±1 o C and 90-95 % RH with two consecutive foggings of CIPC at the rate of 40 ml per tonne. The first fogging is given at the first fogging. The stored potatoes maintain low reducing sugars (&lt; 0.25 %) and are suitable for chipping and culinary purpose.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Horticulture</head><p>In case of occurrence of root damage due to water stagnation in pear, peach etc. apply 10 g Bavistin 50 WP + 5 g Vitavax 75 WP in 10 litres of water along the trunk after draining out the excess water and drying of soil. Prune the dried ends of the branches alongwith 5-8 cm of the live wood.</p><p>---</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.3">Floods</head><p>In The alternate crops can be grown when flooded areas will reach the wattar condition, the mash varieties mash 114, Mash 338 and Mash 1-1 can be sown using 15-20 kg seed rate/ha. This gives us 7.5-8.8 q/ha yield of mash. Fields reaching wattar condition in first week of September can be sown with toria varieties PBT 37 and TL 15 using 3.75 kg/ha seed and maintaining a line to line distance of 30 cm.</p><p>Kill the hibernating larvae of maize borer in plant material like stubbles, stalks, cobs and cores.</p><p>Use trichoderma cards on 10-15 days old maize crop Spray Fenvalerate @40ml Cypermethrin @40 ml Spray Monochrotophos @100 ml in 100 L of water against the mite • In addition to combat the demand of green fodder, green cobs from maize crops can provide good profit to farmers. This crop can be followed with late wheat or sunflower.</p><p>---</p><p>• The farmers can also grow toria+gobhi sarson in the middle of September.</p><p>---</p><p>• Farmers may grow vegetable: August is suitable for growing radish, cucurbits like bottlegourd, bittergourd and lufa, etc. Lobia (Cowpeas) can also be grown for vegetables.</p><p>--- </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drought</head><p>Feed and fodder availability Increase area under fodder cultivation.</p><p>Collection and storage of wheat /paddy straw.</p><p>Processing &amp; storage of feed/fodder and roughages in the form of complete feed/blocks.</p><p>Establishing fodder banks and preserving fodder as silage and hay.</p><p>Utilizing fodder from fodder bank reserves.</p><p>Utilizing stored silage/hay.</p><p>Transporting complete feed/fodder and dry roughages to the affected areas.</p><p>Training/educating farmers for feed &amp; fodder storage.</p><p>Maintenance / repair of silo pits and feed/fodder stores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drinking water</head><p>Preserving water in the village ponds/ tanks.</p><p>Excavation of bore wells.</p><p>Rain water harvesting on individual farm/community basis.</p><p>Using water from village ponds/tanks.</p><p>Ground water resources to be exploited for drinking purposes.</p><p>Maintenance/ cleaning and strengthening of water reservoirs/village ponds.</p><p>Health and disease management Preparedness with sufficient stocks of medicines.</p><p>Vaccination of animals.</p><p>Insurance of animals.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Conducting mass animal health camps and treating the affected animals</head><p>Culling sick animals.</p><p>Insurance claim for mortalities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Floods</head><p>Feed and fodder availability Collection and storage of wheat /paddy straw.</p><p>Establishing feed/ fodder reserves at places safe from floods.</p><p>Processing/ storage of feed/ roughages in the form of complete feed/blocks.</p><p>Using excess fodder for silage/hay making.</p><p>Moving feed and fodder from the reserves to flood affected areas.</p><p>Maintenance and strengthening of feed / fodder storage facilities Ensure availability of quality feed and fodder for high yielding animals</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drinking water</head><p>Excavation of bore wells. Supply of clean and safe water to the animals.</p><p>Cleaning and disinfection of water reservoir/village ponds/tanks.</p><p>Repair/maintenance of bore wells.</p><p>Health and disease management Provision of community shelters at safe places.</p><p>Proper &amp; timely vaccinations.</p><p>Preparedness with sufficient stock of medicines.</p><p>Constitution of Rapid Action Veterinary Force.</p><p>Shifting animals from affected areas to safe places at short notice. Utilizing feed from feed reserve banks.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quick action by</head><p>Strengthening of feed storage facilities.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drinking water</head><p>Strengthening of water supply sources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ensure sufficient drinking water supplies -</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Health and disease management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Vaccination of birds.</head><p>Veterinary preparedness with sufficient stocks of medicines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Critical observation of flocks for any infection on daily basis.</head><p>Culling /disposal of affected birds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Floods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shortage of feed ingredients</head><p>Ensure feed reserves to meet requirements for 2-3 months at places safe from floods.</p><p>Use feed from feed reserves.</p><p>Transport feed to affected areas.</p><p>Cleaning &amp; disinfection of feed stores Dispose of fungal contaminated feeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Drinking water</head><p>Excavation of deep bore wells.</p><p>Use water from deep bore well. Maintenance of water supply sources.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Health and disease management</head><p>Emergency veterinary preparedness with sufficient stocks of medicines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Deworming of birds.</head><p>Visit of rapid action force to the affected areas for emergency treatment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Culling affected birds.</head><p>Proper disposal of dead carcasses.</p><p>Cleaning and disinfection of poultry houses.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cyclone</head><p>Not a cyclone prone district.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shortage of feed ingredients</head><p>Drinking water</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Health and disease management</head><p>Heat wave and cold wave</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Shelter/environment management</head><p>Build comfortable shelters.</p><p>Make provision for cooling devices.</p><p>Tree plantation/wind breakers around poultry facilities.</p><p>Ensure supply of fresh drinking water.</p><p>Use cooling / heating devices for comfort of birds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Increase or decrease ventilation and air movements as per requirements</head><p>Use feed additives as protective measure to reduce the effects of cold or heat.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Health and disease management</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Vaccination of birds.</head><p>Emergency veterinary preparedness with sufficient stock of medicines.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Watch the flocks for any infection critically.</head><p>Testing the titer against RD.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Quick treatment of birds against any disease outbreak</head><p>Culling and disposal of affected birds.</p><p>Proper disposal of mortalities. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.5.3.">Fisheries/ Aquaculture</head></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Unusual rains (untimely, unseasonal etc) (for both rainfed and irrigated situations)</figDesc><table><row><cell>Grapes Pests and disease outbreak (Yellow rust on wheat, BLB on 56 Condition 2.1.2 Drought -Irrigated situation Condition Condition of 1% MnSO 4 in case of Mn</cell><cell>0.055 Suggested Contingency measures -Suggested Contingency measures Suggested Contingency measures and holes in the godowns thoroughly. -</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">paddy, Late blight on potato, Sucking pests like aphids, Early season Major Farming Normal Crop/cropping Major Farming Normal Change in crop/cropping system Agronomic measures Crop management Soil nutrient &amp; Major Farming Normal Change in crop/cropping Agronomic measures deficiency Disinfest old gunny bags by dipping Remarks on Remarks on Remarks on Implementation</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Rapeseed and Mustard Sunflower Potato Major Horticultural crops (Crops to be identified based on total acreage) --1 ------Crop Production Metric tonnes Kinnow 1591 Ber 269 Amla 26 Misc 279 1.12 Sowing window for 5 major field crops Paddy Kharif-Rainfed Kharif-Irrigated 2 nd week of June to 1 st week July Rabi-Rainfed -jassid, whitefly, Mealy bug in cotton) Others Yellow vein mosaic virus in Mungbean 1.14 Include Digital maps of the district for Location map of district within State as Annexure I 1187 --Wheat ----Mean annual rainfall as Annexure 2 Soil map as Annexure 3 drought (Normal onset) situation system Normal onset followed by 15-20 days dry spell after sowing leading to poor germination/crop stand etc. Condition Suggested Contingency measures -4.9 1535 -296 22450 Production (000 t) -0.085 0.241 -Sunflower ---Enclosed: Yes / No Enclosed: Yes / No Enclosed: Yes / No moisture conservation 1 4.9 296 Productivity (kg/ha) 1187 1535 22450 -Maize Potato ----4 th week May to 4 th week June --measures Implementation NA Mid season drought (long dry spell, consecutive 2 Major Farming situation Normal Crop/cropping system Crop management Soil nutrient &amp; moisture conservation measures Remarks on Implementation Condition situation Crop/cropping Implementation situation Crop/cropping system system them in emulsion of 6 ml Sumicidin -Suggested Contingency measures Major Farming situation Normal Crop/cropping system Change in crop/cropping system Agronomic measures system 20EC or 5 ml Cymbush 25 EC in 10 Remarks on Sunflower Summer Moong (SML 832 and Insufficient Tubewell irrigated Paddy Alternate crops to be sown Laser land leveling Laser leveling of field saves 20-litres of water for 10 minutes and dry Implementation Delayed release of water in canals due to low rainfall Tube well irrigated alluvial soils Paddy Prefer Short duration varieties (PR-115) and Basmati rice (Pusa Basmati-1, Pusa 1121, Punjab Basmati-2, Punjab Mehak) Direct seeding of paddy and laser land leveling should be done Direct seeding of rice saves about 20% of irrigation water. Laser leveling of field also saves 20-25 % of irrigation water Maize Moong (PAU 911 and ML 818), Mash (Mash 114 and Mash 338). Wheat Gram (PDG $ and PDG 3) and Toria (PBT 37). SML 668) and Summer Mash (Mash 1008 and Mash 414) Condition Suggested Contingency measures Major Farming situation Normal Crop/cropping system Change in crop/cropping system Agronomic measures Remarks on Implementation Non release of water in canals under delayed onset of monsoon Tubewell irrigated alluvial soils Paddy Maize, Soybean (SL 744 and SL 525) and moongbean Bed planting of soybean and maize laser land leveling should be done groundwater recharge due to low rainfall alluvial soils like pulses (Moong PAU 911 and ML 818), Mash (Mash 114 and Mash 338), Oilseeds in place of predominant crops of rice-wheat. should be done. 1% FeSO 4 spray in case of iron deficiency at weekly interval and decrease irrigation interval 25 % of irrigation water. Sowing of wheat with happy them in shade before filling with Maize grains or use new gunny bags. Wheat seeder immediately after harvest of paddy saves pre sowing Sugarcane -Earthing up of the --Sugarcane sugarcane crop may be irrigation done if not done earlier Paired row trench planting of sugarcane saves about 10-15% during the first week of Wheat can be sown with July. irrigation water Happy seeder Drain out excess water in Bed planting saves technology immediately case of water stagnation 20-25 % irrigation after harvesting of conditions. water. Laser leveling of field also saves 20-Maize paddy. Horticulture crops -Drain out excess water --Moong (PAU 911 and ML -Rabi-Irrigated -4 th week October to 1st week December --Last week of September to mid October. Spring-Irrigated --2 nd week to 4 th week --weeks rainless (&gt;2.5 mm) period) At vegetative stage NA Sugarcane Moong (PAU 911 and ML 818), Mash (Mash 114 and Mash 338 in catchment 25 % of irrigation 818), Mash (Mash 114 and Paired row Heavy rainfall with high speed winds in a short span trench water Mash 338). Wheat --Don't irrigate on windy or stormy -planting of sugarcane days as it will lead to lodging of 2.0 Strategies for weather related contingencies Wheat Oilseeds wheat crop. -Orange and Malta 74 1.811 18110 Lemon 82 0.075 7530 Mangoes 834 0.090 7520 Litchi 49 0.801 13584 Guava 3633 0.006 1232 Pear 753 3.949 21940 Peach 240 0.820 22790 Plum 51 0.214 17860 of January. 1.13 What is the major contingency the district is prone to? (Tick mark) Regular Occasional None Drought --Flood --Cyclone --Hail storm --Heat wave --Cold wave --Frost --Sea water intrusion --2.1 Drought 2.1.1 Rainfed situation (100 per cent area is irrigated): Not Applicable Condition Suggested Contingency measures Early season drought (delayed onset) Major Farming situation Normal Crop/cropping system Change in crop/cropping system Agronomic measures Remarks on Implementation Delay by 2 weeks NA Delay by 4 weeks Delay by 6 weeks NA Delay by 8 weeks NA (Early withdrawal of monsoon) situation system moisture conservation measures Implementation NA Maize Wheat Wheat can be replaced with oilseeds Sugarcane Mash ( Mash 114 and Mash 338 Wheat Mn deficiency can be -Store new grains in clean godowns or -monsoon Moong (PAU 911 and ML 818), Lack of inflows into tanks due to /delayed onset of water insufficient alluvial soils so drain out the excess NA sensitive to standing water Tube well irrigated Maize -This crop is highly --NA Condition Suggested Contingency measures Mid season drought (long dry spell) Major Farming situation Normal Crop/cropping system Crop management Soil nutrient &amp; moisture conservation measures Condition Sugarcane Sugar cane should be replaced Sugarcane If dry weather conditions Suggested Contingency measures with Moong ( P A U 911 and prevails might may also cause Remarks on Implementation At flowering/ fruiting stage NA Condition Suggested Contingency measures Terminal drought Major Farming Normal Crop/cropping Crop management Soil nutrient &amp; Remarks on Major Farming situation Normal Crop/cropping system Change in crop/cropping system Agronomic measures Remarks on severe damage to this crop. ML 818), Mash ( Mash 114 Implementation Limited release of water in canals due to low rainfall Tubewell irrigated alluvial soils Paddy Prefer sowing of Basmati rice, Maize, Soybean and other pulses. Direct seeding of paddy laser land leveling should be done. Sunflower can be grown by transplanting of nursery in February. Direct seeding of rice saves and Mash 338 For its control spray the crop with 400 ml of malathion 50 2.2 Condition EC in 100 litres of water/ Suggested contingency measure about 20% of irrigation water. Laser leveling of field also saves 20-25 % of irrigation water. Condition Suggested Contingency measures Major Farming situation Normal Crop/cropping system Change in crop/cropping system Agronomic measures Remarks on logging Implementation Continuous high Vegetative stage Flowering stage Crop maturity stage acre. Remove Baru weed Post harvest growing around the sugarcane rainfall in a short span leading to water field.</cell></row><row><cell>corrected by repeated sprays</cell><cell>receptacles. Plug all cracks, cervices</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>general there are no floods, floods came in 1988 and 1995 in the low lying area of Kapurthala</figDesc><table><row><cell>Condition</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Suggested contingency measure</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Transient water logging/</cell><cell>Seedling / nursery stage</cell><cell>Vegetative stage</cell><cell>Reproductive stage</cell><cell>At harvest</cell></row><row><cell>partial inundation</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Maize</cell><cell>•</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
