<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Agriculture &amp; Allied Sector Profi le of North East Region</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<title level="a" type="main">Agriculture &amp; Allied Sector Profi le of North East Region</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">FCDEA726DD89C4CBC9BA4E1F3A7521EB</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>North East Overview</head><p>The North-eastern Region (NER), which includes the eight States of Arunachal Pradesh, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, Mizoram, Nagaland, Sikkim, and Tripura, is the easternmost region of India. Since each state has a border with at least one of the five nations to the east of the country, this area serves as a gateway to Southeast Asia and is of great strategic importance.</p><p>Furthermore, the NER is widely recognized as one of the most diverse regions in Asia, characterized by a rich tapestry of ethnicities and languages. Each state within NER boasts a unique blend of distinct cultures and traditions.</p><p>The Northeast region of India is a well-known biodiversity hotspot that is also home to a rich mix of cultures. In addition, the region is blessed with abundant natural resources that are yet to be fully explored and exploited. The region also holds a significant stake in the country's 'Act East Policy,' which is aimed at promoting economic, political, and cultural ties with Southeast Asia. With a wealth of natural resources, human resources, and potential for agriculture and horticulture, the region is rapidly emerging as a hub for sustainable manufacturing and service industries. Additionally, the region's rich ethnic, religious, linguistic, and cultural diversity makes it a highly attractive destination for tourists, offering significant potential for growth and development in the tourism sector.</p><p>With an area of 2.6 lakh sq. km, the NER accounts for about 7.98 per cent of the total geographical area of India while being home to 3.78 per cent of India's total population. The region is characterised by a mixed topography of hills and plains, with hills occupying 70 per cent of the land area. With a significant tribal population accounting for around 54 percent of its total population, especially in the hilly areas, the Northeast region of India is unique in its diversity. The region is home to approximately 135 Scheduled Tribe groups out of a total of approximately 705 across India.</p><p>With plentiful natural resources, agro-horticultural and forest resources, hydroelectric potential, oil and natural gas and mineral deposits, the northeast region is well poised for investment and economic growth.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Demographic Indicators</head><p>Snapshot of NER </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key Economic Indicators</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Advantage North East</head><p>Gateway to Southeast Asia: A strategic location that offers easy access to ASEAN markets.</p><p>Abundant Natural Resources: An abundance of oil, gas, coal, minerals, timber, medicinal plants, bamboo, forest products, and an abundance of water for industries to exploit.</p><p>India's Green Hub: Home to lush forests and rich biodiversity, it is an ideal destination for ecotourism and agrobased industries.</p><p>Diverse Cultural Heritage: A region with unique ethnic communities and traditions that offer investment opportunities in tourism and handicrafts.</p><p>Government Incentives: A range of incentives, including tax holidays, subsidies, and reimbursements to support business growth.</p><p>Low-cost Manufacturing Hub: Low labour costs compared to other parts of India and the world.</p><p>Skilled Workforce: A young, educated, and skilled workforce that is proficient in English.</p><p>Growing Infrastructure: Rapidly developing infrastructure, including new industrial parks, and technology parks.   Jute:</p><p>North East India occupies 7.7% of India's total geographical area supporting 8,000 species of Flora which 2526 species are endemic. The flora and fauna of North East India are unique and diverse, owing to its geographical location, diverse topography, and varied climatic conditions.</p><p>The region is particularly known for its lush forests, which are home to several endemic and endangered plant species. Some of the common flora found in this region include bamboo, orchids, rhododendrons, ferns, and several types of medicinal plants. The region is also home to several rare and endangered plant species, including the Indian gooseberry, the Indian yew, and the red panda plant.</p><p>The agriculture sector of North East India is a vibrant and growing industry that is a significant contributor to the region's economy. Farmers in North East India have demonstrated remarkable resilience and innovation in their farming practices. Abundance of fertile land in the region has allowed farmers to grow a wide range of crops, including rice, tea, spices, fruits, Rubber, Jute and vegetables, making the region a significant source of agricultural produce.</p><p>Another positive aspect of the agriculture sector in North East India is the strong government support and investment in the sector. The government has implemented several schemes and programs to support farmers, including subsidies for farming equipment, irrigation facilities, and agricultural credit.</p><p>The growth of the agriculture sector in North East India has also led to the creation of new employment opportunities in rural areas, contributing to the region's overall economic development. Also, the need for agricultural inputs has gained a considerable momentum leading in many agricultural companies investing in the region.</p><p>The states of Tripura, Assam, Manipur, Meghalaya, and Nagaland are the major rubber-producing states in the region. Tripura is the largest producer of natural rubber in the North East region and accounts for over 50% of the region's total rubber production. Apart from being used for making tires and tubes, rubber has various other applications. Rubber-based industries like footwear, automobile parts, industrial products, consumer goods, and medical equipment are some of the industries that extensively use rubber. Rubber-based products are also used in construction, mining, and aerospace industries.</p><p>Jute is an important cash crop in North East India, particularly in the states of Assam, Nagaland, Meghalaya, and Tripura. The region accounts for a significant portion of India's jute production. One of the most common uses is in the production of traditional handicrafts, such as bags, baskets, and mats. Jute is also used in the production of various industrial products, including sacks, carpets, and textiles. The fibres of the jute plant are strong, durable, and biodegradable, making them a popular choice for eco-friendly products.  The region is known for producing high-quality tea, which is widely recognized and appreciated by tea lovers around the world. The tea sector in the North East region has been growing steadily over the years, with increasing demand for high-quality tea from consumers worldwide. The region has also seen an increase in the number of small and medium-sized tea growers, which has contributed to the growth of the sector. This has resulted in an increase in employment opportunities, particularly for rural communities, and has helped to improve their economic condition.</p><p>Spice production in the north-eastern states of India has been gaining significant momentum in recent years, and this is undoubtedly a positive development for both the region and the country. The cultivation of spices such as ginger, turmeric, black pepper and cardamom in the North Eastern region has been increasing in recent years. This has not only provided a boost to the local economy but has also helped in increasing the export earnings of the country. The unique climatic and soil conditions in this region have also made it possible for farmers to produce high-quality spices that are in great demand both in the domestic and international markets</p><p>With its abundant water resources, the North-eastern region provides an ideal environment for fisheries to thrive. The region is home to a diverse range of fish species, including the popular Pangasius, Catla, Rohu, and Tilapia. These species are in high demand both locally and internationally, making the region a significant player in the global fishery market. The overall fish production in the North-eastern states is 5.18 lakh tons and the total fish seed production is 98899.05 lakhs Fry. Assam ranks 5th in terms of all India per capita fish consumption with 11.72 kg consumption per person per year. The government also recognized the potential of the fishery sector in the region and has implemented various policies and initiatives to support and develop the industry. The establishment of fish hatcheries and training centres has helped to improve the quality of fish produced, which has, in turn, boosted the region's economy.  Moreover, the Government of India has taken several initiatives to promote the tea industry in the North East region, including providing financial assistance to tea growers, setting up of tea parks, and facilitating exports. These initiatives have helped to create a favourable business environment, attracting investment, and boosting the growth of the sector. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Major raw materials available for Processing Industry</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Connectivity in NER</head><p>Accessibility : The Indian government has undertaken several initiatives to upgrade the existing road infrastructure and build new highways, bridges, and tunnels to enhance connectivity within the region and with the rest of the country</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Road Connectivity :</head><p>The Indian government has undertaken several initiatives to upgrade the existing road infrastructure and build new highways, bridges, and tunnels to enhance connectivity within the region and with the rest of the country. One of the most significant projects is the ongoing construction of the 3,000-km long Trans Arunachal Highway, which will connect all the districts of Arunachal Pradesh, the easternmost state of India. Another noteworthy project is the Dhola-Sadiya bridge, which is the longest bridge in India and spans over the Brahmaputra River in the state of Assam. Moreover, the Indian government has also launched the Bharatmala Pariyojana, a flagship highway development program that aims to construct 35,000 km of highways across India. Under this project, several highways are being constructed in the North East region, which will further improve connectivity and promote regional development.</p><p>Air Connectivity : New airports have been constructed and existing ones have been modernized and upgraded with state-of-the-art facilities, making air travel a more comfortable and convenient option for the people of the region. The government has also introduced various incentives to attract airlines to operate in the North East, such as reduced landing and parking fees, which has led to an increase in the number of flights to the region. With better air connectivity, the North East is now more accessible to tourists and businesses from other parts of India and the world. This has not only helped to boost the local economy but has also contributed to the growth and development of the region.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rail Connectivity :</head><p>The Indian Railways has taken steps to preserve the cultural and natural heritage of the region by introducing special trains that showcase the unique beauty and diversity of the North East. This has not only helped to promote tourism in the region but has also generated awareness about the rich cultural and natural heritage of the North East. The introduction of new trains and the extension of existing ones has also contributed to increased connectivity in the region. With better rail connectivity, the North East is now more accessible to tourists and businesses from other parts of India and the world. This has not only helped to boost the local economy but has also contributed to the growth and development of the region. • As a measure to provide a conducive business eco system, the states of North East India have implemented one stop single window system for all G2B permits and permissions required for any business activity • Among many other features of the single window systems, a notable functionality in the system is Centralised Inspection Module which helps in random allocation of inspection inspectors and joint site inspection thereby reducing the time, procedure and cost of many G2B services</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Connected North East</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Highlights of EoDB in the States of NER</head><p>• The North Eastern states have onboarded or are in the process of onboarding their G2B services in the National Single Window Portal. This will enable investors to easily apply for business clearances for their investments in the region.</p><p>• To attract investment in the NER, the states have proactively implemented Industrial Policies which offer state specific incentives</p><p>• Each state in the North East has developed industrial land banks for ease of land allocation • Sector specific Industrial Zones like Plastic Park, Textile Parks and IT Parks have been developed in the region</p><p>• NE States have undertaken an exercise to reduce compliance burden through a process of rationalisation and decriminalizing minor offences.</p><p>• The states have put in place robust feedback and grievance redressal mechanisms to further improve ease of doing business. </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Percentage share of GVA of agriculture and allied sector to total economy is 20.2% in 2021 India is among the top 10 countries in the world in terms of land area under organic agriculture India permits 100 per cent FDI in the food processing sector through the automatic route By 2025, consumption of processed food is expected to be around 25% of the total national Agri produce and employ 9 million people in the food processing sector by 2024 India ranks 1st in production of Milk, Bananas, Mango, Guava, Papaya, Ginger and Okra in the world and ranks 2nd in production of green peas, Potato, Tea, Tomato, Sesame Seed</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The states of Assam, Meghalaya, Nagaland, Arunachal Pradesh, Manipur, Tripura, and Mizoram in North East India have a rich tradition of flower cultivation, and the industry is rapidly growing in these states. Some of the popular flowers grown in the region include orchids, roses, gladioli, marigolds, and lilies. The floriculture industry in North East India has many advantages, including a vast consumer market within the region, proximity to neighbouring countries such as Bangladesh, Myanmar, and Bhutan, and the availability of cheap labour. The industry also provides employment opportunities for many people, especially women. Some ways to boost the floriculture industry areThe north eastern states of India alone accounts for more than 40% of India's endemic plant species. Important medicinal plants such as Aconitum feorx (Indian Aconite), Aconitum heterophyllum (Indian Atees), Swertia chiryata (Chirayita), Coptis teeta (Mishmi teeta/Gold thread), Podophyllum hexandrum (May Apple), Illicium griffithii (Star Anise), Berginia ciliate (Winter Begonia), Paris polyphylla (Himalayan Paris), Homalomena aromatica (Scented Arum), Garcinia spp. (Sap tree), Oroxylum indicum (Broken bones), Smilax glabra (Sarsa Parilla) etc. are all available in the forests of North East India. At present, the raw material produce (unprocessed medicinal plant parts) from the region is traded mainly in the markets of Delhi, West Bengal, and Bihar. The medicinal plant sector has great potential to boost the economy of North East India.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Assam and Nagaland produces 24517 tonns of chilli in 2020-21. Also accounts for growing the world's hottest natural chilli"BHUT JOLOKIA" Large cardamom The states of Sikkim, Arunachal Pradesh, Nagaland and Manipur produced 7672 tonns of large Cardamom in 2020-21 Ginger The states of Sikkim, Arunachal Pradesh, Mizoram, Meghalaya and Assam produces 407415 tonns of Ginger in 2020-21 Turmeric The states of Mizoram, Meghalaya and Assam produces 70809 tonns of Turmeric in 2020-21. Lakadom turmeic found in Meghalaya contains 7.8 % of curcumin which is much higher than the curcumin content in other turmeric varieties.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,-1.11,0.00,722.26,721.18" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="5,718.80,-1.15,722.21,722.21" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="7,-1.16,0.00,722.25,720.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="10,718.94,0.00,722.15,721.10" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="11,-1.08,-0.00,722.16,720.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="13,-1.00,0.00,722.21,721.23" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="17,-1.06,0.00,722.09,721.17" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="18,718.97,0.00,722.15,721.16" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_1"><head>Reasons to Invest in Agriculture in North East India</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Stable Business Environment: A favourable business climate with a low crime rate, stable political environment,</cell></row><row><cell>and supportive government policies.</cell></row><row><cell>Emerging Consumer Market: A growing consumer market with rising incomes and increased urbanization that</cell></row><row><cell>offers immense potential for business.</cell></row><row><cell>4 agro-climatic zones and abundant perennial water</cell></row><row><cell>Global tea hub contributing to more than 50% of the country's total tea production</cell></row><row><cell>Total of 8869.1 thousand tons of food grains production in 2020-21</cell></row><row><cell>More than 78 species of Bamboo are naturally available in NER</cell></row><row><cell>Major fruits and spices produced in the state include Pineapple, Jackfruit, Oranges and varieties of Lemon &amp;</cell></row><row><cell>Lime, Ginger, and Turmeric</cell></row><row><cell>India's leading producer of Tea.</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>East India Scenario: Agriculture and allied Sector Highlights Flora and Fauna of NER Agriculture and allied sector Rubber:</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>North</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Commodities</cell><cell>Food</cell><cell>Vegetables</cell><cell>Fruits</cell><cell>Flowers</cell><cell>Spices</cell><cell>Rubber</cell><cell>Jute</cell><cell>Tea</cell><cell>Bamboo</cell><cell>Meat</cell><cell>Fish</cell><cell>Dairy</cell><cell>Egg</cell></row><row><cell>Quantity in 000</cell><cell>Grains</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>MT)</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Total</cell><cell>8869</cell><cell>6141.74</cell><cell>4507.77</cell><cell>103.55</cell><cell>779.77</cell><cell>94430</cell><cell>933.58</cell><cell>699.74</cell><cell>84991</cell><cell>253</cell><cell>5.18</cell><cell>1528</cell><cell>12145</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(000</cell><cell>million</cell><cell></cell><cell>(000</cell><cell>(Lakh</cell><cell></cell><cell>(Lakh</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Bales)</cell><cell>Kgs</cell><cell></cell><cell>Tons)</cell><cell>tonn)</cell><cell></cell><cell>eggs)</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Implementation of single window clearance portal in all the states of North East for providing G2B services in a seam- less timebound manner Integration with NSWS Industrial Policy for attracting investment in the region Preferential land allotment policy through creating of Industrial Land Banks Reducing Compliance Burden A robust feedback and grievance redressal mechanism</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Availability of organically grown raw products</head><p>Availability of skilled manpower for agriculture and food processing industry from state Agriculture universities in Assam, Meghalaya, Nagaland, and Tripura Availability of Food Processing Infrastructure: Dedicated Mega Food Park, Cold chain project, Testing Laboratory, land bank for industry</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Supporting Infrastructure Educational and Knowledge Infrastructure</head><p>There is immense potential for private players to invest in warehouses and other logistics infrastructure based on the diversity of Agricultural products and production throughout the north eastern region.</p><p>Additionally, Government of Arunachal Pradesh has proposed a Mega Food Park Scheme under PM SAMPADA Yojana There are several educational institutes which provide state of the art education to students across the North East Region. Some of the major institutes imparting education in the agriculture and allied subjects are as follows: </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
