<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main"></title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">3EB9B63819DF592031D2F872CD85F270</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract/>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.0">OBJECTIVES</head><p>After studying this unit, you will be able to:</p><p>• explain causes of pest incidence in crops;</p><p>• discuss pest epidemics and their causes;</p><p>• describe diagnostic symptoms of pests in crops;</p><p>• explain principles and approaches of integrated pest management; and</p><p>• discuss pest residues and their consequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>By studying principles and practices of crop production, you must have got an idea about how we can enhance our crop productivity and production.</p><p>However, crop yield potential is threatened by biotic constraints such as insect pests and diseases. Until and unless these bottlenecks are not tackled effectively, it is very difficult to harvest a high crop yield. In this unit, you will learn about causes that increase pest intensity on crops. You will also be acquainted with the concept of pest diagnostics and principles and practices of integrated pest management. Finally, the harmful effects of pesticide residues and safety measures against residues will be discussed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.2">CAUSES OF INSECT PESTS AND DISEASES IN CROPS</head><p>Since man started agriculture by clearing forests, he has been disturbing the balance of nature by reducing environmental resistance through ecologically unsound methods of cultivation. Even any slight decrease in any of the processes of 'environment resistance' results in a population explosion of an insect species and the consequent epidemics. Nature too sometimes plays role in causing pest epidemics. Favorable conditions, which reduce the natural mortality and bring down the rapid development of the insect coupled with the conditions unfavorable to the natural enemies of that insect, often result in the rapid increase of its population leading to a sudden pest outbreak. Man's interference in ecosystems thus causes intensification of insects and diseases on crops and the main causes of this are discussed below.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i)</head><p>Monoculture: Due to ease in agronomic operations and other economic considerations, farmers resort to monoculture. Continuous cultivation of a crop species on extensive tracts provides unhindered availability of food for pests and as result, these attain higher populations than they would in a mixed crop environment.</p><p>ii) Staggered planting: Certain pests attack crops during a particular crop growth stage e.g. rice gundhi bug damages crop during the milky stage. Staggered planting of rice in an area ensures food availability to the pest for a prolonged duration thereby increasing the extent of crop losses.</p><p>iii) Multiple cropping: Growing the same crop on a piece of land continuously for more than one season during a year ensures uninterrupted food supply to pest species, thus accentuating pest problems e.g. multiple cropping of rice practiced in south India.</p><p>Likewise, retooning of sugarcane and brinjal also aggravates pest problems. Growing two crops in continuity that share the same pest fauna also increases pest losses e.g. in the rice-wheat cropping system, losses due to pink borer and nematode have increased.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>iv) Improved cultivars:</head><p>The majority of improved crop cultivars are bred for better yield and quality without addressing the pest resistance issue. These respond very well to fertilizers and irrigation showing excellent vegetative growth. These are preferred by pests and diseases that reproduce profusely on them inflicting heavy crop losses. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b)</head><p>Check your answer with those given at the end of the unit. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.3">PEST EPIDEMICS</head><p>Insects and pathogens are integral components of forest ecosystems and normally are present at a relatively low density, causing little damage and having a negligible impact on crop growth and vigor. Pest populations are frequently regulated below their potential levels of abundance by natural enemies, host resistance, or other biological interactions. However, sporadically, in time or space, some species may attain rapidly very high populations, which may persist for a variable length of time before subsiding. Such large populations are called epidemics and may have adverse effects on the growth, yield, and quality of crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Factors responsible for pest epidemics i)</head><p>Human manipulation of the environment: Large-scale cultivation of resistant crop cultivars against some pest species may result in a large population of some other pest species due to reduced competition. Introduction of Bt cotton resistant to bollworms experienced very high populations of cotton mealybug, Phenacoccus solenopsis. Lack of competition from bollworms and high fertilizers especially nitrogenous fertilizers stimulated population build-up of sucking pests. The unnatural conditions in the man-made environment induce unusually high and destructive pest populations.</p><p>ii) Foreign pests: Despite quarantine regulations, many foreign insects species get accidentally introduced into new habitats. With their lower environmental resistance due to the absence of their natural enemies in new habitats, their populations may attain unusually high magnitude. Some of the foreign pests, which caused havoc in India during the last 1-2 decades include sugarcane woolly aphid, Ceratovacuna lanigera; coconut eriophyid mite, Aceria guerreronis; coffee berry borer, Hypothenemus paspalivorus; sapota seed borer, Trymalitis margirias; spiraling whitefly, Aleurodicus disperses; serpentine leaf miner, Liriomyza trifolii. Introduced species became serious problems when they found an abundant food supply, a favorable climate, and few or no effective natural enemies.</p><p>iii) Introduction of the crop into the unsuitable environment: Many ornamental plants are chosen for their beauty and planted without proper consideration of their suitability for a particular site. Drought, nutrient, or temperature stress may affect such plants and make them more susceptible to pest attack. Proper watering and fertilizing of plants allow them to compensate for pest damage while stressed plants may be seriously injured by the same amount of pest damage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>iv) Weather:</head><p>Weather plays an important role in pest outbreaks by initiating the early activity of pests, promoting growth rates, and reducing mortality rates. Favorable weather in form of early onset of summer rains with suitable temperatures may initiate early breeding of pest population which may facilitate completion of extra generations during the season and as a result enormous population levels may be witnessed. Increased population levels may be 50-100 times higher than normal owing to the prolific fecundity of pest species. It has been observed that the early onset of rains in May further followed by regular monsoon rains led to a BPH outbreak on rice, leading to severe yield losses. The Pest situation may further be aggravated by heavy use of nitrogenous fertilizers, continuous flooding of rice fields, and indiscriminate use of broad-spectrum pesticides.</p><p>v) Pesticides: Broad-spectrum pesticides kill pests and their natural enemies as well. Pesticides prove effective until pests develop resistance against them. Once a resistance problem arises pesticide does not kill pests hence pest population explodes. This is known as pest resurgence. Pesticides targeted against major pests may also kill natural enemies of secondary pest but not secondary pest itself particularly when it belongs to different groups e.g. pesticide used against an insect pest may not kill a mite pest. In such a situation, secondary pest attains an enormous population due to the absence of major pests as well as due to the absence of their natural enemies.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Check</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4">PEST DIAGNOSTICS</head><p>Rapid and accurate diagnosis of pests and diseases is necessary before we can adopt proper control measures. It is the first step towards the study of any pest and its management. Diagnosis is largely done based on characteristic symptoms expressed by the affected plant. Identification of causal organisms is also essential to diagnosis. Diagnosis of plant diseases is more complex as their symptoms are more varied than those of insect pests. Insect pests are visible to naked eyes and symptoms can be broadly assigned to the type of pests in the field itself and then species can be further identified.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.1">Disease Diagnosis</head><p>Diagnosis of plant disease is a practical science and experience is the most important factor in the identification of a disease in the field. In preliminary disease identification, illustrated guides and charts are of paramount significance. Identification of those diseases is easier in which pathogen produces specific growth such as in downy mildew, powdery mildew, rusts, smuts, and many sclerotial diseases. However, in several other diseases, symptoms do not prove as helpful in identification as they overlap among many diseases e.g. chlorosis or yellowing of leaves can be caused by a nutritional disorder, fungus, virus, or bacteria.</p><p>In case of the identification of overlapping symptoms, the first step is to determine whether the pathogen is infectious or non-infectious. Field observations on the pattern of development of disease in plant population and spread of symptoms on other plants help in distinguishing the two. If the disease spreads among the plants then it is infectious. An infectious disease may be caused by bacteria, fungi, viruses, and nematodes. To determine their presence, an infected plant can be observed for the presence of bacterial ooze, fungal structures, or nematode cysts or females and then confirmed by laboratory studies. If fungus is not a biotroph, it can be cultured on artificial media and then tested for Koch's postulates. Bacteria can also be detected similarly. Apart from ooze often seen on the host surface in the case of bacteria, examination of cut pieces of the infected part in water under the microscope would reveal streaming of bacterial cell masses.</p><p>A. Koch's postulates comprise the following steps:</p><p>i)</p><p>The pathogen must be invariably found in infected plants or must be associated with it in some form.</p><p>ii) The pathogen should be separated from the host and grown in artificial culture.</p><p>iii) The pathogen from the artificial culture should be able to reproduce the disease when inoculated on a healthy plant of the same kind from which it was isolated. Symptoms produced should be identical with those seen on the plant from which the isolation was made.</p><p>iv) The artificially produced disease should yield the same pathogen on re-isolation.</p><p>Nematodes, if present, can be seen on the host or macerated tissues examined under the microscope. Nematodes can not be grown on artificial media. However, by separating the eggs and larvae from the host and multiplying them on a susceptible host under sterile conditions, sufficient larvae can be obtained for proving Koch's postulates.</p><p>Viruses can not be seen or grown in culture. They generally produce symptoms similar to those of nutritional deficiencies. However, the latter condition is non-infectious and does not spread from plant to plant while viruses are infectious and spread among plants.</p><p>If in artificial culture no pathogen is obtained and in tissue examination, including the vessels, no fungal structures of a biotroph or structures of nematodes are seen but the disease is infectious, it can be expected that the disease is caused by a virus or mycoplasma like organism (MLO). The differentiation between viruses and MLO can be made by electron microscopy and by spraying streptocycline antibiotics, which mask the symptoms of MLO diseases but not that of virus diseases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Plant disease symptoms i)</head><p>Rust: Rusts infecting thousands of economically important plants are caused by more than 4,000 species of fungi. These diseases produce rusty symptoms. The rusts appear as small pustules of spores that may be dusty or compact and red, brown, yellow, or black. Yellow, brown, and black rusts are important diseases of wheat (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1).</head><p>During their life cycle, rust fungi parasitize either one species of plant (autoecious or monoecious rust) or two distinct species (heteroecious rust). ii) Mildew: In these diseases, the pathogen is seen as white, grey, brownish, or purplish growth on the host surface (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.2). In powdery mildew, an enormous number of spores are formed on the superficial growth of fungus on the surface of leaves, buds, young shoots, fruits, and even flowers, producing a dusty or powdery appearance. This is caused by many specialized races of fungal species in the genera Erysiphe, Microsphaera, Phyllactinia, Podosphaera, Sphaerotheca, and Uncinula.</p><p>In downy mildew, superficial growth of the fungus is tangled cottony and downy growth, and grey, bluish, or violet downy patches of mildew form mostly on the undersides of leaves in damp weather. Palegreen to yellow or brown areas usually develops on the upper leaf surface opposite the downy growth. A disease of plants, especially in cool humid regions is caused by several fungi including species of Basidiophora, Phytophthora, Pseudoperonospora, and Sclerospora. iii) Smut: Smut disease infecting wheat, maize, rice, sorghum, onion, and grasses is caused by many species of fungi (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.3). The term 'smut' means a sooty or charcoal-like powder. It is characterized by spores that accumulate in soot-like masses called sori, in seeds, leaves, stems, flower parts, and bulbs. The sori usually break up into a black powder that is readily dispersed by the wind. In some smuts, a mass of spores may be compact and held under the epidermis appearing as black streaks on the host surface. They broke open the epidermis and expose white powdery masses of spores. Often, such symptoms have been called white rust but since there is nothing common between them and true rusts, they are more appropriately termed as white blisters.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>v)</head><p>Blotch: This symptom consists of a superficial growth giving the fruit a blotched appearance as in the sooty blotch of apple fruit.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>vi) Sclerotia:</head><p>A sclerotium is a compact, often hard, a mass of dormant fungus. In some diseases, as in ergot of cereals, the sclerotium assumes a characteristic horn-like shape but in others, the shape may be different. An ear of rye infected with ergot exudes yellowish mucus for some time followed by loss of starch as the ear ceases growth. The ovaries are then permeated by the mycelium, which in autumn forms the spur-like purple-black sclerotium.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>vii) Exudations:</head><p>In some fungal diseases, the invasion of the pathogen causes exudation of a gum-like material on the stem and collar. This is known as gummosis. In most bacterial diseases e.g. bacterial leaf blight and bacterial leaf streak of rice, fire blight of pear and apple, bacterial cankers of stone fruits, masses of bacterial cells come out as ooze on the infected host surface where they may be seen as drop or smear. On drying, they form a crust.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>viii) Colour changes:</head><p>Changes of colour from the normal or discolouration is one of the most common symptoms of plant diseases. Chlorosis is yellowing due to the influence of low temperature, lack of iron, excess of lime or alkali in the soil, and infection of viruses, fungi, and bacteria. On the other hand, etiolation is the disappearance of green pigment due to lack of light.</p><p>Mosaic is caused by various strains of viruses. Symptoms are variable but commonly include irregular leaf mottling (light and dark green or yellow patches or streaks). Leaves are commonly stunted, curled, or puckered while veins may be lighter than normal or banded with dark green or yellow. Plants are often dwarfed, with fruit and flowers fewer than usual, deformed, and stunted. Flowers may be blotched or streaked.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ix) Atrophy or hypotrophy or dwarfing:</head><p>In many diseases, there is inhibition of growth that results in stunting or dwarfing. The whole plant may be dwarfed or only certain organs may be affected. Stunting may be caused by viral, bacterial, fungal, or nematode infections and by non-infectious (abiotic) means including excess or lack of water, imbalance of soil nutrients, excess light, chemical or mechanical injuries, insect or mite feeding, and too deep planting.</p><p>x) Overgrowth and hypertrophy: Many pathogens induce hormonal imbalances in plants through their biochemical activity. This results in excessive growth of host tissues and causes an abnormal increase in the size of the affected organ. It is brought about by one or both of the processes known as hyperplasia and hypertrophy. Hyperplasia is the abnormal increase in the size of plant organs due to an increase in the number of cells while hypertrophy refers to the increased size of the organ due to an increase in the size of cells. The overgrowth and its effect are seen in the form of galls, curl, pockets, hairy roots, witches broom, intumescence, etc. Bakane disease of rice caused by fungus results in lanky plants as a result of elongation of tillers and reduced tillering.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>xi) Spots:</head><p>The cells are killed in limited areas and dead tissues usually become brownish (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.4). The most common diseases in this group are the leaf spots e.g. brown leaf spot of paddy. Leaf spots are caused by species of bacteria or by many fungus species.  xvi) Rot: Rot is characterized by plant decomposition and putrefaction. These are named after the plant part infected e.g. root rot, stem rot, bulb rot, fruit rot, etc. They are caused by any species of soil-borne bacteria and fungi. Fungal rots are usually dry to spongy or powdery, while bacterial rots are commonly moist, soft to mushy, and foulsmelling.</p><p>xvii) Burn or scorch: This is a symptom of plant disease in which tissue is burnt because of unfavorable conditions or infection by bacteria or fungi. Commonly there is a dead area along or between the veins and margins of leaves.</p><p>xviii) Wilt: Wilt is characterized by drooping of leaves and stems due to water loss (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.6). Wilt diseases are caused by a variety of fungi, bacteria, and viruses and are easily confused with root and crown rots, stem cankers, insect injuries, etc. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.4.2">Insect Damage Diagnosis</head><p>Damage symptoms of insect pests depend upon the types of their mouthparts and plant part affected. Accordingly, there is damage in the form of tissue boring, defoliation, leaf folding, leaf-mining, sap-sucking, etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>A. Tissue boring</head><p>This includes stem boring, root feeding, and fruit boring.  ii) Root boring: Some insects like root borers, termites, white grubs, root weevils feed on plant roots thereby killing the plants. Affected plants can easily be pulled out. The difference between stem borer and root borer damage is that in the case of the former, the roots of the plant are not damaged, and the only above-ground portion of the stem is damaged.</p><p>iii) Fruit boring: Fruit borers' larvae damage fruits e.g. in tomato, ladyfinger, brinjal, pomegranate (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.8). Likewise, fruit fly maggots cause damage in mango, cucurbits, ber, which results in the rotting of the fruit. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>B. Defoliation</head><p>Defoliators such as grasshoppers, beetles, and caterpillars damage plant leave causing defoliation (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.9). The extent of defoliation varies from small holes to complete defoliation and sometimes only midribs are left. In the case of grasshoppers and armyworms, damage resembles as if grazed by cattle.  Insect larvae fold leaves and then feed on green tissue inside the fold. When the fold opens, the affected leaf looks white as in case rice leaf folder damage in rice (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.11). Leaf rolling is also observed in the case of cotton. Sucking pests like aphids, jassids, planthoppers, whiteflies, bugs, thrips, coccids, scales, mites suck sap from xylem and phloem bundles of plants with their piercing and sucking mouthparts. As a result of sucking from leaves, stems, flowers, fruits plants lose vigour and turn pale and dry up. In the case of brown planthopper of rice, hopper burn symptoms are observed which are initially small circular patches of dried plants but enlarge with an increase in damage magnitude (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.12). In case of leafhopper damage in ladyfinger, upward cupping of leaves occurs, and eventually, they may fall. Likewise, thrips damage results in flower drops in many crops.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5">INTEGRATED PEST MANAGEMENT (IPM)</head><p>The sole reliance on pesticides to control insect pests has created several problems such as the development of resistant pests, pest outbreaks, mortality of useful organisms, adverse effect on human health, and environmental degradation. Adverse effects of pesticides prompted scientists to explore safer and environment-friendly methods of pest control and consequently integrated pest management came into vogue.</p><p>Integrated Pest Management (IPM) refers to the use of available pest control methods in a unified manner to reduce pest population below economic levels and ensure favorable, ecological, and economic consequences. Pest management signifies an ecological approach to tackle pest problems because here the emphasis is on containing pests in such a way that other biotic components of the system such as natural enemies, human beings, and wildlife are not harmed and the environment is not degraded. Pest management works on the premise that all pest population levels are not injurious to crops and crops can tolerate some amount of pest injury. Moreover, some pest population is also required for the survival of natural enemies of the pests. This has given rise to the concept of economic injury level (EIL), which helps to avoid the unwarranted application of control measures. The EIL refers to the minimum pest population or damage that causes economic damage. On the other, economic damage signifies the damage level at which expenditure on pest control is equal to the value of crop saved from pest damage. The EIL-based pest control measures ensure a favorable cost-benefit ratio to farmers. Pest management also underlines that pest control tactics should be socially acceptable and within the reach of farmers. It is a holistic approach to pest problems in which we aim to protect our commodities against all the pests and ensure the production of healthy crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.1">Principles of IPM a. Understanding of pests:</head><p>The biology of pests should be thoroughly studied to detect weak points in the life cycle for the maximum benefit from control measures. We should know whether it is univoltine i.e. having a single generation in a year or multivoltine. In the case of univoltine species, the action during the weak link of the life cycle can reduce their populations significantly, for example in the case of rice grasshopper and mango mealybug, the eggs are laid on the bunds of paddy fields and under the mango tree in the soil, respectively. The destruction of egg pods by raking field bunds and mango tree basins greatly reduces the pest populations. In the case of fruit borers and stem borers, the destruction of newly hatched larvae is the most appropriate method to control them; otherwise, once these enter the tissue it becomes very difficult to control them. Likewise, population reduction can also be done by attracting and killing the moths. Proper identification of the pest is necessary, for knowing its natural enemies so that these can be conserved and if necessary can be produced from other places for mass multiplication and released against pest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b.</head><p>Understanding the agro-ecosystem: Ecosystems are self-sufficient habitats where living organisms and nonliving environments interact to exchange energy and matter in a continuing cycle. Ecosystems are entities, such as forests, ponds, and fields, and in general, they are self-regulating. Agro-ecosystems contain a lesser diversity of animal and plant species than do natural ecosystems such as forests and prairies. Usually, there are few major species and numerous minor species and, in a pest outbreak, usually, only one pest species at a time is present in large numbers. A typical agricultural unit may contain only 1-4 major crop species and 6-10 minor pest species.</p><p>The agro-ecosystem is intensively manipulated by man through ploughing, mowing, and treatments with pesticides which harms the natural enemies. Natural enemy diversity is thus relatively low in agro-ecosystem. Therefore, agroecosystems are more susceptible to pest damage and catastrophic outbreaks. This happens due to a lack of diversity in plant and insect species and due to the sudden alternations imposed by weather and man. Often an insect can attack, establish and survive only during a short period but staggered planting may make food available for pests for a longer period and increase pest problems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>c.</head><p>Planning of agro-ecosystem: Planting crops should be done in such a way as to minimize or prevent pest problems. Agronomic practices can be modified suitably for this purpose. Deep ploughing in summer exposes soil pests such as cutworms, white grubs, mole crickets, armyworms, etc. to predators and extremes of weather, thereby reducing their population in the ensuing crop season.</p><p>Similarly, planting time can be preponed or postponed, for example, early planting of rapeseed-mustard in September in place of October reduces aphid infestation on these crops. Rice crop planted in August faces less incidence of Gundhi bug than crops planted in June or July. Sometimes change in planting dates may have a contrasting effect on different pests. In such a situation, the planting date should be chosen based on the relative importance of the pests.</p><p>If pest incidence appears in the nursery on crop seedlings then it should be controlled in the nursery itself as it is easier to control it on small scale with minimum contamination of the environment. Likewise, seedling dipping in pesticide solution at the time of transplanting or seed treatment before sowing also proves very effective in checking pest problems and reducing the environmental pollution. Rice seedlings dipping in chlorpyriphos before transplanting prove very effective against stem borer, gall midge, and plant hopper. Seed treatments in pulses, mustard, sorghum, cotton also prevent pest problems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>d.</head><p>Cost /benefit: It is the ratio between the cost of control measures and the value of the crop saved from pest attack due to the application of control measures. For a profitable situation, this ratio should be less than one. Lesser the ratio more is the profit to the farmer due to the control of pests. When its value is greater than one, then the farmer suffers indirect loss. In this situation, the cost of control measures is more than the value of crops protected from pest attack. Such a situation does not warrant the adoption of any control measures against the pest. To ensure that farmer does not face such loss incurring situation, the control measures should only be applied when the population reaches the economic threshold level. The economic level is worked out based on the cost of control measures, the market value of the crop, and the damage potential of the pest in the crop.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>e.</head><p>Benefit/risk: Benefit/risk analysis provides a means for assessing the relevant economic benefits versus the risk pest control poses to the environment. The risk may include harmful effects on beneficial organisms, wildlife, and humans; soil, water, and air degradation, and development of resistant pests, and the presence of pesticide residues in food. The consideration and assessment of benefit/risk are fundamental to pest management.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>f. Tolerance of pest damage:</head><p>To promote pest management and reduce our dependence on pesticides for pest control we must learn to live with insects. The pests cause economic loss only when they have reached some population level on the crop. Therefore, complete freedom from pests is not necessary for obtaining higher yields because crop plants are capable of compensating for some damage due to pests. However, this is not applicable for insect vectors of plant diseases, where complete eradication is desirable. In some cases, the removal of excess foliage due to pest damage even caused an increase in yield over the healthy crops. There should not thus be any reason for panic on witnessing a few insects in the field. Moreover, some pest population is always needed for the survival of natural enemies of pests, which play a very important role in pest suppression in the field. Therefore, minimum population or damage which can be tolerated without any adverse effect on crop yield and quality should be determined to avoid unwarranted application of control measures. The determination of economic threshold level (ETL) and economic injury level (EIL) is a step in this direction. These imply a tolerant approach to pest problems and need-based application of pesticides.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>g. Leaving a pest residue:</head><p>We have discussed that complete freedom from pests is not necessary for higher yield as plants can always compensate for some pest injury. Pest management philosophy thus advocates suppression of pest population to non-economic level and not the elimination of pests from the field. With this approach, fewer insecticidal treatments are required as compared to the elimination of pests. The presence of some pests in the field will ensure the survival of natural enemies of the pests, which would reduce dependence on pesticides and curtail environmental contamination.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>h. Timing treatments:</head><p>Pest management emphasizes the needbased application of pesticides. The calendar-based application or prophylactic treatments are generally discouraged. The need for the application of pesticides can be determined through regular monitoring to find out whether the population has reached the economic threshold level or not. The need-based application may reduce pesticide requirements by at least 50%. The pesticide application should coincide with exposure to the most vulnerable stage of the pest for best results. For example in the case of stem borers such as rice stem borer or maize stem borer and fruit borers, regular monitoring for eggs laying is very important. The application should coincide with egg hatching so that larvae come in contact with pesticides and die. Otherwise, once the larvae enter the stems or fruits, the application of pesticides will not be effective. In the case of fruit flies, an attempt should be made to control adults of these pests because only this stage is exposed whereas eggs and maggots are hidden in the fruits and pupae are in the soil.</p><p>Proper or precise placement of insecticides also helps in controlling pests more effectively and at the same time avoids contamination of the environment. For example, the rice planthoppers are mainly confined to the stems of rice plants. The pesticide application does not prove effective if the spray is directed at foliage, hence should be directed at stems.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i) Public understanding and acceptance:</head><p>Farmers are the users of IPM programmes therefore these should be developed through their active participation. The farmers' experiences with pest problems and the techniques used by them to combat pests should be given due consideration. The indigenous technical know-how (ITK) adopted by farmers has a sound scientific basis and hence the IPM programmes should be developed through a judicious blend of indigenous and modern technologies. Such programmes will be popular among farmers as will consider them as their programmes. Besides, these will also prove economical.</p><p>Extension workers should teach farmers that community cooperation is essential for the effective management of pests. The management of pests such as armyworms, locusts, and white grub beetles requires coordinated effort on the part of the entire community. Similarly, planting crop around the same time in an area also reduces the incidence of several pests. They should also have the will to share their plant protection equipment.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.5.2">Approaches of IPM</head><p>In IPM different methods of pest control such as resistant varieties, cultural methods, physical methods, natural enemies, and pesticides are integrated to suppress pest population without jeopardizing other components of the environment. Any pest management programme should be preferably based upon the use of resistant cultivars and natural enemies and other control methods should be blended with them for tackling pest menace. The utility of different pest management components has been described in the following discussion (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.13). The resistant cultivars enhance the efficiency of some natural enemies against the pests, for example, there is more predation of spiders against planthoppers on moderately resistant varieties than susceptible varieties. Likewise, on moderately resistant cultivars, the need for pesticide application is greatly reduced.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>IPM Mechanical Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>DB-Cultural Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Bio-control Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Physical Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Chemical Methods</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Nematode</head><p>Similarly, these are also compatible with cultural methods of pest control. However, the continuous use of resistant varieties has given rise to the problem of biotype development in some insects.  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b.</head><p>Cultural methods: Routine agronomic practices can be utilized for minimizing pest infestation by slight modification in timing or method of their application. These function as a preventive method.</p><p>The field operations right from field preparation to harvesting or postharvesting can reduce the population of one pest species or other.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>i)</head><p>Clean cultivation: Destruction of crop residues help to prevent carryover of pest to next season crop, for example, destruction of cucurbit vines and stubbles of rapeseed mustard after crop season kills population of pumpkin beetle and painted bug respectively. Similarly, disposal of stubbles in rice, maize, sorghum reduces carryover of stem borers.</p><p>ii) Tillage: Deep ploughing of fields exposes the soil-inhabiting stages of pests such as armyworms, cutworms, borers, white grubs, termites, mole cricket to vagaries of nature and thus helps to reduce pest infestation in crops (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.15). The raking of bunds of rice fields destroys egg pods of grasshopper. Similarly raking the soil at the base of the mango tree destroys the eggs of the mango mealybug. iii) Sowing time: The change in sowing/planting time is aimed at disturbing synchrony between host and pest populations. In rice, early planting (June-July) results in low populations of gall midge, leaf folder, and armyworm, while late planting (August) reduces the incidence of grasshopper, Gundhi bug, and BPH. Early sowing of cucurbits escapes the attack of the pumpkin beetle. However, a change in planting time should be adopted based on the relative importance of different pests in the area. As far as possible, crops should be planted around the same time in a locality as staggered planting increases pest incidence. If there is an incidence of pests in the nursery then it should be preferably tackled in the nursery itself as it is easier to contain a pest problem at a small scale.</p><p>iv) Intercropping: Intercropping helps in reducing the incidence of certain pests by making microclimate less favorable for them. It also hinders the free movement of pests among the plants of the same species. Intercropping of cabbage with tomato reduces infestation of the diamondback moth. Intercropping of chickpea with wheat decreases the incidence of pod borer while intercropping of mustard with wheat causes a decline in aphid population on rapeseed-mustard.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>v)</head><p>Crop-rotation: Crops sharing the same pests should not be grown in a rotation. It has been found that with rice-wheat rotation, the pests of rice and wheat are showing more incidences. Similarly, multiple cropping of rice results in outbreaks of pests.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>vi) Trap crops:</head><p>Trap crops protect by preventing the pests from reaching the main crop. The trap crop must be more attractive to the pests and less economical than the main crop. Mustard as a trap crop with cabbage reduces the incidence of diamondback moth, leaf webber, webworm, and aphids. Marigold planted with tomato as a trap crop is highly effective against fruit borer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>vii) Nutrient and water management:</head><p>Fertilizers should be applied in a balanced manner. Excess use of nitrogen intensifies the incidence of several pests such as planthoppers and leaf folders in rice. Most of the times farmers only apply nitrogen and not phosphorus and potash. Potash induces resistance in plants against pests. Likewise, excess use of water should also be avoided. In rice, it has been found that continuous flooding of fields is as good as alternate wetting and drying. Drying of the field at some intervals helps reduce the incidence of planthoppers in rice.</p><p>viii) Harvesting: Crops should be harvested at the optimum time. These should be harvested in such a manner that pests inside the stubbles get destroyed. The harvesting of rice at ground level destroys larvae of stem borer, thereby reducing pest survival for the next season.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>ix) Mechanical and physical methods:</head><p>The removal of infected plant parts and conspicuous pest stages manually or mechanically can reduce pest incidence to a certain extent. Dead hearts, whiteheads, silver shoots, aphid-infested shoots, bored brinjal, and bhindi fruits should be picked and destroyed. Similarly, egg masses, hairy caterpillars, and beetles can also be collected and killed by dipping in kerosene. Light traps can be used for attracting and killing moths of stem borers, leaf folders and case worms, etc. (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.16). Although mechanical methods are labour intensive these prove very effective if practiced at the initiation of pest incidence. Likewise, pheromone traps carrying female moths' smell can also be used to attract and destroy male moths (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.17). predators, parasitoids, and pathogens in fields, and these help to reduce pest incidence if not harmed by broad-spectrum pesticides. The egg parasitoids Trichogramma are very effective against stem borers, fruit borers, and bollworms. Likewise, there are several effective larval and pupal parasites. Predators such as coccinellids, syrphids, spiders, dragonflies, ground beetles, and rove beetles also devour pest populations in the field (Fig. <ref type="figure" target="#fig_10">5</ref>.18). The vertebrate predators like fish, ducks, and frogs also consumers pests in rice ecosystems. Likewise, bacteria (Bt), fungi, and viruses (NPV) also kill pests. Artificial releases of natural enemies are also carried out to combat these pests (Table <ref type="table" target="#tab_3">5</ref>.2).  </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>d. Chemical control:</head><p>Pesticides have a definite role to play in pest management. However, their application should be need-based and in a judicious manner. The pesticide consumption can be greatly reduced, and these can be made safer for the environment by adopting improved techniques and proper timing of application e.g. planthoppers are controlled more effectively if a spray is directed at the base of rice plants. Regular monitoring of pests should be carried out and pesticides should only be applied if the population has reached the economic threshold level. The ETL-based pesticide use causes a substantial reduction in pesticide requirement. If pest infestation begins in the nursery then it should be nipped there itself, because it is easier to manage pests at a small scale and this will also not pollute the environment. The perusal of various control methods reveals their effectiveness in general against pests. Depending upon the pest problem, the relevant and mutually compatible methods can be selected and integrated to achieve pest suppression. Following is an example of the integration of different control methods for managing rice pests.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Integrated management of rice insect pests</head><p>• Cultivation of resistant cultivars like Vajram, Chaitanya, Nagarjuna, Pratibha,</p><p>• Manasarovar and other high-yielding varieties/ cultures like Badava Mahsuri and IET 7251. In this way, pest management packages can be formulated against key pests of other crops also. The adoption of IPM packages will help to reduce dependence on pesticides and pests can be managed in an eco-friendly and sustainable manner.</p><p>Contrary to the belief, the pesticide is not a bad word in pest management.</p><p>Pesticides have to play a definite role in pest suppression. However, their use has to be judicious and need-based. The need for pesticides should be determined through regular monitoring and economic threshold level.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Check Your Progress 5.4</head><p>Note: a) Use the spaces given below for your answers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b</head><p>) Check your answer with those given at the end of the unit. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6">PESTICIDE RESIDUES AND CONSEQUENCES</head><p>The amount of pesticide, its derivatives, and adjuvants found in or on a treated substrate such as plant, animal, soil after various intervals of time is called "residue". The amount of pesticide initially deposited on the treated surface may be termed as "deposit". The residue is expressed as parts per million (ppm) or billion (ppb) or even trillion (ppt) or even at lower levels. Some portion of the deposited pesticide applied on plant surface slowly gets weathered and whatsoever amount penetrates the system is termed as "effective residue". Residue found in the substrate at the time of harvest is called "harvest time residue".</p><p>After application, degradation of pesticides takes place due to physical factors like light, temperature, moisture, rainfall, wind velocity, and biological factors such as animals, plants, and microorganisms. Degradation refers to any change in the molecular structure of the pesticide or its products. Terms such as decomposition and break down are analogues to degradation.</p><p>The disappearance of residues refers to the apparent loss of the parent pesticide. Initially, the rate of disappearance is fast and is known as dissipation. may also be called as the first phase of disappearance. Later the rate of disappearance slows down and there is a slow decrease in the amount of residue. This is known as persistence. The rate of disappearance of residues of pesticides can be expressed in terms of half-life, which is defined as the time required for half of the amount of initial deposit of pesticide to disappear.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6.1">Adverse Effect of Pesticide Residues</head><p>Pesticides are poisons and can cause carcinogenic, mutagenic, and teratogenic effects in animals. Some of the pesticides like the majority of chlorinated hydrocarbons undergo biomagnification as they move from lower trophic levels to higher trophic levels along the food chain e.g. DDT, aldrin, endrin, etc. are lipophilic and after entering the living system these keep depositing in fatty tissues without being excreted. This way these chemicals reach a million times higher concentrations in organisms like big fish, birds, and human beings, which are at the higher end of the food chain than their concentration in water. When these concentrations reach lethal levels these may prove fatal. Keeping in view the adverse effects of pesticides on humans, animals, and the environment as a whole, these should be used judiciously and commodities treated with them should only be consumed or used when residue levels are at non-harmful levels. To safeguard the health of humans and animals, safety measures like acceptable daily intake (ADI), waiting periods, maximum residual limits (MRL), etc. are fixed and implemented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.6.2">Safety Precautions against Residues</head><p>Following are the important safety precautions against pesticides residue:</p><p>a.</p><p>Waiting period: The waiting period is the time that must elapse between pesticide application and crop harvest. MRLs are defined as the maximum concentration of pesticide residue likely to occur in or on food and feeding stuff after the use of pesticides according to Good Agricultural Practice (GAP). The GAP refers to the application of pesticides in line with the product label recommendations and keeping with local environmental and other conditions. These are expressed as milligrams (mg) of residue per kilogram of food/animal feeding stuff.</p><p>MRL levels are set by the Codex Alimentarius Commission, a United Nations agency managed and funded jointly by the World Health Organization (WHO) and the Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>b. Maximum residue limit:</head><p>Where there is an approved use of the compound on a particular crop or for pesticide residues on imported produce (import tolerance), the MRL is generally set at a value determined from field trials. In field trials, the crop is treated with the pesticide, and samples of the crop are analyzed to determine residue levels. MRLs can typically be less than a milligram (mg) of pesticide residue in a kilogram of food (1mg/kg or less) up to 5 mg/kg.</p><p>However, where there is neither approved use nor an 'import tolerance', a residue level is set at the 'Limit of Determination (LOD)'. This is an effective 'zero' level of residues reflecting the lowest level at which reliable quantitative analysis can be performed. A LOD MRL can also be set where an approved use is not expected to result in residues and this has been demonstrated from the field trial data. The LOD MRLs are usually between 0.01 and 0.05 mg/kg.</p><p>MRLs are intended primarily as a check that the pesticide is being used correctly and to assist international trade in treated produce. MRLs are primarily trading standards but they also help ensure that residue levels do not pose unacceptable risks for consumers.</p><p>The MRL is not a health-based exposure limit and exposure to residues over an MRL does not necessarily imply a health risk. This is because the use of a pesticide would not be allowed if the proposed MRL resulted in long-term and short-term exposure of pesticide residues in the human diet above safety limits such as the Acceptable Daily Intake (ADI)) and Acute Reference Dose (ARfD).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acceptable daily intake (ADI)</head><p>The ADI is the amount of a pesticide in food or drinking water that can be ingested (orally) daily over a lifetime without an appreciable health risk. ADIs are expressed in milligrams of the substance per kilogram of body weight per day (mg/kg body weight/day). An ADI value is based on current research, with long-term studies on animals and observations on humans.</p><p>The studies are performed with several doses including high doses. First, a No Observable Adverse Effect Level (NOAEL) is determined based on these studies. The NOAEL refers to the amount of a pesticide that shows no toxic effects. In the case of several studies on different effects, the lowest NOAEL is usually taken. The NOAEL is then scaled down by a safety factor, conventionally 100, to account for the differences between test animals and humans and possible differences in sensitivity among humans.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acute reference dose (ARfD)</head><p>The ARfD is defined as an amount of a pesticide in food or drinking water that can be ingested in 24 hours or less without appreciable health risks to the consumer based on all known facts at the time of the evaluation. This is expressed on a bodyweight basis. The ADI and ARfD are calculated before any pesticide approval is given. The MRL is not linked to the ADI or ARfD, and could result in dietary intakes considerably below these safety levels. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.7">LET US SUM UP</head><p>After studying this unit, you have learned that:</p><p>• Since man started agriculture, he has been disturbing the balance of nature by reducing environmental resistance through ecologically unsound methods of cultivation. Even any slight decrease in any of the processes of 'environment resistance' results in a population explosion of an insect species and the consequent epidemics. Man's interference in ecosystems thus causes the intensification of insects and diseases on crops.</p><p>• Rapid and accurate diagnosis of insect pests and diseases is necessary before we can adopt proper control measures. It is the first step towards the study of any pest and its management. Diagnosis is largely done based on characteristic symptoms expressed by the affected plant.</p><p>• Sole reliance on pesticides created several problems such as the development of resistant pests, pest outbreaks, mortality of useful organisms, adverse effect on human health, and environmental degradation. As a result, integrated pest management came into vogue.</p><p>• Integrated pest management (IPM) refers to the use of available pest control methods in a unified manner to reduce pest population below economic levels and ensure favorable economic, ecological, and economic consequences.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>•</head><p>In IPM different methods of pest control such as resistant varieties, cultural methods, physical methods, natural enemies, and pesticides are integrated to suppress pest population without jeopardizing other components of the environment. Any pest management programme should be preferably based upon the use of resistant cultivars and natural enemies and other control methods should be blended with them for tackling pest menace.</p><p>• Pesticides are poisons and can cause carcinogenic, mutagenic, and 4.</p><p>is the abnormal increase in the size of a plant organ due to an increase in the number of cells while hypertrophy refers to the increased size of the organ due to an increase in the size of cells.</p><p>Check Your Progress 5.4</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>1.</head><p>The EIL refers to the minimum pest population or damage that causes economic damage.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Enhanced efficiency of some natural enemies</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Clean cultivation, tillage, sowing time, intercropping, crop rotation, etc.</p><p>Check Your Progress 5.5</p><p>1.</p><p>The amount of pesticide, its derivatives, and adjuvants found in or on a treated substrate such as plant, animal, soil after various intervals of time is called "residue".</p><p>2. Carcinogenic, mutagenic, and teratogenic effects.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>The waiting period is the time that must elapse between pesticide application and crop harvest.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>The ADI is the amount of a pesticide in food or drinking water that can be ingested (orally) daily over a lifetime without an appreciable health risk. The ARfD is defined as an amount of pesticide in food or drinking water that can be ingested in 24 hours or less without appreciable health risks to the consumer based on all known facts at the time of the evaluation.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.11">TERMINAL QUESTIONS</head><p>1.</p><p>Explain the main causes of pest intensification on crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2.</head><p>Describe major factors responsible for pest epidemics.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3.</head><p>Write short note on Koch's postulates.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4.</head><p>Discuss principles of pest management.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5.</head><p>Explain pest management approaches.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.</head><p>Write a short note on the maximum residue limit (MRL).</p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head>v)</head><label></label><figDesc>Monogenic resistant cultivars: Monogenic resistant cultivars may lead to the development of pest biotypes. It has happened in the case of rice where several biotypes of gall midge and brown planthopper (BPH) have evolved in response to wide-scale cultivation of monogenic resistant cultivars against these pests. vi) Excessive use of fertilizers and irrigation: Instead of applying fertilizers in a balanced manner, excessive use of nitrogenous fertilizers has resorted to that stimulates pest reproduction. Likewise, excessive use of irrigation also aggravates pests in crops. Heavy doses of nitrogenous fertilizers accompanied by continuous flooding of rice fields create favorable conditions for rice BPH. vii) Indiscriminate use of pesticides: Indiscriminate use of broadspectrum pesticides leads to the death of natural enemies of pests and their continuous use evolves pests that are resistant to pesticides. In such a situation, when neither pesticide is effective nor natural enemies are there, pests wreak havoc. Likewise, excessive use of pesticides also results in the outbreak of secondary pests. viii) Import &amp; export of agricultural commodities: Due to quarantine negligence, foreign pests sometimes enter new territories where their natural enemies are not present. Due to reduced environment resistance, they proliferate and realize very high densities. ix) Introduction of crops in new areas: If a crop is introduced into a new area where crops sharing pest fauna with the introduced crop are grown, it would increase pest problems. x) Climate change: Climate change is also responsible for causing shifts in pest fauna of crops in different regions. A northward shift in favorable zones of crops, as well as pests, is being observed with climate change. Pests might thus gain entry into new areas and in the event of reduced environmental resistance might realize higher populations. Check Your Progress 5.1 Note: a) Use the spaces given below for your answers.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>Your Progress 5. 2 Note</head><label>2</label><figDesc>: a) Use the spaces given below for your answers.b)Check your answer with those given at the end of the unit.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head>Fig. 5 . 1 :</head><label>51</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.1: Wheat affected by yellow rust</figDesc><graphic coords="7,265.13,193.49,207.75,136.20" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_3"><head>Fig. 5 . 2 :</head><label>52</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.2: Powdery mildew on grapes Courtesy: www.britannica.com</figDesc><graphic coords="7,300.25,586.91,137.50,107.05" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>Fig. 5 . 3 :</head><label>53</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.3: False smut disease in rice iv) White blisters: In crucifers and many other plants, numerous white, blister-like pustules are found on leaves. They broke open the epidermis and expose white powdery masses of spores. Often, such symptoms have been called white rust but since there is nothing common between them and true rusts, they are more appropriately termed as white blisters.</figDesc><graphic coords="8,118.78,131.00,212.45,147.70" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head>Fig. 5 . 4 :</head><label>54</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.4: Black spot Courtesy: www.britannica.com xii) Dieback: This disease is characterized by the progressive death of twigs, branches, or shoots, from the tip backward. Dieback is caused by many fungi and a few bacteria that produce cankers, anthracnose, wilts, and stem or root rots. Nematodes, stem or root boring insects, mechanical damage, paving over roots, winter injury from cold and a deficiency or excess of moisture or an essential element may cause dieback. xiii) Blight: Symptoms of blight include sudden and severe yellowing, browning, spotting, withering, or dying of leaves, flowers, fruit, stems, or the entire plant e.g. late blight disease of potato and tomato</figDesc><graphic coords="9,296.25,478.54,145.50,103.30" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Fig. 5 . 5 :</head><label>55</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.5: Late blight Courtesy: www.brittanica.com xiv) Streaks or stripes: These are elongated but relatively narrow lesions containing dead cells. These are initially yellowish before the death of affected cells. xv) Damping-off: In this disease, the tender stem of seedlings is attacked near the soil line. The affected portion becomes constricted due to necrosis and seedling collapses. This is caused by seed-and soilborne fungi.</figDesc><graphic coords="10,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Fig. 5 . 6 :</head><label>56</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.6: Wilt disease in chillies</figDesc><graphic coords="10,87.38,564.64,275.25,206.40" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>i) Stem boring: Stem borer larvae bore into plant stems and cause their death. Rice stem borer causes the death of central shoot called 'dead heart' in young plants and death of panicle known as 'white ear' in maturing plants (Fig. 5.7). Likewise, maize stem borer and sugarcane early shoot borer also cause dead heart symptoms. The damaged shoot can easily be pulled out occasionally with larva still inside it.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head>Fig. 5 . 7 :</head><label>57</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.7: Stem borer damage in rice</figDesc><graphic coords="11,227.29,425.51,284.63,160.72" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.8: Brinjal damaged by fruit borer</figDesc><graphic coords="12,130.13,54.00,207.75,155.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.9: Cabbage defoliated by cabbage butterfly C. Leaf mining Insect larvae make mines in the leaf tissue by eating away the green tissue e.g. citrus leaf miner, pea leaf miner. White zigzag pathways can easily be spotted on the upper leaf surface or both sides (Fig. 5.10).</figDesc><graphic coords="12,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.10: Leaf miner damage in soybean</figDesc><graphic coords="12,104.47,616.79,241.06,130.85" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.11: Leaf folder damage in rice</figDesc><graphic coords="13,254.41,122.09,230.25,156.00" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.12: Rice crop damaged due to plant hopper sucking Check Your Progress 3 Note: a) Use the spaces given below for your answers. b)Check your answer with those given at the end of the unit.</figDesc><graphic coords="13,246.39,467.05,246.28,185.08" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. 5.13: IPM components a. Resistant cultivars: Preference should be given to the cultivation of resistant cultivars because their use greatly reduces the need for other methods of pest control (Fig. 5.14).The resistant cultivars enhance the efficiency of some natural enemies against the pests, for example, there is more predation of spiders against planthoppers on moderately resistant varieties than susceptible varieties. Likewise, on moderately resistant cultivars, the need for pesticide application is greatly reduced.Similarly, these are also compatible with cultural methods of pest control. However, the continuous use of resistant varieties has given rise to the problem of biotype development in some insects.</figDesc><graphic coords="18,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_16"><head>Fig. 5 .</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.14: Resistant and susceptible germplasm Biotypes of brown planthopper and gall midge have developed due to the cultivation of monogenic resistant varieties of rice. Resistant cultivars of various crops against insect pests are presented in Table 5.1.Table 5.1: Resistant cultivars/sources of resistance against insect pests in different crops</figDesc><graphic coords="19,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Fig. Tillage and irrigation</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. Tillage and irrigation</figDesc><graphic coords="22,115.43,54.00,219.15,179.80" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head>Fig. 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc>Fig. 5.16: Light trap Fig. 5.17: Pheromone trap c. Biological control: There is a rich diversity of natural enemies viz.predators, parasitoids, and pathogens in fields, and these help to reduce pest incidence if not harmed by broad-spectrum pesticides. The egg parasitoids Trichogramma are very effective against stem borers, fruit borers, and bollworms. Likewise, there are several effective larval and pupal parasites. Predators such as coccinellids, syrphids, spiders, dragonflies, ground beetles, and rove beetles also devour pest populations in the field (Fig.5.18). The vertebrate predators like fish, ducks, and frogs also consumers pests in rice ecosystems. Likewise, bacteria (Bt), fungi, and viruses (NPV) also kill pests. Artificial</figDesc><graphic coords="23,369.85,359.01,175.90,206.22" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_19"><head>Fig. Spider-predator of pests</head><label></label><figDesc>Fig. Spider-predator of pests</figDesc><graphic coords="24,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>•</head><label></label><figDesc>Deep ploughing and raking of bunds to kill soil-dwelling pest stages and grasshopper egg pods • Altering planting time, preponing, or postponing depending upon pests in the area • Clipping of seedling tips at the time of transplanting to destroy stem borer and hispa eggs • Dipping seedlings in chlorpyriphos for protection against stem borer and planthoppers • Formation of alleyways in the field for proper air circulation • Synchronous planting for avoiding food availability to pests for a longer period • Balanced use of fertilizers with emphasis on recommended N dose • Field sanitation-removal of excess nurseries and weeds from the field • Water management-draining of water from field at certain intervals • Conservation of natural enemies through the need-based and selective use of pesticides.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_21"><head>Check Your Progress 5. 5 1 ) 2 )</head><label>512</label><figDesc>Note: a)Use the spaces given below for your answers.b) Check your answer with those given at the end of the unit. What is pesticide residue? What sort of effects can pesticide residues inflict on organisms?</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="1,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="2,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="4,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="6,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="14,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="15,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="16,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="17,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="20,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="21,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="25,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="27,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="28,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="30,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="31,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="32,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><graphic coords="33,14.85,289.49,564.30,249.02" type="bitmap" /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 5</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table /><note>.1.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 5 .1: Resistant cultivars/sources of resistance against insect pests in different crops Crop Pest Cultivars</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Rice</cell><cell>Stem borer</cell><cell>Deepti, Rama, Ratna, Sasyasree, TKM-6,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vikas, IR 20, IR 26</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Gall midge</cell><cell>Karna, Lalat, Sarasa, Ahaya, Ruchi, Kshira,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Dhanyalaxmi, Pothan, Mahaveer, Divya,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>IR36, Kakatiya, Kunti, Phalguna, Shakti,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Surekha</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Brown planthopper</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Multiple resistance</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Gall midge, BPH,</cell><cell>Suraksha, Shaktiman</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>WBPH</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Gall midge, BPH, GLH Daya, Lalat</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Gall midge, BPH,</cell><cell>Kshira</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>WBPH, GLH</cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>Bhadra, Chandana, CO 42, Jyoti, Kanaka, Pratibha, Vajram, Chaitanya, Nagarjuna, Sonasali, Manasarovar, Krishnaveni, Kakatiya, Aruna, Makom, Remya, HKR 120 Green leafhopper IR 20, Vani, Vikramarya Leaf folder Adt-34, Dular, Giza-171, Basmati Dwarf, Pattambi-29, IR-28, IR-50, Tainan-3, Pusa-1120-7-3 Aphids SPV 1450, SPV 1359, SPV 1155, SPV 1380, SPV 1413, SPV 1452, SPV 1453, SPV 1462, SPV 1465, Selection 3, SPH 1162, SPH 1174, SPH 1020, SPH 1026, SPH 1079 DPL 7, DPL 16, DPL 26, DPL 34, PL 81-1, PL 88-54, PL 406, L 19-12, L 4136, L 4150, LL 56, LH 88-8, DHL 90-13 Pigeonpea Gram pod borer Pod fly ICPL (Abhaya), ICPL 87088, ICPL 84060, ICPL-1, ICPL-2, ICPL 87-1, ICP 10466-E3, IPCL-6, JAT-10, UPAS-120, ICP-903E, ICP-1903E ICPL 82064-E15-E, PDA-881E, PDA-882E,PDA-883E, ICP 7946, PDA-89-2E, ICP 8102-5-6, ICP 7946, MA2, PDE-89-23</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 5 .2: Biological suppression of crop pests with released predators, parasitoids / sprayed pathogens Pest Natural enemy Release/application</head><label>5</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Rice yellow stem</cell><cell>Trichogramma</cell><cell>Inundative release @50,000-</cell></row><row><cell>borer &amp; leaf folder</cell><cell>japonicum &amp; T.</cell><cell>100, 000/ha/week for 5</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>chilonis</cell><cell>weeks</cell></row><row><cell>Sugarcane pyrilla</cell><cell>Epiricania</cell><cell>Periodic release @8000-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>melanoleuca</cell><cell>10,000 cocoons or 800,000-</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>1000,000 eggs/ha</cell></row><row><cell>Maize stem borer</cell><cell>T. chilonis</cell><cell>Inundative releases @</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>100,000/ha/3 days -5 times</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>(Singh, 2002)</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Tobacco caterpillar Telenomus remus</cell><cell>3 fortnightly releases @</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>(egg parasitoid)</cell><cell>40,000/ha</cell></row><row><cell>Cotton bollworms</cell><cell>T. chilonis (Bio</cell><cell>@ 1,50,000/ha/7-10 days</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>C1, Bio C6)</cell><cell>during egg laying period</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Chrysopa carnea</cell><cell>@ 2 larvae/plant during peak</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>egg hatching</cell></row><row><cell>Apple San Jose</cell><cell>Encarsia</cell><cell>@ 2000/infested tree</cell></row><row><cell>scale</cell><cell>perniciosi or</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Aphytis sp.</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>@20/infested tree</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Chilocorus</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>infernalis</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Apple wooly aphid Aphelinus mali</cell><cell>-</cell></row><row><cell>Codling moth</cell><cell>T. embrophagum</cell><cell>@2000/tree during active</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>egg laying period</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_0">Indian Agriculture</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" xml:id="foot_1">Pest and Disease Management</note>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mealybugs &amp; scale insects</head><p>Cryptolaemus montrouzieri @10-50 beetles/plant</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cottony cushion scale</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Rodolia cardinalis -</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anar butterfly</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Deudorix isocrates</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>T. chilonis</head><p>Inundative release @50,000/ ha/week Efforts should be made to enhance natural enemies by providing artificial foods and shelters. The application of broadspectrum pesticides poses the greatest hazard to the natural enemies of pests. The preference should be given to selective pesticides such as neem, Bt, NPV, diflubenzuron, propargite, cartap, etc. which do not harm nontarget organisms.</p><p>In the absence of selective pesticides, even non-selective pesticides can be applied to achieve the same purpose through suitable formulations. The teratogenic effects in organisms. Therefore to safeguard human and animal health, safety measures like acceptable daily intake (ADI), waiting periods, maximum residual limits (MRLs), etc are fixed and implemented.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.8">KEYWORDS</head><p>Diagnosis: It is the identification of the nature and cause of anything.</p><p>Pest resurgence: When a resistance problem arises neither pesticides kill pests nor their natural enemies are present, and hence pest population explodes. This is known as pest resurgence.</p><p>Pest : A plant or animal detrimental to humans or human concerns (as agriculture or livestock production)</p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Agricultural Entomology</title>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Anonymous</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1983">1983</date>
			<publisher>All India Scientific Writers Society</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">436</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Agricultural Pests of India and South East Asia</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Atwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1986">1986</date>
			<publisher>Kalyani Publishers</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">529</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Insect Pests of Rice and Their Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Chander</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">A Text Book of Rice Agronomy</title>
				<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2000">2000</date>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="173" to="190" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Rajendra Prasad</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<monogr>
		<title/>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Sunil</forename><surname>Kumar</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">Jain</forename></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="page">238</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Integrated Pest Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><forename type="middle">S</forename><surname>Dhaliwal</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">G</forename><surname>Arora</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2006">2006</date>
			<publisher>Kalyani Publishers</publisher>
			<pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Biological Pest Suppression</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">D</forename><surname>Gautam</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="2008">2008</date>
			<publisher>Westville</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">288</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Introduction to Insect Pest Management</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><forename type="middle">L</forename><surname>Metcalf</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Luckman</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<editor>W.H.</editor>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982</date>
			<publisher>John Wiley &amp; Sons</publisher>
			<pubPlace>USA</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b7">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Household and Kitchen-garden Pests</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">H</forename><surname>Singh</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<imprint>
			<date type="published" when="1984">1984</date>
			<publisher>Kalyani Publishres</publisher>
			<biblScope unit="page">420</biblScope>
			<pubPlace>New Delhi</pubPlace>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b8">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">10 ANSWERS TO CHECK YOUR PROGRESS Check Your Progress</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b9">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">Due to interaction between organism&apos;s biotic potential and environmental resistance</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b10">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Monoculture, multiple cropping, monogenic resistant cultivars</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">etc. Check Your Progress</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b11">
	<monogr>
		<title level="m" type="main">When the pest population suddenly attains a very high population, this is called a pest epidemic</title>
		<imprint/>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b12">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Human manipulation of the environment, foreign pests, etc</title>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="s">Check Your Progress</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">3</biblScope>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
