<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">UNIT 13 CROP DISEASES Structure</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<address>
									<addrLine>8.1 Wheat 13.8.2 Rice 13.8.3 Maize 13.8.4 Pea 13.8.5 Pigeon Pea 13.8.6 Tomato and Porato 13.8.7 Rapeseed and Mustard 13.8.8 Cotton 13.8.9 Sugatcane</addrLine>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">UNIT 13 CROP DISEASES Structure</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">926D8BEDB608704BF93B06D3EBA342FA</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:46+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>Objectives 13.2 Concept of Plant Diseases 13.3 Nature of Plant Diseases 13.3.1 Non-infectious or Abiotic Diseases 13.3.2 Infectious or Biotic Plant Diseases 13.4 Seed-borne Diseases 13.4.1 Seed-borne Pathogens 13.4.2 Seed-borne Disease 13.4.3 External or Internal Seed-borne Pathogen 13.5 Soil-borne Diseases 13.5.1 Soil-borne Pathogens 13.5.2 Soil-borne Diseases 13.6 Air-borne Diseases 13.6.1 Air-borne Pathogens 13.6.2 Air-borne Diseases 13.7 Fungicides 13.7.1 Fungicide 13.7.2 Systemic Fungicides 13.7.3 Characters of a Good Fungicide 13.7.4 Classification of Fungicides 13.8 Diseases of Major Crops 13.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.1">INTRODUCTION</head><p>Plant diseases originated along with the plants. When man started growing food they also unwillingly started culturing the pathogen. The outbreak of plant diseases, then, must have occurred much before recorded history. Developments in "Biological Sciences" adding new dimensions to science of understanding the nature of pathogen and diseases plant as well as art of treating the sick plants.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Objectives</head><p>After going through this unit you should be able to define and discuss plant diseases and their causes, discuss the nature and type of pathogens, define and discuss the nature of diseases, list the various fungicides (chemicals) presently being used for crop protection, list causes, syrnptomatology and describe control measures for various diseases in crop plants, and apply these concepts to manage practical problems in field.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.2">CONCEPT OF PLANT DISEASES</head><p>Plant disease can be defined as malfunctioning of host cells and tissues that results from their continuous irritation by a pathogenic agent or environmental factor and leads to development of symptoms, which results in reduced economic value of the produce. Disease is a condition involving abnormal changes in the form, physiology, integrity, or behaviour of the plant. Such changes may result in partial impairment or death of the plant or its parts.</p><p>Pathogen: A pathogen is an agency which incites the disease Parasite: An organism which subsists wholly and partially upon living tissues Pathogens may cause disease in plants by <ref type="bibr">(1)</ref> weakening the host by continually absorbing food from host cells for their own use, (2) killing or disturbing the fietabolism of host cells through toxins, enzymes or growth regulating substances they secrete, (3) blocking the transportation of food, mineral nutrients and water through the conductive tissues, and (4) I consuming the contents of host cells upon contact. Diseases caused by environmental factors result from extremes in the conditions (temperature, moisture, light and so on) for its normal course of growth and in excessive or deficient amounts of chemicals absorbed or required by plan$.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ 1</head><p>i) Define plant disease.</p><p>ii) List thc factors due to which pathogen causes disease in plants.</p><p>--</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.2">NATURE OF PLANT DISEASES</head><p>Tens of thousands of diseases affect cultivated plants. Each kind of pathogen may affect anywhere from one variety to hundreds of species of plants. To facilitate the study of plant diseases they are grouped in ordinary fashion.</p><p>For practical purposes diseases are classified according to their symptoms (i.e. rusts, smuts, wilts, blights, cankers, mildews, damping off etc.), plant organs they affect (e.g. leaf spots, root rot, fruit rot, stem lesions etc.) and mode of survival and dispersal of their pathogens (e.g. seed-borne, soil-borne and air-borne). The most useful criterion for classification of dlsease, however is the type of pathogen that causes the disease. ?he advantage of such classification is that it indicates the cause of disease, knowledge of which suggests the probable development and spread of the disease and also possible control measures. On this basis, plant diseases are classified as follows:</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.3.1">Non-infectious or Abiotic Diseases</head><p>These diseases are consequence of </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.3.2">Inrectious or Biotic Plant Diseases</head><p>These diseases can be further grouped as: 1) Diseases caused by fungi 2) Diseases caused by prokaryotes (bacteria and phytoplasms)</p><p>3) Diseases causetl by parasitic higher plants 4) Diseases caused by viruses, viroids 5) Diseases caused by nematodes 6) Diseases caused by protozoa Infectious diseases are often classified according to their occurrence in following groups: i) Endemic diseases: When a disease is more or less constantly present from year to year in moderate to severe form in a particular area, it is called endemic to that area.</p><p>ii) Epidemic or Epiphytotic diseases: An epiphytotic disease is one which occurs widely but periodically. It may be present constantly in the locality but assumes severe proportions only on occasions.</p><p>iii) Sporadic diseases: Sporadic diseases are those diseases which occur at very irregular intervals and locations and in relatively few instances.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.4">SEED-BORNE DISEASES</head><p>In broad agronomical sense seed refers to all the materials used for propagation of crops.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.4.1">Seed-borne Pathogen</head><p>Any infectious agent that is associated with the seed and has a potential to cause the disease termed as seed-borne pathogen. This includes all pathogenic fungi, bacteria, viruses and nematodes which are carried on, in, or with the seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.4.2">Seed-borne Disease</head><p>This term is usually used to ind~cate the mode of perpetuation of the pathogen responsible for a disease through the agency of the seed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.4.3">External or Internal Seed-borne Pathogen</head><p>These terms indicate the location of a pathogen in relation to seed. If a pathogen is located on the outer surface of seed it is called externally seed-borne and if located inside the seed, it is internally seed-borne i.e. loose smut of wheat.</p><p>Diseases caused by externally or internally seed-borne pathogens are called externally and internally seed-borne &amp;seases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.5">SOIL-BORNE DISEASES</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.5.1">Soil-borne Pathogens</head><p>Any pathogen that perpetuates in soil and cause disease when host plant is grown in that soil, is termed as soil-borne pathogen. This includes all pathogeilic fungi, bacteria, and nematodes surviving in soil.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.5.2">Soil-borne Diseases</head><p>In case of soil-borne diseases the pathogen persists in the soil far a long period and cause disease in the crop grown there. Most of the nematode diseases are soil bome in nature.</p><p>Root rot and wilt are main soil bome diseases. Soil-borne diseases cause endemic diseases because of their slow spread as compared to air-borne and seed-borne diseases p~ 13.6 AIR-BORNE &amp;EASES -</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.6.1">Air-borne Pathogens</head><p>These are also known as foliar pathogens causing foliar diseases. In this case pathogen survives in weed hosts during off season and the wind-borne inoculurn of pathogen is carried to the crop plants and cause diseases in crops. These pathogens produce enomom9 spores.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.6.2">Air-borne Diseases</head><p>In this case, me pathogen survives in weed plants (alternate or collateral hosts) during off season and cause infection by means of air-borne spores, in the crop, grown during the crop season, e.g. leaf blights, rusts, false smut etc.</p><p>Air-borne patbogens have caused several epiphytotics in the past, due to their fast spreading nature e.g. Potato late blight (Irish femine), Helminthospcnium blight of rice (Bengal fernine) and several epiphytotics of wheat rusts.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.7">FUNGICIDES</head><p>Fungicides are very important tools for managing the plant diseases. Literally "fungicide" should mean a chemical capable of killing fungi.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.7.1">Fungicide</head><p>A fungicide may be defined as "any chemical substance which has the ability to prevent damage caused by fungi to growing crops and their products.</p><p>Fungistat Some chemicals do not kill the fungi. 'Ihey simply inhibit fungal growth temporarily. If the fungus is freed lYom such substances, it would revive such a chemical is called as "fungistat".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Protectants</head><p>Fungicide which is effective only if applied prior to fungal infection is called a protectant, e.g. 'S' fungicides, Zineb etc.</p><p>Horsfall(1957) classified protectant fungicides as contact and residual fungicides. Contact fungicide is one which is aimed to seek out the fungus at rest, either before or after the fungus has found the host.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Eradicants</head><p>Erad~cants are those which remove pathogenic fungi from an infection court (area of the host around a propagating unit of fungus in which infection could possibly occur), e.g., Lime Selphor organic mercurials, dodine etc. Eradicants are protectants also.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Therapeutants</head><p>Fungicide which is capable of eradicating a fungus after it has caused infection and thereby curing the plant, is called a therapeutant, e.g. Oxathin, Quinon fungicides, Aureofungin etc.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.7.2">Systemic Fungicides</head><p>Systemic fungicide are those which act by entering in to the system of plants. Most systemic fungicides act by inhibiting fungal growth by interference with specific biochemical processes and consequently are often referred to as "site-specific" e.g., Carboxamides (Oxathies), phenylamides, and hydroxypyrimidine are "narrow spectrum" and others including benzimidazoles and inhibitors of sterol biosynthesis have "broader specuum".</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.7.3">Characters of a Good Fungicide</head><p>A good fungicide should have the following qualities:</p><p>1) High field performance: This is further determined by following factors as: a) 'The inherent fungitoxicity b) Availability of the active constituent so that it can act against fungi c) Good coverage of host surface d) Initial deposition on host in case of spraying or dusting.</p><p>e) 'Ihe tenacity of the residue which would determine the residual effect.</p><p>2) Low phytotoxicity 3) Stability in storage 4) Stability after dilution to spray strength 5) Low toxicity to human beings and cattles.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.7.4">Classification of Fungicides</head><p>According to chemical nature   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The initial symptoms appears as small oval, brown and discoloured lesions on the lower leaves. Further these spots enlarged and cover larger areas eventually resulting in the death of the entire leaf giving it blighted appearance. In severe attack leaf sheaths, awns and glumes are also infected. Heads are bronzed and white.</p><p>The pathogen survives in seed and soil as saprophytes on crop residue.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Seed treatment with Thiram (@ 2.5 gkg) or Bavistin @ 2g/kg of seed to control seed borne inoculwn ii) Spraying plants with indophil-M45 or Ziram or indophil z-78 or Tilt (propiconazole) @ 2 gnitre of water.</p><p>iii) Adequate fertilizer (N:P:K) and irrigation application</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Rusts</head><p>Rusts are the most important diseases of wheat. Three types of rusts that occur on whedt are commonly known as yellow, brown and black rusts. Brown and yellow rusts are causing damage to the early sown wheat crops whereas, the black rust appears late and normally do not cause substantial damage except m the late sown crops.</p><p>i) Brown or leaf rust</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Puccinia reconditu</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>This is the earliest rust to appear as small, round, light yellowish brown pustules 011 the leaves which later turn black covered by tlie epidermis. The rust pustule mostly develops on the leaf and leaf sheaths. The uredial pustules are bright orange in colour are never in rows but are either in small clusters or irregularly scattered.</p><p>In case ;)f severe attack the plants mature early, produce light and shrivelled grains with poor developinent of root system. This rust is most widespread and causes serious loss in yield in n ~a ~l y 'areas.</p><p>ii) Yellow or stripe rust</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Pucciniu striiformis</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The uredopustules are formed on the leaves but in severe attacks, they are formed oil the leaf sheaths, stalks and gluines also. The green colour of the leaves fades in long streaks on which rows of siwall uredo-sori appear. The uredopustules are oval in shape, lemon yellow in colour and are arranged in rows. The arrangement of lemon yellow pustules in rows (end to end) is the characteristic feature of yellow rust. In severe attack however, these rows .are not distinct as the large patches of leaf become covered witll crowded pustules.</p><p>In severely attacked fields, the ground may appeaar orange or red due to a barge number of spores Falling on it. The fungus survives on the crops in the hills on volunteer or self sown plant stubbles etc. and on the regular crops (sunlmer &amp; winter) in the Nilgiris and Pullley hills and the submountainous regions in the 'Himalayas in the North, which become the chief source of primary infection.</p><p>iii) Black rust or Stem rust</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Puccinirt graminis tritici</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The uredial pustules appetar on stem, leaf sheath, leaves and earheads in the form of reddish brown in colour and elongated in shape. These are inorc on the stem and leaf sheaths and less on leaaves and ears. This rust spreads Fast under relatively warmer and humid environmental condtion. By the time the crop matures, dark, black, elongated, telial pustules are formed.</p><p>Black rust appears in endemic form in the southern, central and eastern India where high tenpratures prevail during wheat growing season. Black rust is called the killer of wheat plants and in severe infection there is shrivelling of grains and failure of crop.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Grow resistant varieties of wheat recommended for p~articul'ar area like Sonalika, Giri.ja, Arm, Ar-jun, PV-18, UP-301, UP2338 etc.</p><p>ii) Grow different varieties in the farm iii) Apply babanced dose of Nitrogen and Potash iv) Spray the crop in case of severe infection on good crop. Spraying will not be economical on a poor crop of wheat. Spray Indophil M-45 or Ii~dopl~il Z-78 @ 2gllitre of water with 0.1% Sandovit. Give first spray with the appearance of rust pustules in the last week of January or first week of February. Repeat sprayings at 10-12 days intervals by using 600 to 1000 litres of waterha.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause Ustilago segatum tritici</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>This is an internally seed bome disease. The earheads are smutted in which the grains are replaced by a black powdery mass of spores and finally only the naked rachis is remaining behind. As a matter of fact the diseased ears emerge a little earlier than healthy plants.</p><p>Almost every ear of a diseased plant is converted into black powder. The black powder is a mass of olive-green spores of the fungus.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>Grow resistant varieties like Kalyansona, Sonalika and PU-18.</p><p>i) Treat seeds with Vitavax @ 2-2.5 gkg seed or Rexil (@ 1.5gkg seed) before planting.</p><p>ii) Rogue out suspected diseased ears at the time of ear emergence and destroy them by burning or burying under the ground.</p><p>iii) Solar heat treatment of seeds is practicable in the hot summer areas of plains. On a bright sunny day in the last week of May or first week of June, soak the seeds in water for about 4 hours in the morning and then dry it under hot sun in the afternoon. Store the well dried seed for use in the next season.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4">) Karnal bunt</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Neovossiu indicu</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease appears when the grains have developed. In this disease, some grains in the spdce are partially or wholly converted into black powdery masses. The embryo tissue is generally not destroyed. Not all the ears in a stool carry the disease and even in the same ear only few grains (five to six only) are smutted. The black powder gives a foul smell due to presence of trimethylamine.</p><p>The fungus is both seed-borne and soil-borne and the infection occurs at flowering time by airborne sporidia.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control i) Grow resistant varieties</head><p>ii) Use disease free seeds iii) Treat seeds with ThirarnfCaptan or Vitavax @ 2-2.5 gkg seed for eliminating seed bome infection. iv) Avoid excessive irrigation at the time of flowering v) 1-2 sprays of Tilt (Propicomzole) at boot to heading stage @ 0.1% is found to be effective.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>5) Ear Cockle of Wheat</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Anguinu tritici</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The infested plants may remain dwarfed and show generally twisted, rolled and crinkled leaf blades. The glumes become more divergent and grains are replaced by hard, dark coloured galls which are full of nematodes. The dseased ears are shorter and thicker than the healthy ones and keep green longer.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>Use gall free seeds. This can be done by floating the seed with salt water. ?'he seeds are treated with 20% salt solution and stirred vigorously. The affected seeds along with galls floating on the surface can be separated with sieves. The healthy seeds settle down and call be used for sowing after washing and drying.</p><p>i ! Name the pathogens causing foliar blight in wheat.</p><p>ii) Name the iilcitants of wheat rusts.</p><p>iii) Name the causal organism of Kamal bunt and its mode of survival.</p><formula xml:id="formula_0">I I i v )</formula><p>Name the causal organism of ear cockle of wheat.</p><p>' v) What are the control measures of loose smut of wheat. vi) Describe symnptoln~ of stripe rust.</p><p>i I</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.8.2">Rice</head><p>1) Blast: This is also known as rotten neck, rice fever disease, Brusone.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Pyriculuriu oryzae (Tel. Mugnuporthe griseu)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The cliwactertstlc symptoms of the disease appear on Uie leaf and leaf sheath as brown spindle shaped lesions. 'The lesions are more or less boat or eye shaped with grey or dark brown margin. The central portion of the young spot becomes pale green or dull-greyish-green and appears water soaked but in older spots the central portions turn grey or ctraw coloured. The lesions on stems and grains are darker. In case of neck infectloll the stem below the earhead gets infected and turns into brown to black spots which may cover the entire stem. The neck infection results in dropping of panicle. Affected grains are partially filled up. Due to necrosis of neck tissues the panicle brcak and fall off which results in maximum damage.</p><formula xml:id="formula_1">I Control I i)</formula><p>Seed treatmelit with Bavistin (@ 2.0gAg) or Captanl Thiram @ 2.5 gAg of seed ii) In endemic area where the disease appears every year spray the crop with 0.1% Hinosan 50EC (1 mlll) or Belllate (lgll) or Bavistin (1 gll). Four to five sprays at 10 days interval may be needed for complete control. One spray should be given at the nursery, two during tillering stage and one to two during panicle elnergence stage.</p><p>iii) Spraying of Indophil M-45 (2.5 g/l) or Brestanol(4gll) is equally effective. iv) Grow tolerant varieties like IR-8, IR-20, IR-24, Jaya, Ralna and Vijay v) Bum affected straw and stubbles after harvest. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Typical sy~nptoin is U11 development of innumerable, dark, brown, elliptical spots on the leaves, stems and glu~ncs. In severe cases these spots may coalesce and cover the enllre Icd. I~~loresceilcc In a mature plant becomes distorted. Tlle grains fail to form. In case of early and severe ~tlfection thc head may fail to emerge from the sheath and perish without developing fully. 171c kernels of i~lfccted spikelets become shrivelled and discoloured. Entire leaf inay become brown and dry out in heavy inkection.</p><p>Control i) Treat the sceds with Captm or Tllirain @ 2.5 gkg seed .</p><p>ii) Add Muriate of Potash lo correct the potash deficiency in soil. Apply balanced dose of NPK fertilizers.</p><p>iii) Give three to four spraying of Indophil 2-78 or Indopl~il IM-45 at the rate of 2.5 g/I at 10-12 days interval just before the appearance of initial syinptolns of the disease.</p><p>iv) Grow moderatcly resistant varieties like Bala, Krishna, Sabarmati, IR-24.</p><p>v) Do not select seeds from the diseased fields and plants.</p><p>3) Sheat,h blight</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Rhizoctonia soluni (T/~unatephonu,s cucunzeris )</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The chief syinptorns develop as 2-3 centimetre long greenish-grey lesions with irregular dark brown margin on the leaf and leaf sheath. The lesions turn to straw colour and surrounded by bluish grey narrow bands. The lesions increase in size and girdle the stem.</p><p>The leaf blade of the affected sheath dries up from the tip downwards. The grains are shrivelled and poorly filled.Hemispherica1 or spherical greyish-black sclerotia are formed on the lesions which fall on the ground. Selerotia form even on the grain in case of severe infection.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>* i) Grow tolerant varieties like Saket-I, Krislwa, CR-33-11.</p><p>ii) Seed treatment with Thiram or Captan @ 2.5 gkg seed .</p><p>iii) Soil application of Thiramor Brassicol @ 25 kglha before transpkanting has been recommended.</p><p>iv) Heavy dose of Nitrogen should not be givp,n in the endemic areas of disease occurrence .</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>4) Bacterial leaf blight</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Xanfhomonas oryzae = Xunthomonas cumpestris pv. Otyzae (Ishiyama)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Sy~nptoms</head><p>The disease appears in two phases viz. Wilt or 'Kresek' phase and leaf blight phase;</p><p>Kresek phase: This is the most destructive phase of the disease which results from early systemic infection. The leaves roll completely, droop and turn yellow or grey and ultimately the tillers wither away. Affected shoot inay be completely killed in severe attack.</p><p>Leaf blight phase: The symptom is chawacterized by the appearance of straw coloured stripes with wavy margins generally on both edges of the leaves. These strines usually start from the tip and extend downwluds. The leaves turn straw yellow. Yellowish bacterial ooze appears on the surface which dry into bead like encrustations if there is no rain for a few days. This blight phase usually appears 4 to 6 weeks after transplanting. The grains are partially filled or become chaffy in the diseased plants.</p><p>The pathosen survives on the infected rice stubbles and seeds and also on some weeds.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Use disease free seeds from the reliable sources ii) Drain the slandiilg water in the field from time to time iii) Give balanced dose of NPK fertilizers after soil testing. Use of heavy dose of Nitrogen aggravates the disease iv) Spray the crop with a mixture of copper oxychloride and streptocycliile. Apply 7.5g streptocycline or Agrimycin-100 and 500 g copper oxychloride (yloldE3iitox-50) in 500 litres of water. Star1 spraying after 30 days ot trdl?splmting and repeal .after 15 days interval.</p><p>I ) Seed soaking for 12 hours and treating in hot water at 53' C for 30 t~iilutes will inake the seed free from bacterium.</p><p>vi) Grow resistant varieties like Ratna, Pusa-2-21, IR-20, Praslld, Govind, 1R-24, Jaya, Vijay, Shakti, RP-4-14, RP-5-32, Rf-31-49-2, MR1-550.</p><p>vii) In endemic areas of bacterial blight coinplete transplanting by last week ol'June.</p><p>viii) The run off water from the affected field to the adjacent rice field should be avoided.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5">) Tungro or Leaf Yellowing</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Virus (Maize Chlorotic Dwarf Virus).</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The older leaves turn yellow or,mge starting from Ihc tip and margin. Plants becoinc stunted and bear poor panicles with empty glumes due to shortening of both the leaf shealh, leaf blade and illternode. Interveinal chlorosis is observed. The young leaves of iilfectcd pluiw $are usually mottled with pale green to whitish spols, Root development is poor and the grains are usually covered with dark brown blotch.</p><p>The virus is transmitted by the nymph, adult male and female rice green leaf hopper (Nep1101etti.x irnpicriceps). The hopper becomes capable to transmit the virus dter 30 ininuLes of feecling on the diseased planls.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) The green stubbles should be uprootecl u ~d bum1 afler 11.avest.</p><p>ii) Rogue out isolated plants showing disease syinptom? in the beginning and destroy them so that the insect does not get itloculum to spread the disease.</p><p>iii) Control vector by spraying Basudin (Diazino~i) @ 1.5 kg a.i/ha. First spraying should be started in nursery after 10 days of sowing followed by next sprayings a1 15,30, 45 and 60 days after transplanting in the main field.</p><p>iv) Sevin 50WY and Dimecron-100 also control the vector populations v) Seedlings should be dipped in Carbofwa1175WP solution before transplanting. For this purpose solution dissolving 25-30g of Carbofuran 75 WP in 10 litres of water ]nay be prepared.</p><p>V I ) Whs11 the disease is spotted oil the plants the water from the fields should bc drained and soil should bc allowed to bike in the sun. Before the soil slarts cracking, tl~c field should be reflooded again.Top dressing of urea Cn\ 30-35 kg/ha should be done twice at an interval ot 15-20 days.</p><p>vri) Ideal yellowing can be minimised by spraying urea (3%) m~xed with hldopliil %-75 (2gn). About 500-600 litres ol' water will bc: ncetlcd for onc heclare. ii) Spray with Fytolan or Blitox 50 or Indophil-M45 (0.2%) after appearance of disease.</p><p>iii) Spraying should be repeated after 15 days according to severity of disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Charcoal Rot</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Mucrophominu phuseoli, Sclerotium batuticolu</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The symptoms of disease appear only near maturity. Water soaked, brown lesions appear on roots which turn brown later on. With maturity of the plants the fungi grow into the lower internodes -md cause premiture ripening and shredding resulting 111 breaking of the stalk at the crown level. The black tiny spots (sclerotia) are seen on the eipderrnis of the stalk. The presence of numerous sclerotia give charcoal like appezdnce. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>'['he plants inay be infected at any stage of growth in rainy season. The symptom appears at the lower nodes and may remain confined at one or two internodes only. The inner tissues also get mfe'cted in severe cases. The infected tissues are at first soft but later on they turn into dry mass of shredded fibres. The plants may topple down at this stage. In soine cases the infection (light to dark brown rotting) may spread rapidly throughout the leaf sheath and cause withering of leaf sheath and leaf under favourable ei~vironmental conditions. The stalks and ears may also be affected which emit an offensive dour.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Spray with 0.2% copper fungicide or 0.25% streptocycline ii) Rogue out affected plrants and destroy.</p><p>iii) Spraying of the mixture solution containing 50g of Agrimycin and 2.0 kg of Blitox 50 per ha also control the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.8.4">Pea 1) Powdery Mildew</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Erysiphe yolygoni E. pisi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease first appears on the leaves and then on the, other green parts of the pl-ant. The characteristic symptoms are the formatioil of white floury patches on both sides of the leaves and also on the tendrils, slerns and pods. In advanced stages, the entire plant surface may be covered with white powder like mass. The superficial mass consists of mycelium and spores of the fungus. Later on black dots may appear late in the season when the crop reaches maturity. The pod and grain formation is adversely affected.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Spray Sulfex (0.25%) or Elosat (0.5%) or niovit (0.5%), Midex (0.2%), Milstem (0.2%). Cosan (0.2%), Morocide (0.1%). Karathane (0.2%), Hexasul or any of the wettable sulfur at the rate of 3 flitre of water. Give first spray after appearance of the disease in the crop. Second spray should be given after 14 days of first spray. Repeat spraying only if needed.</p><p>ii) Avoid late planting iii) After harvest collect and destroy the plant debris. iv) Resistant varieties like T-10, T-56, P-185, P-388, P-6583 and P. 6587 may be grown.</p><p>2) , Rust</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Uromyces fubue and U. pisi</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>All the green part.? of the plant are affected. The earliest symptoms of the disease are the production of yellow spots (aecia) in round or elongated clusters. The uredo pustules develop on both surfaces of the leaf as well as on the other parts inform of powdery, light brown appedrdnce. The teleuto sorus or pustules develop in brown or almost black in colour. The stem cf the plant becomes malformed and the affected plant dries out. iii) Affected pl-mt debris should be collected and burnt after harvest. iv) Spraying with Bayleton (0.05%) and Calixln (0.2%) has shown effective in controlling the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ 6</head><p>i) Name the causal organisn~s of powdery 11llldew of pea.</p><p>ii) Mention fungicidal conlrol of powdery ~nildews.</p><p>iii) Meiltion two varieties of pea resistant to powdery llli]&amp;w. iv) Name tlle iilcitant or pea rust.</p><p>v) Give typical syniptoms of pea rust. . </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.8.5">Pigeon Pea</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>' n ~e chief symptom is the developi~ient of brown to dark brown lesions on the stems near tile soil surface. These lesioris rapidly girdle the whole stem and as a result of this tlle plants start drying. 'l'he symptoms of Ulis disease can be separated from the wilt by examining the roots which remain healthy in this case. The rot affected plants camlot he uprooted easily hut break at the affected sten] position whereas wilt affected plailts are easily uprtmtcd.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>(jrow resisbailt varieties and crop rotation at least l i ~r 3 years.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>3) Sterility mosaic</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Sterility mosaic virus</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I Symptoms</head><p>The leaves become pale yellow in colour and shorter in size. The affected plants are stunted in growth and branch profusely. In case of mild infection the plants may bear flowers *and fmits but in case of severe infection plants remain completely sterile and do not bear flowers and fruits. Sometimes only a few branches in the plant are affected while other parts remain healthy. The disease is transmitted by the criophyid mite from plant to plant.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ 7 I )</head><p>N,iinc the causdl dfeiit of pigeon pea wilt.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>11)</head><p>L,Is~ the conirol measures of plgeon pea wilt. I l i ) Give the chi~racteristlc synlptomnq of slein rot ok pmgeomi pea. iv) Mhat are Ule symptoms of sterility nlosaic disease of pigeon pea.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control i) Grow resistant varieties</head><p>ii) Spray 0.1% Metasystox for controlling mites. Spraying should be started after the tkst appearance of the disease.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.8.6">Tomato and Potato 1 ) Late blight</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Phytophthora infestuns</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease can attack any ground part of the plant at any stage of the crop growth. Water soaked brown to purple black lesions develop at any pornt on leaflet, rachis, petiole, stem or leaf. These lesions advance rapidly to cause a severe blight under warm and humid conditions. In times of low humidity, the lesion growth is checked. On the lower side of the leaves, white fructification of the fungus appears at the joining point of pale and purple areas. On potato tubers brownish spots and on tomato fruits, dark olivaceous, greasy-appearing spots are fumed. These may enlarge to cover the entire fruit. In very moist weather, a white weft of fungus growth develops on the invaded areads.</p><p>The fungus survives on other host plants and on the potato refuse. The fmgus also liveb in soil. Potato and tomato both are infected at the same time.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Use resistant cultivars of Potato-Kufri Jyoti, Kufri-Navtal Kufri Surya mukhi etc.</p><p>ii) Spray Zineb @ 2 flitre water just after the appearance of the disease. Repeat spraying at 8-1 0 days if needed.</p><p>iii) Destroy the infected plant or plant parts .and debris by burying under the soil.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>2) Earlyhlight</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Alternariu solani (Ell. &amp; Mart.) Jones and Grout.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The chief symptoms of the disease appear on the leaves as circular to angular, dark brown to black spots. The concentric ~g e s often form leathery necrotic tissue. Usually a narrow chlorotic zone around the necrotic spots fades into normal green. The infected leaves witber, droop and drop off. The stems and fruits ate also affected. On the stem dark spots appear at any point and it leads to collar rot. In case of fruit infection, the leslons start at the stem end as dark black or brown sunken spots and concenmc rings on potato tubers.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>The lesions become leathery in consistency.</head><p>The fungus re-viable in the dry infected leaves for more than a year. The fungus is carried on plant debris and seed material.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Spray Indophil M-45 or Indolphil Z-78 @ 2 ghitre water or Captan @ 3 g/litre water or Ziram @ 2gAitre at 7-10 days interval. The spraying should be started two months aftGplanting.</p><p>ii) Seeds/tubers should be disinfected with Captan @ 2gkg of seed before sowing.</p><p>SAQ 8 i) Name the disease 'and pathogen known for famous Irish fanine.</p><p>ii) Where the late blight pathogen survives.</p><p>iii) Name two potato varietlcs resistant to late blight.</p><p>iv) Give characteristic symptom of early blight on potato tubers.</p><p>v) Give the chemical cvntrol lneasures for early blight.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.8.7">Rapeseed and Mustard 1) Alternaria blight</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause Alternaria brassicae, A. brc~ssicicola</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Disease appears as small light brown lesions on catyledons and hypocotyl which later on turns to black coloured due to appearance of spore masses which ack as source of secondary infection in the season. On the leaves lesion varies in size from 1-20 mm. In some brassica species formation of concentric rings in the lesions and a zone of yellow halo around the lesions is very prominent. Several lesions on the leaves fuse to cause blighting and defoliation under humtd weather.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Growing resistant varieties like YSPB-24.   ii) Sowing of healtby and bold seeds from disease free plots.</p><p>iii) Spraying Indophil M-45 or Difoltan or Duter at the rate of 2gAitre of water at 10 days interval with the appearance of the disease. iv) Collect and destroy the affected plant parts after harvesting of the crop.</p><p>2) White rust</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Albugo candida</p><formula xml:id="formula_2">I Symptoms</formula><p>Prominent white or cream yellow scattered pustules appear on the under surface of the leaves. These pustules are raised blisters found on the leaves, stem and floral parts. These blisters brust and liberate a white powder. Floral parts are much deformed. The flowers get malformed (hypertrophied) and become sterile. The petals become green and stamem are transformed into leaf like structures which become thick and club shaped. All parts of plants except roots are attacked by this pathogen.</p><p>The dsease becomes more serious if it occurs along with the downy mildew.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) All crop refuse should be destroyed carefully after harvest.</p><p>ii) Follow crop rotation with noncruciferous crops.</p><p>iii) Give two to three sprayings with 0.3% Blitox-50 or Indolphil Z-78 or Difolstan @ 2gAitre of water as soon as symptoms appeared.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ 9</head><p>I ) What are the charactenstic symptoms of Alternana blight of rapeseed and mustard.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>11)</head><p>Narnc: causal orga~ism of white rust ot crucifers.</p><p>11i) Give the characteristic symptoms 01 white rust of crucifers,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.8.8">Cotton</head><p>1) Verticillium wilt</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Verticillium alboatrum.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>Plants of all stages of growth are affected but the symptoms appear mostly at blossoming time following rainy weather. The cotyledons of seedlings are yellowed and plants may be stunted at all stages of growth. The typical symptom is the mottled appearance of leaves with yellow areas developing between the veins and on the margins. The infected leaves curl and shed. Longitudinally cut stems from close to the soil surface exhibit a slight brownish discolouration of the woody stem, which is usually more evenly distributed through the stem centre and lighter brown than the discolouration caused by Fusarium wilt. Infected plants, however, shed all their leaves except young immature ones and many of their bolls. Bolls retained on the infected plants may open prematurely, producing poor quality fiber.</p><p>The fungus survives as micro sclerotia o r dark resting hyphae in the soil or infected residue.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control i) Grow resistant varieties like 'Sujata'</head><p>ii) Treat seeds with captan or Thiram @ 2.5 gkg seed or Bavistin (@ 2.0g kg seed).</p><p>iii) Rotate cotton with non susceptible crops </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The disease attacks all the above ground plant parts at all stages of plants gowth. The earliest symptom of the disease is seen as green, round water soaked spots of different sizes on the under surfaces of the cotyledons. The disease spreads to new leaves formed and the seedlings may ultimately collapse and die. The lesions on leaves are angular and water soaked, turning brown to black, delimited by the small veinlets of the leaves. Sometimes large areas are formed by coalescing a number of spots leading to death and shedding of leaves.</p><p>The lesions on the stems and petioles are dark brown to sooty black, elongated and sunken. The affected stem show cracks and gummosis .and are easily broken by wind or there may be girdling or death of the affected organs.</p><p>The lesions on bolls or fruits are small, round and water soaked with slightly raised centres that become sunken with the maturity of the bolls. Young infected bolls fall down prematurely. In the affected areas large amount of bacterial slime are exuded which form a dry film on the lesions. The lesions on the bolls may coalesce as infection extends through ovary wall.tissues, where the lint may be damaged and destroyed.</p><p>The bacterium over winters on the seed or on plant debris in the soil. Bacterium is both externally and internally seed borne also.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Control</head><p>i) Treat the acid delinted seeds with Ilhuam or Captan @ 2.5 g/kg of seed.</p><p>ii) Soak seed in 10 litres of water containing 0.5 gm of Streptocyclin or 15 gm of Agromyciri-100 and 10 gm of CaptainIAgallol or 5 gm of AretaflatBsan for 6-8 hours. One gram of succinic acid may be added in the 10 litre mixture solution of fungicide and antibiotic to promote good crop establishment and better early crops.</p><p>iii) Spray the crop with copper oxychloride (FytoladBlitox-50) @ 2.5-3 @itre of water or Agrimycin 100 @ 25ppm at 15 days interval after 45 days of sowing. About three sprayings will be needed.</p><p>iv) Collect and destroy plant debris after harvest v) Grow resistant varieties recommended into a particular area.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ 10</head><p>i) Give Ule characteristic symptoms of verticillium wilt of cotton.</p><p>ii) What is the mode of perpetuation of vertlcillium wilt pathogen of cotton'! iii) List co~ltrol measures for verticilliuln wilt of cotton.</p><p>iv) Name tlle causal organism of angular leaf spot of cotton.</p><p>v) What is tlle mode of survival of bacterial blight pathogen of cotton?</p><p>13.8.9 Sugarcane 1) Red rot</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head><p>Colletotriclzum fulcaturn (= Glornerella Cingulutu)</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>This is the most destructive disease of sugarcane. The symptom on leaf consists of small elliptical blood red spots on midribs that quickly elongate and coalesce into lesions that may extend the entire length of the leaf. These lesions later become dark brown with light brown straw coloured centre. Under humid conditions numerous black dot like acervuli develop in the central discoloured portions. If the diseased cane is split open, the pith inside is found reddened. Characteristic bands of clear white areas run transversely across the full breadth of the reddened pith. The diseased tissues emit a typical alcoholic odour. The juice of the affected stalks gives a sour alcoholic smell. In very advanced stage of the disease, the red colour may be replaced by brown and white bands.</p><p>The disease is carried over year after year by means of diseased seed setts, infected plant debris and its spores which remain lying in the fields after harvest of the infected crops. vii) Long crop rotation should be followed</p><p>.r% viii) Keep the crops free from borer and other insect infections as their injury spots serve the entry p i n t for red rot infection.</p><p>ix) Maintain proper sbil moisture in the field x) Harvest the susceptible cultivars before they have passed the peak of maturity.</p><p>2) Smut of sugarcane</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Cause</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Ustilago scitminae</head></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Symptoms</head><p>The typical symptom is the production of a long whip llke black structure at the apex of the stalk. The smut powder on this whip like out growth is covered by a thm white, silvery membrane. The membrane soon ruptures and flakes off exposing dense black powdery dust of spores. Easily recognizable, this unbranched appendage like structkue is variable in length from a few centimetres to a metre or more in length. Small raised galls, also enclosed in a membranous covering, may develop on the young leaves and rupture to expose black masses of chalamydospores. The affected plants have usually a slender and thin canes. These culms are taller and stand distinctly higher than rest of the crop.</p><p>The disease is pnrnarily transmitted through diseased cane setts. Secondary infection of standing canes occur through wind borne spores blown from the smutted whip or ratoon of smutted canes.</p><p>Control i) Remove smutted whips gently by covering them with a closely woven drill bag.</p><p>Then the entire clump may be dug and burnt.</p><p>ii) Use only smut free canes for planting. Never collect canes from the smutted clumps.</p><p>iii) No ratoon should be kept in the diseased fields. iii) Describe the typical syinptoins of urhip smut of sug.arcane.</p><p>iv) What if the mode of secondary irlfection in sugarcane smut.</p><p>v) Name the varieties of sugarcane resistant lo whip smut.</p><p>13.9 SUMMARY 1 This unit introduces the concept of plant diseases and discuss the type of pathogens,</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I</head><p>causing the diseases in crop plants. Considering the perpetuation and spread of the pathogen/disease these are classified as seed, soil and air-borne disease. The most famous epiphytotics are caused by the air-borne diseases including irish femine (late blight of potato), Bengal fernine (Brown leaf spot of rice), coffee rust and wheat rusts. This is due to the fast spread of disease and the polycyclic nature of all these diseases. Fungicides may prove very helpful, if the application is timely and the adequate type of fungicide is chosen against specific disease. The judicial use of fungicides along with the available cultural practices and resistant varieties are the components of integrated disease management strategy. For this the diagnosis of crop diseases is very essential. understanding of syrnptomatology and disease cycle helps in correct diagnosis and management of crop diseases.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.10">KEY WORDS</head><note type="other">Plant Disease Epiphytotic Fungicides Host Infection Inoc~lum Symptoms Virulence Disease cycle Dissemination Hypertrophy</note><p>: Malfunctioning of host cells as a result of continuous imtation by pathogenic agent and heads to development of symptoms.</p><p>: Widespread and destructive outbreak of a plant disease.</p><p>: A compound toxic to fungi.</p><p>: A plant that is invaded by a pathogen to obtain the nutrition.</p><p>: Establishment of a pathogen within a host plant.</p><p>: The propagules of pathogen that can cause infection.</p><p>: External and internal reactions or alterations of a plant as a result of a disease.</p><p>: The degree of pathogenicity of a pathogen.</p><p>: The chain of events involved in disease development including the stages of development of pathogen and the effect of the disease on host.</p><p>: Dispersal of inoculurn from its source to he'althy plants.</p><p>: Excessive growth due to increase in size of cells.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="13.10">ANSWERS TO</head><note type="other">SAQs SAQ 1 Crop Diseases</note><p>i) Any disturbance of a plant that interfers with its normal structure, function and economic value is known as plant disease. iii) Infectious disease are caused by the continuous irritation to host caused by pathogenic microorganisms whereas the noninfections diseases are result of either deficiency or nutrients in soil or extreme in environmental conditions. iv) Endemic diseaseis defined as the disease more or less constantly present from year to year in moderately to severe form in a particular area. v) Any infectious agent which has potential to cause disease-rmd carried on, in or with the seed is termed as seed-borne pathogen vi) In soil-borne diseases pathogen persists on the crop debris and soil.</p><p>vii) The pathogen in the soil cannot spread as fast as air-borne inoculum because of this the spread of soil-borne disease is also slower. iii) Systemic fungicides acts by entering into the system of plant whereas the nonsystemic fungicides do not enter in the plant system but protecting ~t from infection from outside.  vi) The uredo pustules are oval, lemon yellow in colour and arranged in rows as long streak on leaf, leaf sheath, stalks and glumes are also infected by stripe rust.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ 5</head><p>ii) Brown spindle shaped lesions appear on leaf and leaf sheath. The lesions are eye shaped with grey or dark brown margins. Neck infection result in dropping of panicle and breaking of panicles.</p><p>iii) The typical symptoms is the development of innumerable dark brown, elleptical spots on the leaves, stem and glumes.  ii) Spray Calixin (@ 0.15%) or Sulfex (0.25%) or any weltable sulphur compound (@ 3gA.water). First spray at appearance of disease, aiid spray is given after 14 days aid spraying is repeated only if needed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>I</head><p>iii) a-T-56, and b-P-6587. iv) Urorn\lces.fubue and Vrornyces pisi. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ 9</head><p>i) Disease appears as small light brown lesions on cotyledons or hypocotyl which later twins black due to spore mass, which act as source of secondary infection in the season. In some brassica sps formation of concentric rings and a zone of yellow halo around the lesions is very prominenl.</p><p>ii) A lbugo clmdida. ii) a) hesitant varieties should be grown, b) seed treatment with Thirarn (@ 0.25%) or Bavistin (0.2%), and c) crop rotation with nonsuscept~ble crops.</p><p>iii) Xanthomonas axonopodispv. Mulvucearum.</p><p>v) The bacterium over winters on seed, crop debris and soil.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>SAQ '11</head><p>i) On leaf disease appears as small elliptical red spots on midrib, at later stages which covers entire length of leaf and turned dark brown colourcd. Pith of diseased cane found redened and the diseased tissues emit typical alcoholic odour.</p><p>ii) a) Select only healthy sugarcane setts, b) do not use cane from infected fields, c) Rouge out and burn diseased canes, d) Do not ratoon the diseased crop, and e) Long crop rotation should be followed.</p><p>iii) The typical symptom of this disease is production of long whip like black structure at the apex of stalk.</p><p>iv) Secondary infection of standing canes occur through the wind borne spores blown from the smutted whip or ratoon of smutted canes.  </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_1"><head>1)</head><label></label><figDesc>Sulpher fungicide: a) Organic 'S' e.g. Thirarn, Zineb, Maneb, Ziram, Vapam, Ferbam b) Inorganic's' e.g. Lime 'S', Wettable 'S', Powder 'S'. 2) Copper fungicide: Bordeaux mixture, Burgundy mixture, fixed basic copper like coper-oxychloride, cuprous-mercurial: e.g. Phenyl mercury acetate, Methoxy ethyl mercury chloride 4) Quinone: Chloranil and dichlone 5) Heterocyclic Nitrogenous: Captan, folpit 6) Oxathiins: Carboxin, Oxycarboxin 7) Benzimidazoles: Benomyl, MBC, TBZ 8) Others: PCNB, Dodine, Tin Compounds and Antibiotics etc.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_2"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>characters of a good fungicide. iii) Differentiate between the systemic and non-systemic fungicides. iv) List the protectant, theruptant and eradient fungicides.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_4"><head>2)</head><label></label><figDesc>Brown spot or Helminthosporiose or Sesame leaf blight or NaiYake Cause Cochliobolus rniyuheunus (Ito &amp; Kur.) Drech ex Dast. (Helrninthosporiut oqaue Breda de Ham.)</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_5"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>the pathogen of nce fewer disease. ii) Mention the characteristic symptoins of blast disease of rice. iii) Mention typical symptoms of sesame l e d blight of rice. iv) Name two resistant varieties of rice against sheath blight, v) What is Kresek phase in Bacterial 1e. d blight of ricc. vi) Name the vector of Rice Tungro Virus. vii) Name two rice varieties resistant to Tutlgro disease. small water soaked linear to irregular shaped lesions are formed 011 the leaf blade which may extend into l e d sheath. Lesions are light olivaceous to brown coloured which finally turned black to straw coloured as the tissues dries up. In Southern corn blight lesions are typically elliptical first but become elongaled in later stages, with reddish yellow colour with dark brown borders. The number of lesions are more as compared to Northern corn blight. Control i) Use of resistant varieties i.e. Ganga saphed.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_6"><head>Control 1 )</head><label>1</label><figDesc>Avoid water stress after flowering of the plant. 2) Destroys the crop debris and adopt crop rotation at least for 3 years 3) Bacterial Stalk Rot Cause ,7-..+-.+-..---.--...-,. /'-i ..-</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_7"><head>Controli)</head><label></label><figDesc>Spray the top with Indophil M 4 5 at the rate of 2 g per litre of water. Two to three sprays will be sufficient and should be given at 15-20 days interval.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_8"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>(!;(lr-i~vr~ O . V ~~S ~~O ~I ~~! I I I , ; sp, ~, ~C / I ( ~I I Symptoms 'l?~c chiei'synlploni of the. discusi: is the wilting of seedlings and adult plants as if they have sul~fe~cd fro111 ;valcr shortage. 'ille wilting plants show gradual, sometimes sudden. yellowing, i~:i:hc~-i~?g and dsyiiy o f I c ~t v ~s followed by drying of the entire plant cw some of. its branchc.;. 'I'he 1'001s I~;t:~~olnc thrh hrtnl.y.la iuld devoid of rootlets and s h o ~ a blxk slrcak below tile bark. Palcl~cs of discasel! pianls art. scarrered throughout the field,, Control i i I:o!lon~ 111sc'c !o 1'our ~C ; U S crop rotatioil ii) (;row mixed i.~-oj&gt; (:I'Jo\r';~r illlil Arhar in Ilcavy inlkslctl soil iii) Collecl ; I I I ~ bur11 tile pla~it Jebris aLLcr harvest ivj Grow disease resistant v:~riel~cs 2) Stem rot Cause PI~~tu~~hthui-u dreschlerrl vclr. cuji111i.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_9"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>2) Bacterial blightThis also known as black arm or angular leaf spot of cotton Cause Xanthomonas axonopodis pv. mlvacearum</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_10"><head>Controli)</head><label></label><figDesc>Select only healthy sugarcane setts. Do not use canes for seed if slight red colour is visible at the cut ends.ii) As far as possible do not use the canes from the fields affected with the red rot dsease iii) Dip the setts in 0.25 per cent solution of Agallol or Aretan for five minutes before planting. Hot water treatment of setts is very effective iv) Grow resistant varieties recommended for the particular area.v) Rogue out and burn the diseased canes. Uproot the entire clump showing diseased canes or suspected for disease symptoms.vi) Do not ratoon the dseased crop.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_11"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>iv) Volunteer or self sown cane plants should be roughed out during season of cropping of other plants. v) Treat setts before planting with the solution of Agallol or Aretan (0.25%) for 5 minutes.vi) Growing specially cared nursery, developed from heat treated setts, multiplying further for seed canes is recommended.vii) Grow smut resistant varieties like CO440, 11 18,114s: BO 11, 22.24 and CS I the characteristic syniptonis or' red rot 01 sugarcane, ii) List cultural practices used to conmol red rot of sugarcane.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_12"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>ii) a) Increased metabolism, b) Blockage in transportation of food, mineral nutrients and water, c) Killing or disturbance in metabolism due to toxins secreted by pathogen, and d) Consumption of host cells on contact.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_13"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>blight of cereals. xi) Air-borne pathogens produce enormous spores, completes their life cycle quickly so that they produce secondary inoculum very quickly to crop within same season. x) a) Irish femine (Phytophthora infestance) Ireland, b) Bengal femine (Helminthosporium oryule) India, c) Coffee rust (Helmeliu vestrutix) Ceylon, d) Downy mildew of Grape (Endotheaparusitica) France, and e) Southern maize leaf blight (Helminthosporium muydis) USA. SAQ 3 i) Any chemical substance which has ability to prevent damage caused by fungi to growing crops and their products, ii) a) High field performance, b) Low phytotoxicity, c) Stability in storage, d) Stability after dilution to spray strength, and e) Low toxicity to human beings and cattles.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_14"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>iv) a) Protectant fungicides: Zineb, Blitox-SO, Mancozeb, b) Therapeutant fungicides: Lime sulpher, Dodine Organo murcurial fungicides, and . c) Eradicants: Oxathin, Wnon fungicides, Aureobungin. SAQ 4 i) Alternaria triticina and Drechslera sorokiniana.ii) a) Leaf rust -Puccinia reconditu, b) Stripe rust -Puccinia striiformis, and c) Stem rust -Pucciniu gruminis rritici. iii) Karnal bunt of wheat is caused by Neovossiu indicu and pathogen survives in seed and soil. iv) Earcockle of wheat is caused by a nematode, Anguinu tritici. V) a) Seed trktment with Vitavex (@ 2-2.5 /kg seed), b) Roughtout the infected earheads at the time of ear-emergence, c) Use of resistant varieties, and d) Solar heat treatment of seeds.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_15"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>iv) a) Saket-I, and b) Krishna. v) This is most destructive phase of the disease and is result of early systemic infection. The leaves roll completely, droop and turn yellow and grey, withering of tillers and complete killing of affect shoots occur in severe infection. vi) Nymph and adult rice green leaf hopper (Nephotettix i~lrpicticeps). vii) a) Rama, and b) Vijaya.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_17"><head>Iv)</head><label></label><figDesc>Production of yellow spots (decid) in round or elongated cluslers, the stem of plants becomes malformed and the affected plants dries out. SAQ 7 i) Fusaritlrn oxj1sporurnfisp. udurn. ii) a) Crop rotatioli up to 3 years, b) Mixed cropping of Jowar (Sorghum vulgaris), c) Collect and burn crop debris after harvest, and d) Grow resistant varieties. iii) Developinent of brown to dark brown lesions on the stem near soil surface, later 011 Uiese lesions rapidly girdle the stem ultimately plants start drying. iv) The leaves become pale yellow and shorter in size, plants become stunled and t profusely branched, in case of severe infection plant become completely sterile and do not bear flowers and fruils. fernine was due to late blight of potato caused by Plz~~tophthorrr infestance. I ii) The pathogen survives on other host plants, infected tubers, crop debris and soil i as well. iii) a) Kufri Jyoti, and b) Kufri Surya mukhi. iv) Disease appear as circular toangular, &amp;ark brown to black spots with concentric rings forming leathery necrotic tissues. v) a) Seed/tuber treatment with Captan (0.2%) before sowing, and b) Spray Indophil M-45 (2gA.water) at 7-10 days interval, two months after planting.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_18"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>iii) a) White or cream yellow scattered pustules as raised blisters under surFace of laves, stem and floral b) Dcfor~nation of floral parts, c) Flowers get malformed (hypertrophied) and become sterile, and d) Petals become green, stamens become thick aid club shaped. SAQ 10 i) Yellowing of cotyledons, stunted growth of plant, motteling and curling of leaves and shedding of leaves. The pathogen survives as microsclerotia or dark resting hyphae in the soil or crop residue.</figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_20"><head>I</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc></figure>
		</body>
		<back>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
