<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Towards Sustainable Growth Opportunities State Profile West Bengal</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher/>
				<availability status="unknown"><licence/></availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">West Bangal State Presnetation and Economy Growth Report | IBEF</orgName>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Towards Sustainable Growth Opportunities State Profile West Bengal</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<imprint>
							<date/>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">C47C5FC5E83AEB742C47FDD0D98EAF91</idno>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2025-12-19T09:47+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Growth and Linkages in the Indian Food Processing Sector:</head><p>The Indian food-processing sector has witnessed remarkable growth, during the last 9 years ending 2023-24, Food Processing Industries sector has been growing at an Average Annual Growth Rate (AAGR) of around 6.55% as compared to around 6.06% in manufacturing at 2011-12 prices. The sector constituted as much as 7.93% share of FPI in the manufacturing sector in 2023-2024. The sector is one of the largest employment providers in the organized manufacturing sector with 12.91% employment in the total registered/organized sector. This highlights its competitiveness and capacity to cater to global markets.</p><p>India is the world's largest producer of milk, pulses and jute and ranks as the second largest producer of rice, wheat, sugarcane, groundnut, vegetables, fruit and cotton. It is also one of the leading producers of spices, fish, poultry, livestock and plantation crops. This abundant raw material base offers immense potential for value addition and export. Notably, India reported the processed food exports amounted to USD 10.09 billion in 2024-2025 with significant shares in processed vegetables and fruits, pulses, cereal preparations etc. Further, the sector has attracted 7.21 billion FDI inflow in the last one-decade ending 2024-25. Recognizing the sector's significance, the Ministry of Food Processing Industries has extended support and incentives for creation of modern infrastructure with efficient supply chain management, creation of employment opportunities, reducing post-harvest losses, increasing the processing level and enhancing export of processed foods.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Agricultural Strength and Economic Advantages of West Bengal:</head><p>The food processing sector plays a crucial role in establishing strong linkages between the industry and the agriculture sector. It facilitates collaboration and integration, benefitting both sectors and boosting the overall agricultural value chain. West Bengal, is India's sixth largest state in terms of economic size, has a projected Gross State Domestic Product (GSDP) of 18.8 trillion (US$ 227.05 billion) in 2024-25. The average annual GSDP is estimated to increase at 10.5% from 2023-24BE 1 . Moreover, West Bengal benefits from its strategic location, with easy access to both domestic and international markets. The State's proximity to major ports and transportation networks facilitates the smooth export of processed food products. The Single Desk Portal "Silpasathi" in West Bengal is a dedicated Single Window Clearance (SWC) system that streamlines the process of doing business.</p><p>West Bengal has emerged as a prominent player in the food processing and export sector. The State is largest producer status in various vegetables and fruits, such as, Brinjal, Cabbage, Cauliflower, Cucumber, Pineapple etc 2 . West Bengal holds their markable position of being the second-highest producer of fish 3 , highlighting its prominent role and dominance in the seafood industry. The state showcases abundant opportunities with 11 food and allied geographical indicator tags 4 . This agricultural prominence creates a strong base for food processing enterprises to tap into. The state has witnessed the highest bank credit flow to Micro, Small, and Medium Enterprises (MSMEs) in recent years, reflecting a supportive business ecosystem. The state has received assistance/incentives from the Ministry of Food Processing Industries under its flagship scheme, such as, Pradhan Mantri Formalisation Micro Food Processing Enterprises.</p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Overview</head><p>West Bengal, located in the eastern part of India, is a state that possesses a distinctive charm. Situated alongside the Bay of Bengal, it shares borders with Bangladesh to the east, as well as Nepal, Bhutan, Odisha, Jharkhand, Bihar, Sikkim, and Assam within India. West Bengal occupies a significant position on both national and international trade routes, linking to countries, such as, China, Bangladesh, Singapore, New Zealand, Australia, Indonesia, Malaysia, and other coastal states. In addition to its strategic location, West Bengal is a melting pot of diverse languages, religions, customs, traditions, cuisines, and lifestyles, adding to the cultural richness of India. Bordered by the majestic Himalayan ranges in the north and the vastness of the sea in the south, the state possesses all the necessary ingredients for prosperity. While predominantly an agrarian state, West Bengal also capitalizes on its economic potential. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">Advantage West Bengal</head><p> The second largest metro rail network in the country. <ref type="bibr">15</ref>  Robust infrastructure with excellent rail and road network.</p><p> Silpasathi: Single window portal for business approvals with Time bound and Transparent services. <ref type="bibr">16</ref>  Strategic gateway to South-East Asia and North-East India, sharing international frontiers with Bangladesh, Nepal, and Bhutan.</p><p> Graded as an Aspirer within the Coastal cluster according to DPIIT's, LEADS 2024. 17</p><p> The second largest tea producer after Assam, known for the famous Darjeeling Tea. <ref type="bibr">18</ref>  Ranked #2 in fish production, showcasing its dominance in the seafood industry. <ref type="bibr">19</ref>  2 nd largest producer of Okra/ Ladyfinger &amp; Potato. <ref type="bibr">20</ref>  Ranked 1 st in vegetable production in India. 21 *  Ranked 1 st in production of pineapple in the country. <ref type="bibr">22</ref>  2 nd largest producer of Litchi. <ref type="bibr">23</ref>  3 rd largest producer of Bael.</p><p> Largest producer of Brinjal, Cabbage, Capsicum, Cauliflower, and Cucumber in the country. <ref type="bibr">24</ref>  Largest producer of Elephant Foot Yam, Parwal/Pointed Gourd, and Radish in the country. <ref type="bibr">25</ref>  The only state in India producing the famous Hilsha fish   </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Production Clusters</head><p>The list below showcases the Production Clusters within the state under the Pradhan Mantri Formalization of Micro Food Processing Enterprises Scheme (PMFME): </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="5.">Agricultural Marketing</head><p>The state has a dedicated department, the Agricultural Marketing Department, responsible for managing agricultural produce and its marketing. The department's primary aims are to accelerate the development of a well-functioning marketing system for agricultural products, enhance the efficiency of agricultural marketing, establish effective coordination between the Agricultural Marketing Organization and Mandi Parishad/Mandi Committees, facilitate exporters and producers, arrange exporters' conferences and seminars to encourage agricultural exports, and identify potential exportable surplus. Fruits and vegetables (F&amp;V) processing, covering the production of dehydrated and frozen F&amp;V items using techniques, such as, IQF/Blast Freezer/Spiral Freezer can produce valueadded products like Dehydrated Potato chips or flakes, Jackfruit products, leafy vegetable products. Additionally, dehydration and powdering of vegetables will produce products like potato, tomato, onion, ginger powder for soups &amp; stews.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.2.Flowers</head><p>West Bengal holds a prominent position in the field of floriculture due to its favourable agroclimatic zones, fertile soil, and round-the-year demand for flowers across religious, ceremonial, decorative, and commercial uses. </p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>6.4.Tea processing and beverages</head><p>West Bengal is one of the largest tea-producing states in India, and it produces a wide variety of teas, such as, Darjeeling tea (black tea), CTC Tea, Green Tea, White Tea, and Oolong Tea. Darjeeling Tea is highly regarded and cherished by tea connoisseurs worldwide for its exquisite taste, rich history, and the natural beauty of its place of origin.</p><p>o Diverse Processed Products: Tea leaves can be processed into various products, like -Tea Bags, Instant Tea (instant tea powder or granules), flavored Tea (infused or blended with various natural flavors, such as, fruits, herbs, or spices, to create flavored tea varieties like fruit-infused teas, herbal teas, or chai teas), tea extracts (for flavored drinks, desserts, and confectionery), tea concentrates (for making tea-based beverages like drink mixes etc.), tea-infused food products (tea-infused chocolates, ice creams, or sauces), etc. o Ready-to-Drink Tea: Brewed tea can be packaged and sold as ready-to-drink beverages, available in different flavors and formulations, such as iced tea, bottled tea, or tea-based energy drinks. o Health Benefits: Darjeeling Tea offers many health benefits and is a healthy alternative to coffee and sugar-laden energy drinks. It is known for its antioxidants and may aid in relaxation and overall well-being. When brewed, Darjeeling Tea produces a pale lemon to rich, amber-colored liquor. It has a complex and pleasing taste with a delicate flavor.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="6.5.">Meat &amp; aquaculture</head><p>West Bengal's fisheries and meat sectors offer an opportunity to tap into a growing market and cater to the rising demand for value-added fish products and a diverse range of meat-based products.</p><p>o Value-Added Fish Products: West Bengal fish production includes both inland and marine fish. The state produces 12.5% of India's famous Hilsa fish <ref type="bibr">52</ref> . Products, such as, fish cutlets, fish balls, fish pickles, prawn pickles, fish soup powder, fish wafers, and ready-to-serve fish curry in flexible pouches can be developed, catering to diverse consumer preferences. o Meat Production Potential: West Bengal stands as the largest producer of meat in the country. This highlights the significant market and demand for meat-based products within the State. o Diversified Meat Products: There are various meat-based products, including meatbased soups and stocks, sausages, deli meats, and meat-based snacks. Chicken or mutton samosas, kebabs, sausages, and meatballs are examples of popular meat snacks that can be manufactured and marketed.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="7.">State Government Initiatives and Schemes</head><p>West Bengal has always endeavoured to provide a hassle-free business environment to enable investors. To boost exports, to enhance the ease of doing exports, strengthening of export infrastructure, better framework, and enhance exportability of goods from state.</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head> WBFPIS (2021)</head><p>The West Bengal Food Processing Incentive Scheme (WBFPIS) aims to support and incentivize individual micro food processing enterprises, groups, and cooperatives to enhance their competitiveness and formalize the unorganized sector. This is primarily achieved through a credit-linked grant-in-aid of up to 40% of the total cost of plant and machinery, limited to a maximum of Rs. 10 lakh per unit, for setting up new units or upgrading existing ones Key incentives introduced by State Government of West Bengal for the industries including food processing industry under its major policies are summarized in the table below 53 : For micro/small enterprises:</p><p>• Subsidy @ Rs 1 per unit on power tariff for a period of 5 (five) years from the date of commercial production for Micro and Small Enterprises located in Zone A &amp; B* • Subsidy @ Rs 1.5 per unit on power tariff for a period of 5 (five) years for enterprises located in Zone C, D &amp; E* * Subject to ceiling of Rs 10 Lakh and 20 Lakh for Micro and small enterprises respectively For medium enterprises:</p><p>• Subsidy @ Rs 1 per unit on power tariff for a period of 5 (five) years from the date of commercial production for Micro and Small Enterprises located in Zone A &amp; B* • Subsidy @ Rs 1.5 per unit on power tariff for a period of 5 (five) years for enterprises located in Zone C, D &amp; E* *Subject to a ceiling of Rs 30 Lakh per annum</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Subsidy of energy efficiency</head><p>For micro/small enterprises:</p><p>• Reimbursement @ 50% of the cost of energy audit undertaken by a certified agency to be granted post implementation of the recommendations</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Key Initiatives</head><p>Banglashree for Micro, Small, and Medium Enterprises 2020-25 For micro/small enterprises: Subsidy @ 50 % on the cost of quality certifications and patent registration for micro or small enterprises subject to a maximum of Rs 5.00 lakh each For medium enterprises: Subsidy @ 50 % on the cost of patent registration for medium enterprises subject to a maximum of Rs 5.00 lakh</p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="8.">Regulatory Framework: Registration/NoCs/ Licenses</head><p>The table below represents the indicative information regarding Regulatory Mechanism available in the State of West Bengal.    </p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head>Table 1 : West Bengal Overview</head><label>1</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Particulars</cell><cell>Details</cell></row><row><cell>State Capital</cell><cell>Kolkata</cell></row><row><cell>Geographic Area 5</cell><cell>88,752 sq. km</cell></row><row><cell>Population (Census 2011) 6</cell><cell>91.3 million</cell></row><row><cell>Total Road Length (March, 2020) 7</cell><cell>2,85,197 km</cell></row><row><cell>Gross State Domestic Product (GSDP),</cell><cell>USD 204.11 billion(Rs17,00,93,936 lakh)</cell></row><row><cell>Current Prices, 2023-24 8</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Airport</cell><cell>2 international airports-Netaji Subhash</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Chandra Bose International Airport,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Bagdogra International Airport</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>4 domestic airports-Malda, Balurghat,</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Cooch Behar, private greenfield airport of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>India operational at Andal</cell></row><row><cell>Rail Network 9</cell><cell>4,161 km</cell></row><row><cell>Industrial Area</cell><cell>14 Industrial Parks 10</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>7 SEZs 11</cell></row><row><cell>Infrastructure 12</cell><cell>1 Inland Container Depot (ICD)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>10 Container Freight Station (CFS)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1Air Cargo Terminal</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>1 Private Freight Terminal (PFT)</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>424 Railway Goods Sheds</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>4.04lakh MT Warehouse Capacity</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>59.47 lakh MT Cold Storage Capacity</cell></row><row><cell>Installed Power 13</cell><cell>10,800.27 MW</cell></row><row><cell>Available Land 14</cell><cell>17.36 ha</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_2"><head>3. Local Food System 3.1. Indigenous Produce West</head><label></label><figDesc>Bengal, a predominantly agrarian state, holds the top position in both paddy and vegetable production within the country.26  Its abundant natural resources and favorable climatic conditions contribute to its status as a significant agricultural hub. With an ample surplus of rice, vegetables, and potatoes, West Bengal has successfully cultivated a diverse range of products like Paddy (Rice), Maize, Wheat, Mustard, Sugarcane, Tea, and Vegetables. West Bengal benefits from six agro-climatic zones that support year-round cultivation of a wide variety of agricultural crops, vegetables, and fruits. With a net-sown area of 52.85 lakh hectares, which encompasses 68% of the geographical area and 92% of arable land, the state also boasts a gross sown area of 9,974 Thousand hectares in2022-23. 27    </figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Key Production Statistics</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Table 2: Crops ('000 MT) 39 , 2023-24</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No.</cell><cell>Particulars</cell><cell>Production</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Wheat</cell><cell>593.5</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Pulses</cell><cell>433</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell>Coarse Cereals</cell><cell>2611.3</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Rice</cell><cell>15,687</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">State has received 11 Geographical Indication (GI) Tags for Food Items 28 :</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">1. Darjeeling tea</cell><cell>2. Gobindobhog rice</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">3. MaldaLaxmanbhog mango</cell><cell>4. Tulapanji rice</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">5. BardhamanSitabhog</cell><cell>6. BanglarRasogolla</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">7. MaldaFazli mango</cell><cell>8. Dallekhursani</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">9. Joynagar moa</cell><cell>10. MaldaKhirsapati (Himsagar) mango</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">11. Bardhaman Mihidana</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">3.2. Key Production Highlights</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3"> Ranked 1 aspx</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">27 https://agriwelfare.gov.in/en/StatHortEst</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">28 Intellectual Property | Registration Details of Geographical Indications -Details of GI Applications Registered as on</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">March 31, 2025.xlsx</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>29 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="3">30 http://nriwestbengal.gov.in/nri/common/agro_indus.aspx</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">31 https://dahd.gov.in/sites/default/files/2025-01/FinalBAHS2024Book14012025.pdf</cell></row><row><cell>32 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">33 https://agriwelfare.gov.in/en/StatHortEst</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>34 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>35 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>36 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">37 https://agriwelfare.gov.in/en/StatHortEst</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>38 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table><note>st in production of Pineapple in the country.29    Ranked 1 st in production of vegetables. 30 *  Largest producer of Meat. 31  4 th largest producer in Egg. 32  2 nd largest producer of Litchi/Lychee. 33  2 nd largest producer of Okra/ Ladyfinger &amp; Potato. 34  3rd largest producer of Bael. 35  3 rd largest producer of Pumpkin. 36  3 rd largest producer of Sweet Potato. 37  3 rd largest producer of Jack Fruit. 38  Valuable cash crops including maize, wheat, mustard, sugarcane, tea etc.  Primary commodities are Paddy and Maize. 26 https://nriwestbengal.gov.in/nri/common/Agriculture.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_3"><head>Table 3 :</head><label>3</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Livestock, 2023-24 40 &amp; Fisheries</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No.</cell><cell>Particulars</cell><cell>Production</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Milk (lakh tonne)</cell><cell>76.5</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Eggs (lakh nos.)</cell><cell>1,62,394.33</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell>Meat ('000 MT)</cell><cell>1293.8</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Fish (lakh MT) 41 (2022-23)</cell><cell>20.45</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Table 4: Fruits ('000 MT) 42 , 2023-24</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No.</cell><cell>Particulars</cell><cell>Production</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Banana</cell><cell>1,440.01</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Mango</cell><cell>882.27</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell>Pineapple</cell><cell>347.08</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Jackfruit</cell><cell>227.81</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">Table 5: Vegetables ('000 MT) 43 , 2022-23</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>S.No.</cell><cell>Particulars</cell><cell>Production</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Potato</cell><cell>13000</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Brinjal</cell><cell>3097.93</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell>Cabbage</cell><cell>2,393.85</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Cauliflower</cell><cell>1997.17</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_4"><head>Table 6 : Spices ('000 MT) 44 , 2023-24 S.No.</head><label>6</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell></cell><cell>Particulars</cell><cell>Production</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Ginger</cell><cell>139.54</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>Turmeric</cell><cell>53.39</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell>Garlic</cell><cell>38.62</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell>Red Chillies</cell><cell>16.35</cell></row><row><cell cols="3">39 https://www.rbi.org.in/Scripts/AnnualPublications.aspx?head=Handbook+of+Statistics+on+Indian+States</cell></row><row><cell cols="2">40 https://dahd.gov.in/sites/default/files/2025-01/FinalBAHS2024Book14012025.pdf</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">41 https://dof.gov.in/sites/default/files/2024-06/Handbook.pdf</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell cols="2">42 https://agriwelfare.gov.in/en/StatHortEst</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>43 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>44 ibid</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_5"><head>Table 7 : West Bengal Production Cluster [ODOP (Proposed)]: 45 Sl No.</head><label>7</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>District</cell><cell>Product</cell></row><row><cell>Cooch Behar</cell><cell>Tomato based products</cell></row><row><cell>Alipurduar</cell><cell>Black pepper products</cell></row><row><cell>Jalpaiguri</cell><cell>Green Chilly Products</cell></row><row><cell>Darjeeling</cell><cell>Bakery Products</cell></row><row><cell>Kalimpong</cell><cell>Dalle chilly products</cell></row><row><cell>Uttar Dinajpur</cell><cell>Pineapple</cell></row><row><cell>Dakshin Dinajpur</cell><cell>Maize based products</cell></row><row><cell>Malda</cell><cell>Mango based products</cell></row><row><cell>Murshidabad</cell><cell>Mustard products</cell></row><row><cell>Nadia</cell><cell>Banana</cell></row><row><cell>North 24 Parganas</cell><cell>Milk &amp; Milk based products</cell></row><row><cell>Hooghly</cell><cell>Potato based products</cell></row><row><cell>PurbaBardhaman</cell><cell>Rice Bran Oil</cell></row><row><cell>Paschim Bardhaman</cell><cell>Bakery and confectionery products</cell></row><row><cell>Birbhum</cell><cell>Murabba</cell></row><row><cell>Purulia</cell><cell>Bakery products</cell></row><row><cell>Bankura</cell><cell>Paddy or rice-based products</cell></row><row><cell>Jhargram</cell><cell>Peanut products</cell></row><row><cell>Paschim Medinipur</cell><cell>Milk &amp; Milk based products</cell></row><row><cell>Purba Medinipur</cell><cell>Cashew nut</cell></row><row><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Bakery and confectionery</cell></row><row><cell>South 24 Parganas</cell><cell>Moa</cell></row><row><cell>Kolkata</cell><cell>Sweetmeat</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_6"><head>Table 8 : Agricultural Markets in West Bengal S.No. Particulars Details</head><label>8</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>1.</cell><cell>Mandis 46</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_7"><head>Note -Almost all the mandis and rural markets have fish selling and primary processing centers (cleaning, cutting, fille, ice packing, and retail packing systems in place).</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>6. Potential Opportunities</cell></row><row><cell>West Bengal is one of the agriculturally rich states in India. With an overview of the state</cell></row><row><cell>profile and geographical conditions, following segments can be focused under food processing</cell></row><row><cell>in the state of West Bengal -</cell></row><row><cell>6.1</cell></row><row><cell>46 Agmarket, Directorate of Marketing &amp; Inspection (DMI), Ministry of Agriculture and Farmers Welfare</cell></row><row><cell>47 State wise list of registered FPOs details under Central Sector Scheme for Formation and Promotion of 10,000 FPOs by</cell></row><row><cell>SFAC as on 24-02-2025.pdf</cell></row><row><cell>48 Ministry of Consumer Affairs, Food &amp; Public Distribution</cell></row><row><cell>49 Annual Survey of Industries 2022-23</cell></row><row><cell>50 https://enam.gov.in/web/assest/download/eNAM_Directory_20210720.pdf</cell></row><row><cell>51 https://wbagrimarketingboard.gov.in/List%20of%20Krishak%20Bazars.html</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_8"><head>.Fruits &amp; Vegetables The</head><label></label><figDesc>state of West Bengal presents advantageous agricultural circumstances for horticultural produce, with particular emphasis on Pineapple, Litchi, Mango, Dates (Khajur), Jackfruit, and a range of vegetables including Potato, Cabbage, Carrot, Cucumber, and Okra. The esteemed "Bombai Litchi" brand holds a prestigious position in both the fresh and processed fruit sectors. Within this industry, numerous promising prospects are available, like:</figDesc><table /><note>o Pineapple and Litchi processing, including the production of pulp, juice, jams, jellies, beverages, nectar, candies, and powder. o Mango processing: West Bengal's renowned mango varieties, such as, Malda Laxman Bhog, Malda Khirsapati (Himsagar), and Malda Fazli. These varieties can be transformed into a range of products, including pulp, juice, jams, jellies, beverages, candies, and powder. o Date (Khajur) processing, West Bengal is famous to produce Kejuri gur (Khandsari extracted from dates). This gur is used in wide range of sweet dishes. Khajur Tari is a naturally fermented plant based sweet alcoholic beverage of West Bengal. It is a mild alcoholic beverage collected in a earthen pot from the sap of Khajur tree and after 8-12 hours of natural fermentation, the sugar content of the drink decreases as alcohol content of Khajur tari increases as result of natural fermentation carried out by yeasts.</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_9"><head>Innovations and Technologies for Rice Processing: Smart</head><label></label><figDesc>Dried flowers such as Hibiscus, Rose petals, and Chrysanthemum are processed into caffeine-free herbal teas known for their health benefits, antioxidant properties, and global demand in the wellness beverage sector. o Natural food colorants: Pigments derived from flowers like Marigold (yellow/orange carotenoids) and Hibiscus (deep red anthocyanins) are used as natural food color additives in juices, confectionery, bakery, and dairy products, replacing synthetic dyes. o Rose-based food products: Cultivated extensively in West Bengal, rose petals can be processed into Gulkand (rose petal jam), rose syrup, and rose water, all of which are traditional ingredients used in Indian sweets, beverages, and desserts. These have high commercial viability in both domestic and export markets. o Flower-based condiments and spice blends: Flowers like Tuberose, Rose, and Jasmine are also used in the production of floral salts, spice blends, and flavoured sugars, catering to niche gourmet markets. o Dehydrated edible flowers: Solar and freeze-drying technologies are used to produce dehydrated edible flowers for use as cake garnishes, salad toppings, and decorative ingredients in high-end confectionery.</figDesc><table><row><cell>Rice Milling</cell></row><row><cell>(computerized control systems, automated milling processes, and sensor-based sorting</cell></row><row><cell>techniques, Precision Sorting and Grading (separation of rice grains based on size,</cell></row><row><cell>shape, and color, ensuring consistency and uniformity in the final product), Fortification</cell></row><row><cell>and Value Addition (to enhance the nutritional value of rice, , such as, adding vitamins,</cell></row><row><cell>minerals, or fiber during processing), Solar Drying and Energy Efficiency (reduces</cell></row><row><cell>energy consumption, enhances product quality, and promotes sustainable and eco-</cell></row><row><cell>friendly processing practices.</cell></row></table><note>The state is a leading producer of both traditional and modern flower varieties including Marigold, Tuberose (Rajnigandha), Rose, Gladiolus, Chrysanthemum, and Gerbera, with significant cultivation in districts like Nadia, North &amp; South 24 Parganas, Hooghly, Howrah, and Purba Medinipur. Within this growing industry, numerous processing and value-addition prospects are available, such as:o Essential oil extraction and distillation: Fragrant flowers like Tuberose, Rose, and Jasmine. These essential oils serve the cosmetic, aromatherapy, and perfumery industries. West Bengal's Tuberose oil is particularly valued for its rich fragrance. o Edible flower extracts and infusions: Flowers like Rose, Hibiscus, and Jasmine are processed into natural flavouring agents, floral syrups, and infused waters, which are widely used in gourmet culinary products, beverages, and desserts.o Floral teas and herbal infusions:6.3.CerealsWest Bengal is recognized as the 2 nd largest producer of high-quality rice in India. The state is famous for its "Gobindobhog" rice and "Tulaipanji" rice varieties. Opportunities in rice and paddy processing:oRice Milling and Processing: Setting up modern rice mills equipped with advanced technology for milling, sorting, grading, and packaging. o Rice Bran Oil Extraction: Opportunity to produce a nutritious and versatile cooking oil. o Rice Flour and Rice-based Products: Processing rice into rice flour and producing rice-based products like rice noodles, rice flakes, rice snacks, and instant rice mixes, rice sheets, syrups, vinegar, hulls, bran, brown rice, whole kernel milled rice, brokens, rice cakes, and more. Additionally, rice can be used to prepare ready-to-eat or ready-tocook/ready-to-eat noodles, and various cuisines like sushi. o Rice Husk Utilization: Innovations in utilizing rice husk, a by-product of rice milling, can lead to the development of value-added products, such as rice husk ash, briquettes, insulation materials, and eco-friendly packaging solutions. o Latest</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_10"><head></head><label></label><figDesc>The West Bengal State Government has implemented numerous reforms to create a conducive and investor-friendly business environment for those interested in establishing their businesses within the state. The table below highlights some of the key initiatives undertaken by the State Government:West Bengal is a comprehensive One-Stop-Shop for all investment &amp; business-related information and services, providing unified access to multiple regulatory authorities and facilitating electronic payments for all clearances. It helps in maintaining time-bound delivery of services, promoting transparency and facilitate various incentives available to the businesses. It has brought much needed reforms to promote Ease of Doing Business in the State.(silpasathi.wb.gov.in)   </figDesc><table><row><cell> The Single Desk Portal "Silpasathi''</cell></row></table><note> Central Industrial Land Bank PortalIndustrial parks serve as a one-stop repository of all infrastructure-related information, such as connectivity, infra, natural resources and terrain, plot-level information on vacant plots, and contact details. (iis.ncog.gov.in/parks/login1)  Export Promotion Policy</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_11"><head>Table 9 : Key initiatives by the State government</head><label>9</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Key Initiatives</cell><cell>Banglashree for Micro, Small, and Medium Enterprises</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>2020-25</cell></row><row><cell>Interest subsidy</cell><cell>For micro/small enterprises:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Micro &amp; Small Enterprises for a period of 5 (five) years from</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>the date of disbursement of the loan is as follows:</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>a) Zone A &amp; B: Subsidy @ 55 % on the interest liability</cell></row></table><note>b) Zone C, D &amp; E: Subsidy @ 70 % on the interest liability For medium enterprises: 53 Department of Micro, Small and Medium Enterprises and Textiles, Government of West Bengal</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_13"><head>Table 10 : Regulatory mechanism for starting operations</head><label>10</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="3">S.No. Name of Service</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Authority/ Agency/ Office/</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Department</cell><cell>officer</cell><cell>granting</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>approval</cell></row><row><cell>1.</cell><cell cols="4">Registration under FSSAI Act,2006,</cell><cell cols="2">FSSAI, Government of India Health &amp;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">regulation 2011</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Family Welfare Department, &amp; Food</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Safety</cell></row><row><cell>2.</cell><cell>License</cell><cell>under</cell><cell>FSSAI</cell><cell>Act,2006,</cell><cell cols="2">FSSAI, Government of India Health &amp;</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="2">regulation 2011</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Family Welfare Department, &amp; Food</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Safety</cell></row><row><cell>3.</cell><cell cols="3">NOC (Fire Safety Certificate)</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Fire &amp; Emergency Services</cell></row><row><cell>4.</cell><cell cols="4">Registration under Professional Tax</cell><cell cols="2">Finance Department</cell></row><row><cell>5.</cell><cell cols="3">Factory Registration / licensing</cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Directorate of Factories, Labor Dept.</cell></row><row><cell>6.</cell><cell cols="4">Registration of shops &amp; establishments</cell><cell cols="2">Labor Commissionerate, Labor Dept.</cell></row><row><cell>7.</cell><cell cols="2">Boiler registration</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Directorate of Boilers-Department of</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Labor Employment Training and</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Factories</cell></row><row><cell>8.</cell><cell cols="2">Fire License</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Fire &amp; Emergency Services</cell></row><row><cell>9.</cell><cell cols="2">Trade License</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Department Of Urban Development</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">and Municipal Affairs</cell></row><row><cell>10.</cell><cell cols="4">Registration of Establishment of Principal</cell><cell cols="2">Labor Commissionerate, Labor Dept.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Employer and Amendment of Certificate</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">of Registration under Contract Labour</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">(Regulation of Abolition) Act, 1970 and</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="3">Rules framed thereunder</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>11.</cell><cell cols="4">Registration of Establishment of Principal</cell><cell cols="2">Labor Commissionerate, Labor Dept.</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Employer and amendment of certificate of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Registration under the Inter-State</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Migrant Workmen (Regulation of</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Employment and Condition of Services)</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell cols="4">Act. 1979 and Rules framed thereunder</cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_14"><head>Table 11 : Regulatory mechanism for setting up of business S.No. Name of Service</head><label>11</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">Authority/ Agency/ Office/</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>Department</cell><cell>officer</cell><cell>granting</cell></row><row><cell>approval</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_15"><head>Major Players in Food Processing and Allied Sectors 8.1. Beneficiaries under PLI Scheme of MoFPI, Government of India (Operational Units) Table 12: Details of PLI beneficiaries Name of Scheme</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>8.2</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Beneficiary</cell><cell>Sector</cell><cell></cell><cell>District</cell><cell>Status</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Name</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>TATA</cell><cell>Fruits</cell><cell>&amp;</cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>CONSUMER</cell><cell>Vegetables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PRODUCTS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>TATA</cell><cell>Fruits</cell><cell>&amp;</cell><cell>Jalpaiguri</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>CONSUMER</cell><cell>Vegetables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PRODUCTS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>KEVENTER</cell><cell>Fruits</cell><cell>&amp;</cell><cell>Kolkata</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>AGRO LTD</cell><cell>Vegetables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>ITC LIMITED</cell><cell>Fruits</cell><cell>&amp;</cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Vegetables</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>ITC LIMITED</cell><cell>RTC/RTE</cell><cell></cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>ITC LIMITED</cell><cell>RTC/RTE</cell><cell></cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>PARLE</cell><cell>RTC/RTE</cell><cell></cell><cell>Jalpaiguri</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>BISCUITS PVT</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>LTD</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>PRATAAP</cell><cell>RTC/RTE</cell><cell></cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>SNACKS</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>PLISFPI</cell><cell>PARVATA</cell><cell>Category</cell><cell>2-</cell><cell>Darjeeling</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>FOODS</cell><cell>Organic</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>PRIVATE</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>LIMITED</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_16"><head>Beneficiaries under PMKSY Scheme of MoFPI, Government of India (Operational Units) as on 31 March, 2025 54</head><label></label><figDesc></figDesc><table /></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_17"><head>Table 13 : Mega Food Parks Scheme Name of the firm</head><label>13</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>Location</cell><cell>Product</cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_18"><head>Table 15 : Integrated Cold Chain and Value Addition Infrastructure</head><label>15</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>S.</cell><cell>Name of unit</cell><cell>Sector</cell><cell>Location</cell><cell>Status</cell></row><row><cell>No.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>1</cell><cell>Ascon Agro Products Exporters &amp;</cell><cell>F&amp;V</cell><cell>Hooghly</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Builders Pvt. Ltd.</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>2</cell><cell>KeventerAgro Ltd.</cell><cell>F&amp;V</cell><cell>North 24</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Paragnas</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>3</cell><cell>Prime Cold Stores Pvt. Ltd.</cell><cell>F&amp;V</cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>4</cell><cell>Basukinath Food Processors (P)</cell><cell>F&amp;V</cell><cell>Paschim</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ltd</cell><cell></cell><cell>Medinipur</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>5</cell><cell>Shimla Horticulture</cell><cell>F&amp;V</cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>6</cell><cell>Amicus Healthcare Services and</cell><cell>F&amp;V</cell><cell>South 24</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Solution Pvt. Ltd.</cell><cell></cell><cell>Paragnas</cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>7</cell><cell>Revati Commercial Pvt. Ltd</cell><cell>F&amp;V</cell><cell>Hooghly</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell>8</cell><cell>Megaa Moda Pvt. Ltd.</cell><cell>Marine &amp;</cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Fishery</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>9</cell><cell>NDM Sea Food Processors and</cell><cell>Marine &amp;</cell><cell>Hooghly</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Exporters Private Limited</cell><cell>Fishery</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>10</cell><cell>Shalimar Hatcheries Limited</cell><cell>Meat</cell><cell cols="2">Barddhaman Operational</cell></row><row><cell>11</cell><cell>Sagar Multipurpose Storage Pvt.</cell><cell>Marine &amp;</cell><cell>Howrah</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Ltd.</cell><cell>Fishery</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>12</cell><cell>Pasupati Aquatics Pvt Ltd</cell><cell>Marine &amp;</cell><cell>Medinipur</cell><cell>Operational</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Fishery</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row><row><cell>13</cell><cell>Poddar Projects Limited</cell><cell>Fishery</cell><cell>South 24</cell><cell>Under</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Parganas</cell><cell>Implementation</cell></row><row><cell>14</cell><cell>Mathurapur Agro India Private</cell><cell>Fishery</cell><cell>South 24</cell><cell>Under</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell>Limited (SC)</cell><cell></cell><cell>Parganas</cell><cell>Implementation</cell></row><row><cell>15</cell><cell>FOOD LOVERS Private Limited</cell><cell>Poultry</cell><cell>North 24</cell><cell>Under</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell>Parganas</cell><cell>Implementation</cell></row><row><cell>8.3</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell></row></table></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_19"><head>Beneficiaries under PMFME Table 16: Total assistance approved under PMFME -As on 31.05.2025 State/UT West Bengal</head><label></label><figDesc>total of 155 Farmer Producer Organizations (FPO) is present in the State of West Bengal and out of these the following indicative list represents FPOs with major crop/produce production of the state. The details of FPOs in the state are available at SFAC Farmer Connect FPO Directory 55 . (Refer to annexure)</figDesc><table><row><cell cols="2">10 List of Farmer Producer Organizations Annexures</cell></row><row><cell>Number of Micro Enterprises</cell><cell>212</cell></row><row><cell>Approved Subsidy (in Rs Crore)</cell><cell>12.42</cell></row><row><cell>Number of SHG Members</cell><cell>3238</cell></row><row><cell>Approved Subsidy (in Rs Crore)</cell><cell>10.91</cell></row><row><cell>Number of Approved Incubation Centre</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Approved Subsidy (in Rs Crore)</cell><cell>0.00</cell></row><row><cell>Number of Approved B&amp;M Projects</cell><cell>0</cell></row><row><cell>Approved Subsidy (in Rs Crore)</cell><cell>0.00</cell></row><row><cell>Net Enterprises-PMFME</cell><cell>3450</cell></row><row><cell>Total Subsidy under PMFME (in Rs Crore)</cell><cell>23.33</cell></row></table><note>A</note></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_20"><head>Table 17 : Indicative list of FPOs</head><label>17</label><figDesc></figDesc><table><row><cell>State</cell><cell>Name of District</cell><cell>Block</cell><cell>Name</cell><cell>CBBO</cell><cell>Name</cell><cell>FPO</cell></row><row><cell>West</cell><cell cols="2">Alipurduar Alipurduar II</cell><cell cols="2">Satmile Satish</cell><cell cols="2">Kayakhata</cell></row><row><cell>Bengal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Club "O"</cell><cell cols="2">Rabindra Farmers</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Pathagar</cell><cell cols="2">Producer</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Company Limited</cell></row><row><cell>West</cell><cell cols="2">Alipurduar Alipurduar I</cell><cell cols="2">Satmile Satish</cell><cell cols="2">Siru Bari Farmers</cell></row><row><cell>Bengal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Club "O"</cell><cell cols="2">Producer</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Pathagar</cell><cell cols="2">Company Limited</cell></row><row><cell>West</cell><cell cols="2">Alipurduar Falakat</cell><cell cols="2">Satmile Satish</cell><cell cols="2">Egiye Chalo</cell></row><row><cell>Bengal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Club "O"</cell><cell cols="2">Farmers Producer</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Pathagar</cell><cell cols="2">Company Limited</cell></row><row><cell>West</cell><cell cols="2">Alipurduar Kumargram</cell><cell cols="4">ShamayitaMath Dakhin Rampur</cell></row><row><cell>Bengal</cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Farmers Producer</cell></row><row><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell></cell><cell cols="2">Company Limited</cell></row></table></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_0">https://www.wbidc.com/assets/pdf/West-Bengal-Overview.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_1">https://rbidocs.rbi.org.in/rdocs/Publications/PDFs/HANDBOOK09122024426229B8B51C4BDE99607F1ADC64154A.PD F</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="7" xml:id="foot_2">https://morth.nic.in/sites/default/files/Basic%20Road%20Statistics%20of%20India-2019-20.pdf</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_3">https://www.rbi.org.in/Scripts/AnnualPublications.aspx?head=Handbook+of+Statistics+on+Indian+States | Exchange rate as 31 March 2024</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="52" xml:id="foot_4">Frontiers | Hilsa fisheries in India: a socio-economic analysis of fishers in deltaic Ganga region of river Hooghly</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="55" xml:id="foot_5">State wise list of registered FPOs details under Central Sector Scheme for Formation and Promotion of 10,000 FPOs by SFAC as on 24-02-2025.pdf</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="availability">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p>2 https://nriwestbengal.gov.in/nri/common/Agriculture.aspx 3 WBIDC 4 https://ipindia.gov.in/writereaddata/Portal/Images/pdf/GI_Application_Register_List_22-05-2023.pdf</p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Disclaimer</head><p>Without limiting the rights under the copyright reserved, this publication or any part of it may not be translated, reproduced, stored, transmitted in any form (electronic, mechanical, photocopying, audio recording or otherwise) or circulated in any binding or cover other than the cover in which it is currently published, without the prior written permission of MoFPI.</p><p>All information, ideas, views, opinions, estimates, advice, suggestions, and recommendations (hereinafter 'content') in this publication should not be understood as professional advice in any manner or interpreted as policies, objectives, opinions, or suggestions of Ernst &amp; Young LLP. Readers are advised to use their discretion and seek professional advice before taking any action or decision, based on the contents of this publication. The content in this publication has been obtained or derived from sources believed to be reliable but MoFPI does not represent this information to be accurate or complete. MoFPI does not assume any responsibility and disclaim any liability or any loss, or damages caused due to any reason whatsoever, towards any person (natural or legal) who uses this publication. This publication cannot be sold for consideration, within or outside India, without written permission of MoFPI. Violation of this condition of sale will lead to criminal and civil prosecution.</p><p>Copyright ©Ministry of Food Processing Industries, Government of India. </p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl/>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
